<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes of a Journey taken by Elisha Tyson &amp; James Gillingham on a Visit
                    to some Indians in the neighbourhood of Fort Wayne: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Susanna Morikawa</name>

                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>

            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca.  KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_JG_1808</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Journals</collection>
                        <idno>Mss</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p> pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p> Native Americans and Quakers </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of this book, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases.
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>




                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>
                        <item>Indiana -- Description and travel</item>
                        <item>Ohio -- Description and travel</item>



                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016"/></item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="1"/>
                <head>Notes of a Journey taken by Elisha Tyson &amp; James Gillingham on a Visit
                    to some Indians in the neighbourhood of Fort Wayne</head>
                <p>We set out from Baltimore the 4th of<lb/>the 4 mo 1808. Rode to poplar spring
                    &amp; Lodged</p>
                <p>5th Rode this Day to Middletown &amp; about<lb/>five OClock we put up for the
                    Night at<lb/>the Sign of Genrl. Washington kept by Gas<lb/>-per Herring. the
                    entertainment good of the<lb/>[delete: Fa] House orderly -- We were much
                    delighted<lb/>with the Country between the Catocktin &amp;<lb/>&amp; South
                    Mountains &amp; thought the <lb/>appearance quite equal to that in
                    the<lb/>neighborhood of Fredericktown [delete]<lb/>the Village we are now
                    resting in has<lb/>a very neat &amp; agreeable appearance<lb/>&amp; appears to
                    be in thriving condition several new<lb/>Brickhouses having been lately
                    built<lb/>&amp; more are Building.</p>
                <p>[page 2]</p>
                <p>6th &amp; 4th of the Week set out from Middletown<lb/>Intending to breakfast at
                    Boonsborough but<lb/>taking the wrong road we breakfasted at<lb/>a house on the
                    sheppard town road after<lb/>breakfast we changed our rout &amp; made<lb/>for
                    Williamsport which after losing our <lb/>selves &amp; going several miles out of
                    our way rea<lb/>-ched about 2 oClock &amp; dine afterwards <lb/>rode 8 miles to
                    Daniel Herboin's where<lb/>we are now laid by for the night. our
                    re-<lb/>flections were excited on passing the<lb/>conochocheage Valley a Valley
                    perhaps in<lb/>-ferior to none in the Luxuriance of the <lb/>Soil but the
                    comparison in the tillage<lb/>with the Valley we passed yesterday is <lb/>as
                    much in favour of the former -- as there<lb/>is difference between that
                    cultivated <lb/>by neat Dutch Farmers &amp; that by <lb/>negro Drivers the tints
                    of Distress &amp;<lb/>Slavery being generally observable<lb/>in our rout this
                    Day. our landlord has <lb/>a Spring Issueing from under his house<lb/>which
                    turns a mill about 50 yards <lb/>below where it rises --</p>
                <p>[page 3]</p>
                <p>7th &amp; 5th of the Week Rode 7 miles to<lb/>Hunters. Breakfasted, thence to
                    Hancock<lb/>10 miles dined. &amp; Proceeded to 15 Mile creek<lb/>distance 16
                    Miles whole distance this day 33 miles<lb/>our observations this day not
                    generally of the<lb/>Most agreeable kind the latter part of the <lb/>Day passed
                    several very high hills which<lb/>made our Journey tiresome.</p>
                <p>8th proceeded, breakfasted on the Hills, then<lb/>to old town dined
                    &amp;proceeded to Cumberland<lb/>where we lodged at John Rines a good
                    House<lb/>and attentive landlord the Valley's or Bottoms<lb/>along the River
                    very rich &amp; produce Corn &amp;<lb/>Grass in abundance thousands of
                    Bushels<lb/>now lying in the Fields having we suppose<lb/>just been cut in the
                    Fall &amp; set up in rounds<lb/>Shocks in the same form that we set up
                    corn<lb/>tops --</p>
                <p>9th Staid at Cumberland until <lb/>about 3 oClock rode abut 10 miles<lb/>&amp;
                    lodged at Houtzmans [delete: next day] in a <lb/>Valley of God's Land about 30
                    miles<lb/>we were informed in length</p>
                <p>[page 4]</p>
                <p>10th of the month &amp; 1st of the week<lb/>rode about 20 miles to Browns
                    the<lb/>rode Bad &amp; have had snow ever<lb/>since we ascended the
                    mountains<lb/>until within a few miles of this place</p>
                <p>11th. A Storm of Wind &amp; rain coming on<lb/>Last night still Continues
                    about<lb/>3 oClock set out &amp; Crossed the<lb/>Youghigania rode 15 miles to
                    Clarks<lb/>the weather warm toward Evening<lb/>with thunder &amp; some rain met
                    a <lb/>decent look woman alone in a desolate<lb/>place in the Gust - some miles
                    from any<lb/>House in search of a Stray Horse<lb/>had come about 30 miles &amp;
                    proceeding<lb/>we pitied her &amp; went on to Clarkes<lb/>where we Lodged</p>
                <p>12th Rode to Jonas Cattles where we<lb/>were kindly entertained</p>
                <p>13th Set out accompanied by Jonas crossed<lb/>the Monongahela at Crawford &amp;
                    rode</p>
                <p>[page 5]</p>
                <p>to Henry Mills &amp; staid the night following<lb/>had a conference with Friends
                    &amp; David<lb/>Grave concluded to meet us at conc<lb/>-ord on first Day</p>
                <p>14th set out early rode to washington<lb/>where we dined we were much
                    pleased<lb/>with the redstone country the people<lb/>appear to live well &amp;
                    the Land produces<lb/>abundantly</p>
                <p>[detete: then] Rode [delete: from David Henry Mills?]<lb/>to Alexandria &amp;
                    Lodged</p>
                <p>15th Rode to wheelen mostly along wheeler <lb/>Creek through some Beautiful
                    Bottoms<lb/>&amp; passed some elegant Houses &amp; Mills<lb/>at Wheelen we
                    lodged at Josiah Updegr<lb/>-aff, visited Richard Carter &amp;
                    Ebenezer<lb/>Zanes --</p>
                <p>2nd Day the 18th Crossed the River<lb/>&amp; went home with horton Howard<lb/>the
                    Same Evening I went in Com<lb/>-pany with David Grave to Jon'n<lb/>Taylors next
                    Day being short Creek<lb/>Monthly Meeting -- after meeting<lb/>Dined in Company
                    with Geo. &amp; Mary</p>
                <p/>
                <p>[page 6]</p>
                <p>Kinsey at Jonathan Taylors<lb/>in the evening I went home <lb/>with my Brother
                    and Sister --</p>
                <p>20th went to Concord monthly meeting<lb/>where I meet Elisha who has
                    remained<lb/>at Horton Howards expecting his Company<lb/>on our route. we dined
                    at Burden<lb/>Stantons after which we returned to<lb/>Horton's &amp; found him
                    resolved not to<lb/>accompany us therefore the Lot fell<lb/>upon david &amp; we
                    concluded to set <lb/>out next morning.</p>
                <p>21 we set out early &amp; rode to Joseph<lb/>Vanlaws at Plainfield David in
                    the<lb/>mean time seemed tho in company<lb/>undetermined whether to go or
                    not<lb/>but concluded to accompany us about<lb/>4 miles farther when he would
                    either<lb/>leave us or conclude to go on when<lb/>we came to the place he
                    concluded<lb/>to proceed. we went on about 3 miles<lb/>&amp; lodged.</p>
                <p>[page 7]</p>
                <p>22 The morning very fine &amp; some while<lb/>Fresh [?] we proceeded being in
                    good spirits<lb/>concluded to reach the muskingum<lb/>40 miles which he effected
                    about Sun<lb/>setting &amp; put up at Taylors Tavern</p>
                <p>The lands since we crossed the Ohio<lb/>have been generally good mostly
                    very<lb/>rich in the neighbourhood of Short<lb/>Creek &amp; concord &amp;
                    continued so until<lb/>we got to plainfield where they <lb/>became inferior in
                    Quality tho good<lb/>Farming Land farther on we found <lb/>the Bottoms on the
                    Several Branches of<lb/>wills Creek to be very extensive &amp; the<lb/>upland
                    'tho Hilly pretty good for some <lb/>miles before we reached the
                    muskingum<lb/>the Land was level &amp; of an Inferior<lb/>quality thus [?]which
                    the roads were<lb/>excellent -- Zane Ville on one side &amp;<lb/>Springfield on
                    the other of the muskin<lb/>-gum show what can be expected in <lb/>a few Years
                    by enterprizing people<lb/>being both considerable Villages</p>
                <p>[page 8]</p>
                <p>in Zanes Ville alone there are 7 or 8<lb/>Taverns kept in respectable Houses
                    the<lb/>Best Buildings are over the river <lb/>spring Field where there is
                    one<lb/>three Story of Brick which would not<lb/>disgrace the best street in
                    Baltimore</p>
                <p>24th Rode from Zanesville to Bubb's &amp; lodged then to Lancaster<lb/>through
                    alterable County near Lancaster<lb/>the lands are of prime Quality -- we staid
                    <lb/>that night at Lancaster next morning<lb/>set out &amp; Rode to websters
                    within<lb/>about 5 Miles of Chilicothe</p>
                <p>27 Rode to Chilicothe &amp; breakfasted &amp;<lb/>being discouraged by the repot
                    of the<lb/>Water being high we staid until about<lb/>10 OClock being informed we
                    could not<lb/>Cross the North fork of Paint Creek<lb/>we rode up it to old
                    Chilicothe<lb/>where the same impediment contd--<lb/>we continued on 3 miles</p>
                <p>[page 9]</p>
                <p>to John Hopkinsons where got across<lb/>but had to take an upper rode
                    &amp;<lb/>Lodged at a house where we Lodged<lb/>Partly on the floor before the
                    fire &amp;<lb/>Part in a bed. no hay to be had<lb/>early next 28th we set out
                    &amp; rode<lb/>through Prairie after Prairie until<lb/>the whole County except
                    some<lb/>Small pieces of upland intervening<lb/>become Prairies &amp; so cont
                    thro this days rout<lb/>wading thro the mud &amp; not being <lb/>able to get
                    feed for our Horses we rode<lb/>near 40 Miles to one Township [?]<lb/>where we
                    found plenty of the<lb/>necessaries of Life. the Country<lb/>here is very good.
                    with excellent<lb/>Bottom &amp; upland the Prairies we<lb/>have passed are
                    mostly rich but there<lb/>is so little timber in many parts that<lb/>they can
                    hardly be enclosed with Fences so</p>
                <p>[p 10]</p>
                <p>that if the country is ever settled<lb/>they must be ditched</p>
                <p>29th we staid until near noon when<lb/>we set out &amp; Rode about 12 Miles
                    to<lb/>wolf's tavern where we were well enter-<lb/>tained, through the course of
                    the Day<lb/>we passed the little Miamia a small<lb/>stream at a mill it was
                    enclosed in<lb/>a narrow stone gutter which contd<lb/>narrow with a great fall
                    the Chasm<lb/>increased in depth until we supposed<lb/>it was 50 feet deep &amp;
                    about 20 feet <lb/>wide at the top in about 6 miles<lb/>we passed the Yellow
                    spring it<lb/>was large &amp; proceeded out of a Lime<lb/>-stone Rock. &amp;
                    tinged [delete: the] every thing<lb/>with a deep yellow with a
                    strong<lb/>sulphurious taste &amp; is much resorted<lb/>to in the summer season
                    for health</p>
                <p>30th set out early &amp; rode to dayton <lb/>thro some excellent land</p>
                <p>[p. 11]</p>
                <p>at this Considerable Village which stands<lb/>Just below the Junction of a Mad
                    River with<lb/>the great Miami we breakfasted at Rapids an Excellent House &amp;
                    staid<lb/>until about 12 OClock when we started<lb/>&amp; rode about 12 Miles to
                    one French's<lb/>in the woods where we were entertained<lb/>with much
                    satisfaction only we could <lb/>get no hay for our Horses we have still<lb/>had
                    &amp; this night excellent good clean<lb/>Feather Beds to lie in</p>
                <p>5 mo 1st We rode to Stanton a small <lb/>new Town on the great Miami
                    and<lb/>Intend staying here until we can ac-<lb/>-comodate ourselves with a Man
                    to<lb/>go with us &amp; provide ourselves with<lb/>Grain for our Horses &amp;
                    provisions for our<lb/>-selves, the lands in this rout are of <lb/>an Excellent
                    Quality with a very Large <lb/>growth of Timber interspersed with
                    abun<lb/>-dance of Poplar but for some miles near<lb/>Stanton the Growth of
                    Timber is of Rich<lb/>kind &amp; not very useful except the Walnut</p>
                <p>[ p. 12]</p>
                <p>we have put up at a French Man's<lb/>Called Felix we had letters from<lb/>Dayton
                    to Judge Gerards who was<lb/>kind and attentive in procuring<lb/>a suitable man
                    to go with us, there<lb/>was a young man from Virginia at<lb/>this place of the
                    name of Lowell [?] [delete: Crawford]<lb/>who was very kind &amp; the Land
                    low<lb/>having no Hay he furnished us with <lb/>some of his own freely without
                    So-<lb/>-licitation &amp; would not take pay for<lb/>it. I wish we may make him
                    compen<lb/>-sation when in our power</p>
                <p>5 mo 2nd Still at Stanton the Weather<lb/>rainy &amp; endeavoured to procure a
                    suitable<lb/>person to go with us &amp; provision on<lb/>the way we agreed with
                    a man to<lb/>go &amp; also with with a Woman to bake <lb/>some biscuits &amp;
                    boil us a ham &amp;<lb/>intend setting out tomorrow morn-<lb/>-ing with our
                    Guide.</p>
                <p>[p. 13]</p>
                <p>3rd- our man came this morning &amp;<lb/>begged to be excused alledging
                    that<lb/>both himself &amp; his Horse were too weak<lb/>-ly so we admitted his
                    excuse &amp;<lb/>discharged him. Court began here<lb/>to day &amp; it rained so
                    much that <lb/>we concluded the waters would be<lb/>impassable &amp; meeting
                    with a Man of <lb/>the name of thatcher who agreed<lb/>to go with us we sent our
                    Horse<lb/>by him about 16 miles to his Feed House<lb/>He living on our road at
                    the First Crossing of Loramie &amp; to be<lb/>ready to advance with us at
                    any<lb/>time when we should come forward<lb/>seeing but little prospect of
                    getting<lb/>forward &amp; our inn much crowded<lb/>we went home with
                    Benjamin<lb/>Iddings to [delete: on] Still water where we<lb/>were kindly
                    entertained</p>
                <p>4th Day went with the Family<lb/>about one mile to their weekly</p>
                <p>[p. 14]</p>
                <p>Meeting. which is an Indulged Meeting<lb/>[delete: of about] &amp; a branch of
                    Still water or<lb/>West Branch Monthly Meeting &amp; consists of about<lb/>30
                    Families Still water Meeting being<lb/>about 6 miles lower down the River</p>
                <p>5th Still rainy &amp; no prospect of<lb/>of Proceeding David Graves went<lb/>over
                    the River to Still Water Meeting<lb/>&amp; tho' I wished to go with him yet
                    as<lb/>the River could not be crossed<lb/>without swimming I failed<lb/>&amp;
                    went about a mile to a black-<lb/>-smiths to get my Horse shod</p>
                <p>6 Still raining we stay here<lb/>&amp; the waters so high that we can<lb/>-not go
                    forward --</p>
                <p>7th --weather Clear but the<lb/>water so high we cannot move</p>
                <p>8th. being First Day we went to<lb/>meeting with the Family the Meeting<lb/>House
                    so small that it will not hold<lb/>above one half of the members</p>
                <p>[p. 15]</p>
                <p>But were informed that they propose<lb/>dividing the Meeting &amp; Building 2
                    new<lb/>houses this summer one on each side <lb/>of the River having often met
                    with<lb/>Difficulty in crossing still water --</p>
                <p>2nd Day morning Benjamin Iddings<lb/>proposed setting out with us
                    having<lb/>victuals provided we set out early<lb/>&amp; Rode to Thatcher's 18
                    miles Crossed<lb/>Loramies Creek &amp; a large Branch of<lb/>the great Miami
                    riding thro it being<lb/>about the saddle skirts. after Staying<lb/>sometime we
                    set out in company with<lb/>thatcher &amp; rode to Flins swimming<lb/>our Horses
                    across the second Crossing<lb/>of Loramies Creek where we put up<lb/>for the
                    Night &amp; slept on the Floors<lb/>The land this Day mostly good tho'<lb/>much
                    of it is too flat to settle on<lb/>before we reached thatchers we
                    passed<lb/>several miles thro' the woods where the <lb/>the trees were lined
                    with Pigeons nests [?]<lb/>some times 20 or thirty in one tree</p>
                <p>[p. 16]</p>
                <p>10th. we set out early &amp; Rode to Murrays<lb/>at the first crossing of the St.
                    Mary's<lb/>it being a branch of that River we<lb/>rode thro without much
                    difficulty<lb/>after feeding our Horses at Murrays<lb/>&amp; getting a rough
                    repast /I having<lb/>lost our own provisions bag &amp; all on <lb/>the Road, we
                    proceed to Stephen Youngs<lb/>18 Miles to the 2nd. Crossings of the St.
                    Marys<lb/>where we lodged early next morning<lb/>we set out Swimming our
                    Horses<lb/>across the River which being very<lb/>full was run out into the
                    Bottoms<lb/>so that we had to ride a good way<lb/>thro the water, riding on it
                    began<lb/>to rain so that that we had no<lb/>Choice but to ride 40 miles
                    thro<lb/>a very swampy Country. almost an<lb/>entire level &amp; one swamp so
                    dark that<lb/>we got thro with difficulty &amp; alarms in<lb/>passing which
                    Elisha Tyson lost his <lb/>hat which his Horse trode in the <lb/>mud ---</p>
                <p>[p. 17]</p>
                <p>not one House in the whole distance<lb/>we arrived at Fort wayne in
                    the<lb/>evening wet &amp; tired &amp; put up at <lb/>a French Tavern after we
                    arrived<lb/>John Johnston Indian Factor came<lb/>&amp; invited two of us to his
                    house Elisha <lb/>went with him &amp; the rest of staid at <lb/>the Tavern</p>
                <p>11th we all went to Johnstons where<lb/>we staid some time &amp; then went to
                    the<lb/>Fort &amp; dined with Captain Heald<lb/>who with the other officers were
                    very<lb/>kind &amp; attentive we spent the evening<lb/>in consulting about the
                    execution of <lb/>our Mission &amp; concluded to invite the<lb/>Indians to come
                    to the Fort for consulta-<lb/>-tion &amp; after night had a Conference <lb/>with
                    some of the Potowatomy Indians<lb/>Winnemak a Chief informed us<lb/>that he had
                    been with the president<lb/>who had Promised him that he would<lb/>send some
                    tools &amp; young men to teach <lb/>them to Farm but had not done
                    there-<lb/>-fore he was deceived</p>
                <p>[p. 18]</p>
                <p>that he had set his mind upon it &amp; was much <lb/>disappointed &amp; we found
                    it very difficult<lb/>to remove he prejudices we stated that<lb/>William Kirk
                    had come to their country<lb/>last spring with an intention of assit-<lb/>ing
                    them but that the Potowatomies<lb/>and Miamies had refused to receive
                    him<lb/>&amp; that he had to return back to the <lb/>Shawenesse but he said that
                    he had <lb/>received no account of his being here<lb/>&amp; so had not refused
                    him &amp; throught<lb/>that he can been neglected.</p>
                <p>the country around Fort wayne is not<lb/>of the First Quality [deleted: yet] but
                    on the<lb/>other side of the River the land is<lb/>good the situation of the
                    Fort is<lb/>pleasant &amp; the prospect pretty<lb/>good considering the flatness
                    of the<lb/>Country Elisha &amp; myself lodged <lb/>at Johnstons &amp; the others
                    at the <lb/>Tavern</p>
                <p>[p. 19]</p>
                <p>[deleted paragraph:</p>
                <p>We had conversation with Winnemak<lb/>a Chief of the Potowatomy
                    Nation<lb/>residing on the Peconoe River he told <lb/>us that the President of
                    the united States<lb/>had promised him that he would give<lb/>him assistance in
                    the Cultivation<lb/>of his lands &amp; that he had disappointed <lb/>him in not
                    sending the assistance<lb/>promised]</p>
                <p>We staid at Fort Wayne until First day<lb/>morning the 15th when David Grave
                    &amp; my-<lb/>-self set out for Dennis's Station Elisha<lb/>Tyson having been
                    taken with the Rheu-<lb/>-matism was bled and Blistered &amp; not<lb/>in a
                    situation to ride on acct of the <lb/>soreness of his Blister tho' the pain
                    <lb/>was removed we had concluded<lb/>to call the Indians together in 9
                    <lb/>Days at Fort Wayne &amp; had sent<lb/>an Indian to the Five Medals
                    town<lb/>to give Information &amp; John<lb/>Flin Interpreter for</p>
                <p>[p. 20]</p>
                <p>John Johnston was to accompany us<lb/>to Dennis Station &amp;
                    Massasinneway<lb/>but after Crossing the River to William<lb/>Wallis's he could
                    not Find his<lb/>Horse so we proceeded on &amp; he was <lb/>to overtake us if
                    could get<lb/>his Horse, but we arrived there<lb/>alone &amp; John Flin came
                    there<lb/>in the evening &amp; lodged with us<lb/>at Shaw Griffiths</p>
                <p>16 David's Horse having failed <lb/>we received acct that the <lb/>Massasinians
                    were drunk &amp; killing <lb/>one another we let John go with<lb/>-out us.
                    Elisha &amp; Benjamin Iddings <lb/>arrived in Company with William<lb/>Wells
                    about 3 OClock, Elisha was<lb/>very much overcome with the Jour-<lb/>-ney</p>
                <p>17th - We Walked to the upper Village<lb/>this morning visited the White loon</p>
                <p>[ p. 21]</p>
                <p>The Principal Chief and some others &amp;<lb/>had some conversation with them
                    &amp;<lb/>returned in the afternoon we went down<lb/>the River about half a mile
                    below <lb/>Dennis's Station &amp; visited the Eel River<lb/>Indians The Indians
                    at both these <lb/>Villages live in tolerable log houses<lb/>Which were
                    generally built by Wells<lb/>out of their annuities the amt of<lb/>the Whole
                    Population of these Villages<lb/>with Dennis's Station being about
                    300<lb/>Tomorrow we have appointed to see the<lb/>Indians together--</p>
                <p>18th we heard this morning that several <lb/>of the Indians of the Lower Village
                    were<lb/>drinking which has a disagreeable feeling<lb/>to us but hope they will
                    not Interrupt us<lb/>in Council to day -- abut 12 OClock we<lb/>met with the
                    Indians of the upper and Lower<lb/>Villages &amp; also those at Dennis's Station
                    to<lb/>whom we read the address (that was to have<lb/>been taken out by John
                    Shaw &amp; Griffith &amp; found<lb/>by us at Red Stone it having been to late in
                    get-<lb/>-ting out) William Welles being Interpreter </p>
                <p>[p. 22]</p>
                <p>Some observations were also communicated<lb/>by Elisha Tyson &amp; David Grave to
                    all which<lb/>they gave their assent as is customary<lb/>after Which the White
                    loon made a Short Speech<lb/>acknowledging the propriety of what had<lb/>been
                    said &amp; observed that as they expected to<lb/>attend the Council at Fort
                    Wayne where <lb/>a more pointed reply would be necessary<lb/>he thought it
                    superfluous to say much<lb/>at that time the Indians generally made<lb/>a pretty
                    good appearance &amp; some had on<lb/>very costly dresses. we returned to our
                    young<lb/>mens Habitation &amp; Dined upon Beef killed<lb/>the Evening before by
                    the Indians it was <lb/>said partly on our account they manifested<lb/>respect
                    for us &amp; partly good decorum at the<lb/>time of our counselling together</p>
                <p>We observe few or any of the young men<lb/>at labour &amp; it appears doubtful
                    whether<lb/>the present generation of young men will<lb/>apply themselves to
                    Labour prejudice &amp;<lb/>their habits of ease &amp; Indulgence being<lb/>to
                    deeply Rooted in their minds</p>
                <p>[ p. 23]</p>
                <p>Shaw &amp; Griffith were preparing Ground for<lb/>Planting Corn the weather had
                    been so wet<lb/>for sometime back that the Ground could not<lb/>be plowed to
                    advantage. the land Cleared<lb/>at these Villages is about 100 Acres they
                    have<lb/>about 120 Horse kind &amp; about 50 Horned<lb/>Cattle &amp; a good many
                    Hogs the want of<lb/>mas last Winter proved fatal to abundance <lb/>of Swine I
                    do not find that Friends have<lb/>any Hogs at the Station the land here<lb/>as
                    well for 200 Miles down this River is<lb/>Excellent &amp; would admit of
                    settlements suf-<lb/>-ficient for all the Indians on this side the
                    <lb/>Missisippi &amp; is Navigable up the little River for Boats about<lb/>20
                    Miles above this which is connected by <lb/>a portage of about 8 miles with the
                    St. Mary<lb/>a branch of the Miami of the Lake<lb/>the main Stream navigable
                    many miles Higher<lb/>We viewed the Mill Seat at Dennis<lb/>Station on the River
                    which we pronounced<lb/>a good one also Dennis's Creek a Large<lb/>Branch but
                    pronounced in favour of <lb/>the River Mill the Branch failing <lb/>in the
                    Summer</p>
                <p><lb/>[p. 24]</p>
                <p>the Weather has been fine for 2 Days past but<lb/>this Evening has a threatning
                    aspect so that it<lb/>looks quite likely that we must either be
                    detained<lb/>here or ride in the Rain tomorrow as usual<lb/>the young men have
                    been handing out the <lb/>corn to such as were in want but some of
                    the<lb/>Indians having exprest their dissatisfaction<lb/>we directed them to
                    give all the Corn they had<lb/>to the Indians to be divided by them as
                    they<lb/>saw meet &amp; a thought suggested itself to us<lb/>that it would be as
                    well for whoever should<lb/>be stationed here to spend the chief of their
                    <lb/>time in assisting &amp; Instructing the Indians<lb/>Instead of Raising Corn
                    to be given away</p>
                <p>In the Evening the Chiefs of the Villages<lb/>the White Loon of the upper Village
                    from <lb/>Massisiniway &amp; Charley Chief of the Eel <lb/>River Indians at the
                    lower Village &amp; some <lb/>of their Principal Indians attended<lb/>&amp; we
                    delivered them a pipe after having taken<lb/>taken a fraternal smoke &amp; had
                    some<lb/>Friendly Conversation on the subject <lb/>of our Mission Capt Welles
                    has been<lb/>our Interpreter</p>
                <p>[p 25]</p>
                <p>We were busy this Morning in making<lb/>an early Start in order to reach the
                    Turtle<lb/>town on our way to Fort Wayne but rain<lb/>coming on &amp; it being
                    only a path thro<lb/>thick bushes in places we concluded<lb/>to lie by until
                    Morning. in the Evening<lb/>it came on a Gust with Thunder &amp;
                    heavy<lb/>rain</p>
                <p>20th - upon Consultation this Morning<lb/>we concluded it would be very
                    difficult<lb/>for us to get to Turtle Town on acct<lb/>of the Waters being high
                    so sent<lb/>John Flin. J. Johnstons interpreter<lb/>to give the Little Turtle
                    notice of<lb/>Time of our meeting &amp; invite him &amp;<lb/>we proceeded to
                    Fort Wayne we ar-<lb/>rived at W. Wells's about 3 oClock<lb/>Benjamin Iddings
                    &amp; myself staid<lb/>at Wells's &amp; Elisha went over to the <lb/>Fort to
                    Johnstons</p>
                <p>[p 26]</p>
                <p>David Grave's Mare being sick staid at<lb/>Dennis's Station intending to come
                    on<lb/>first day to the Fort in Company with<lb/>John Shaw</p>
                <p>21st - Breakfasted this morning with Wells<lb/>walked about &amp; Viewed the
                    Plantion which<lb/>is a very Good one it &amp; the neighbour-<lb/>-hood has been
                    formerly the Great<lb/>Village of the Miami Indians the<lb/>Elavation of the
                    Corn Hills is quite<lb/>Visible also the Indian Graves they have<lb/>been buried
                    single in the same manner<lb/>that we bury &amp; there is some graves<lb/>near
                    Wells's House of Indians that have<lb/>been recently buried over one of
                    their<lb/>Chiefs stands a pole with a white flag<lb/>opposite Wells plantion
                    over the River<lb/>St. Joseph we were shewn the Ground<lb/>where Genral Harmer
                    was defeated<lb/>&amp; where many of his men fell in<lb/>Crossing the River it
                    was in a large<lb/>Priarie which would make a beautiful<lb/>Plantion.</p>
                <p>[p. 27]</p>
                <p>being Clear land for a great Extent<lb/>I suppose at least one thousand
                    acres<lb/>Wells's Plantation lies in the fork of<lb/>the Mary &amp; Joseph
                    Rivers which<lb/>come together before they arrive at the<lb/>Fort the stream
                    then takes the name <lb/>of the Miami of the lakes &amp; Runs about<lb/>North
                    east the Joseph runs about <lb/>N.W. &amp; the Mary about South West
                    --<lb/>there is plenty of fish in the River of the<lb/>Cat Bass &amp; Perch
                    &amp; Pickerel &amp; Sheeps head<lb/>&amp;c -- we were Examining some of the
                    goods<lb/>in Johnstons Store they are many of <lb/>them of the most Indifferent
                    in Quality <lb/>Rifles very Indifferent in Quallitty as is<lb/>the hoes without.
                    Steel -- traps by the <lb/>Hundred not worth Six pence per <lb/>piece in Short
                    it appears that if<lb/>more attention is not paid to the<lb/>Selection of Goods
                    for the Indian<lb/>department, our Credit in that<lb/>quarter will be done &amp;
                    the Indians<lb/>will endeavor to trade with</p>
                <p>[p. 28]</p>
                <p>the British this [deletion] we apprehend Judges think<lb/>that ten or Fifteen
                    Thousand Dollars<lb/>might be saved annually if care<lb/>was taken so as to send
                    nothing here<lb/>but what was of good quality. &amp;<lb/>otherwise suitable for
                    this market</p>
                <p>22nd this morning being first day there<lb/>there is a smart frost which will be
                    <lb/>pretty hard upon the Gardens &amp; tender<lb/>Vegetables the Fruit
                    doubtless will<lb/>Suffer -- we went over to W. Wells's to<lb/>dine in Company
                    with J. Johnston &amp;<lb/>the Officers of the Garrison &amp; the
                    Doctor<lb/>where we had a Decent Dinner &amp;<lb/>very good decorum the officers
                    &amp; Doctor<lb/>with Johnston are all young Men<lb/>&amp; appear to be of sober
                    deportment not<lb/>one of them [delete: but] given to Intemperance<lb/>in short
                    we have been much pleased <lb/>&amp; disappointed to find such Characters<lb/>in
                    the Military professions</p>
                <p>[p. 29]</p>
                <p>Several of the Indians made their appear-<lb/>-ance &amp; one of they call
                    Wapakee called<lb/>by the french Maupauk the most Gigantic<lb/>Savage looking
                    Indian that we have <lb/>yet seen he is of the Potowatomy &amp;<lb/>Sioux Nation
                    mixed he was the chief<lb/>who took the 40 Osages prisiners which<lb/>the United
                    States lately redeemed at<lb/>a very great expense the Osages<lb/>have lately
                    killed ten of Sioux &amp;<lb/>five of the Delaware &amp; he is treath-<lb/>-ing
                    vengance against them. he has his<lb/>men he says ready &amp; can stay but
                    <lb/>a short time with us but must meet<lb/>them to go against the Osages &amp;
                    it is<lb/>thought that it will not be possible<lb/>to turn him from his purpose
                    we<lb/>dread his company in Council as he<lb/>does not appear to have any
                    more<lb/>Idea of Civilization than the <lb/>Bears in the Woods he puts<lb/>me in
                    mind of some of the</p>
                <p>[p. 30]</p>
                <p>Antient Giants perhaps Hercules him-<lb/>-self may be pretty well
                    Identified<lb/>in his Person &amp; War club he has<lb/>but one hand &amp; yet
                    they say there <lb/>is not one Indian in the Country<lb/>that the Indians fear
                    so much as <lb/>they do this man -- the five Medals<lb/>&amp; White Loon are
                    here. the little Turtle has<lb/>the Gout or Rheumatism &amp; is
                    hardly<lb/>expected here the prospect is avery <lb/>dull one as we are informed
                    that the<lb/>Turtle &amp; five medals are our ene-<lb/>-mies &amp; will oppose
                    us. The two Chiefs<lb/>at the Wabash, the White Loon for the <lb/>Masseseneway
                    Indians , &amp; Charley for the<lb/>Eel River Indians, I believe are <lb/>both
                    Friendly &amp; if it was not for the<lb/>undue influence that some bad
                    Cha-<lb/>racters have over them &amp; the love of<lb/>Whiskey they might in time
                    be brought<lb/>into some degree of Civilization</p>
                <p>[p. 31]</p>
                <p>23. This being the day we had appointed<lb/>for to hold a Council with the
                    Indians<lb/>&amp; many of them were Collected over the river<lb/>we were engaged
                    in preparing such<lb/>communications to them as we thought<lb/>advisible but to
                    our great Mortification<lb/>we were informed that the son of the<lb/>Five medals
                    had returned from Stanton<lb/>where he had been with several men<lb/>&amp;
                    Horses to purchase whiskey with a <lb/>Large quantity &amp; that the Indians
                    here<lb/>collected had got to drinking it &amp;<lb/>were many of them drunk so
                    that the<lb/>prospect looks gloomy &amp; that all our<lb/>toil will be of no
                    avail</p>
                <p>24 The contractor showed us this morn-<lb/>-ing that in the month of April
                    last<lb/>there was delivered by order of the<lb/>Indian agent 1117 Rations of
                    Whiskey<lb/>or about 35 Gallons The Contractor<lb/>informed us that he offered
                    to furnish<lb/>William kirk when in Friends employ<lb/>[delete] Flour at $6 per
                    [Cut?]</p>
                <p>[p. 32]</p>
                <p>The Indians are still drunk &amp; little<lb/>prospect of doing any business
                    with<lb/>them about nine o Clock the Indians that<lb/>had come in came together
                    except Wapa-<lb/>-kee who was too drunk the five Medals was so<lb/>much
                    intoxicated with divers others,<lb/>that we concluded it would not do<lb/>to
                    pretend to treat with them &amp; but<lb/>just to come together &amp; inform
                    them<lb/>that we were sorry that they had been<lb/>drinking so much as to be
                    unfit to talk<lb/>with at Present but would meet<lb/>them tomorrow morning when
                    if they<lb/>were still drunk we would go away<lb/>without having any public talk
                    with<lb/>them -- The five Medals made reply<lb/>that we might speak, as the
                    Potowa-<lb/>-tomies were the only people that<lb/>were drunk &amp; that they
                    were sober<lb/>enough to listen to what we</p>
                <p><lb/>[p. 33]</p>
                <p>had to say but did not wish to answer<lb/>&amp; that they could go home tomorrow
                    &amp; did<lb/>not care whether they heard what we have <lb/>to say or not. &amp;
                    told Elisha that he<lb/>was no Great Chief &amp; therefore did<lb/>wrong to tell
                    the Indians that we<lb/>would not treat with them if they were
                    drunk<lb/>tomorrow when after a little more talk<lb/>we separated to meet again
                    tomorrow<lb/>-- morning--</p>
                <p>25th the morning pleasant &amp; the sun<lb/>Shining which has not been a
                    very<lb/>common thing [delete] here lately we have<lb/>had 2 very severe frosts
                    within these few day<lb/>past which has killed many things<lb/>even the Potatoes
                    are killed to the very<lb/>ground the Beans &amp;c killed fairly we wish<lb/>to
                    set out as we begin to fear the flies<lb/>The Indians assembled this
                    morning<lb/>[delete] there was but few of the Chiefs<lb/>present</p>
                <p>[p. 34]</p>
                <p>We read the address of the Committee to<lb/>them. also the Turtles &amp; five
                    Medals speeches<lb/>upon the subject of Civilization after wards<lb/>was readd
                    an address of our own with<lb/>the Turtles speech upon spirituous
                    Liquors<lb/>they were mostly interpreted into the<lb/>Miami &amp; Potowatomy
                    Languages --<lb/>by William Wells for the Miami &amp; John<lb/>Flinn for the
                    Potowatomy after which<lb/>we went to dinner with Captain<lb/>Heald &amp; left
                    the Indians in Council<lb/>amongst themselves in order to pre-<lb/>-pare an
                    answer to our addresses --<lb/>about 2 OClock they sent us word<lb/>that they
                    were in readiness to Commun-<lb/>-icate to us their minds. we attended<lb/>&amp;
                    five Medals after making <lb/>some observations replied to <lb/>Elisha Tysons
                    observation respecting<lb/>the proffered aid of Government<lb/>&amp; said that
                    there was but few of</p>
                <p>[p. 35]</p>
                <p>the Chiefs present that they were engaged<lb/>in Business of more importance at
                    this<lb/>time William Kirk was here last year<lb/>that it was the same case with
                    them<lb/>this spring -- &amp; that he did not think us authorized<lb/>to
                    Question him upon that subject</p>
                <p>after he had done the White Loon one <lb/>of the Chiefs residing at Dennis's
                    Station<lb/>made some observations respecting our<lb/>young men residing amongst
                    them<lb/>&amp; said he thought that by Working with<lb/>the Indians in their own
                    Fields they<lb/>would render them more essential<lb/>service &amp; also
                    animadverted upon<lb/>the Indian Corn that was to be distri-<lb/>-buted among
                    the Indians this spring<lb/>at the Station thinking it was a
                    little<lb/>extraordinary that after being a great<lb/>deal of Corn last fall
                    that there<lb/>should be so little this spring when<lb/>it was offered for a
                    division the<lb/>greater part was taken by Shaw some<lb/>less to Wells &amp;
                    some given to the Indians<lb/>so that there was only about 50 Bushls--</p>
                <p>[p. 36]</p>
                <p>26th. We had intended to set out this morning<lb/>but there appeared to be a good
                    deal<lb/>of Writing to do relative to our Mission<lb/>&amp; John Johnston also
                    wished to send some-<lb/>-thing of the Writing kind with us which was
                    not<lb/>fully prepared -- in the course of the<lb/>Day we had a good deal of
                    conversa-<lb/>-tion with Wells we were very plain<lb/>with him, which he took in
                    good<lb/>part &amp; endeavoured to explain or ex-<lb/>-cuse. we plainly saw the
                    Difficulty<lb/>of his situation &amp; were nearly ready <lb/>to conclude that he
                    was determined <lb/>to act uprightly. we think if he<lb/>was Faithful agreeably
                    to his ability<lb/>he would still be of use in his<lb/>Station. We also had a
                    good deal<lb/>of conversation with the White<lb/>Loon respecting Whiskey. he
                    seemed<lb/>very sensible of the bad consequences<lb/>attend[delete: ed]ant upon
                    drinking &amp; made<lb/>some very good observations upon</p>
                <p>[p. 37]</p>
                <p>the subject comparing it to the throwing<lb/>firebrands among the Family &amp;
                    made <lb/>the Women run to hunt shelter some-<lb/>-where else but seemed very
                    doubtful<lb/>of having firmness enough to resist<lb/>the temptation --</p>
                <p>27th. Rode to Fort Wayne through a<lb/>Steady days rain &amp; very deep Roads
                    &amp; ar-<lb/>-rived at the St. Mary's at Stephen <lb/>Youngs about sun setting
                    &amp; Crossed <lb/>over in a Canoe swimming our<lb/>Horses. we let our Horses
                    run loose in<lb/>as fine grass as is common to see. it<lb/>was spear grass &amp;
                    would have mowed<lb/>a good Swarth. here is a proof of In-<lb/>-dian Industry.
                    William Kirk last<lb/>Spring Built a House and Cleared a Corn field<lb/>for this
                    old Indian the field is en-<lb/>-tirely neglected tho the land is<lb/>Excellent
                    a part is grown up with<lb/>spear or Blue Grass so that it won't<lb/>mow</p>
                <p>[p. 38]</p>
                <p>28th. we Set out again this Morning<lb/>&amp; rode as yesterday thro the rain
                    about<lb/>18 miles to Charley Murrays we have <lb/>been very wet these two days
                    &amp; fell a<lb/>good deal through feel about our Health<lb/>but we have a Floor
                    to lie on with <lb/>a good fire at our feet. Murray has<lb/>an Indian Woman for
                    a Wife we eat as<lb/>nice Butter &amp; born Bread of her make<lb/>as need be
                    wished for. this is the second<lb/>crossing of the St. Mary where there has
                    <lb/>been a Garrison the land is good &amp; the<lb/>united states have a reserve
                    of about<lb/>3 miles square at this Place. our pro-<lb/>-spect this morning 29th
                    first day is gloomy in the<lb/>extreme but Elisha &amp; David seem<lb/>intent to
                    go to Wapakunetah the town<lb/>where William Kirk lives contrary <lb/>to my
                    desire which was to proceed<lb/>directly home--</p>
                <p>[p. 39]</p>
                <p>John Flin Interpreter for the united States<lb/>Factory who accompanied us thus
                    far<lb/>&amp; Benjamin Iddings left us to go on to <lb/>Still Water. the river
                    is very high &amp; we<lb/>have a very small Canoe to Ride <lb/>in. after their
                    departure we got our Horses<lb/>in readiness &amp; an Indian Squaw as
                    pilot<lb/>to accompany us to Wapucconetah the <lb/>town where William Kirk
                    resides<lb/>but on examination we found it too<lb/>dangerous a venture so we
                    concluded<lb/>to set out Homeward. we set out about<lb/>about nine OClock in
                    Company<lb/>with Murray &amp; his Indian Wife<lb/>who accompanied us about 6
                    miles<lb/>to see us across 2 Creeks that [delete: appeared]<lb/>were expected to
                    be too high to ride<lb/>we crossed the fork of the St. Mary<lb/>Swimming
                    [delete: in] our Horses &amp; rode to Flins<lb/>where we crossed Laramie
                    Creek<lb/>Swimming our Horses as before<lb/>then to Thatchers 9 miles
                    where<lb/>we lodged on the Floor</p>
                <p>[p. 40]</p>
                <p>as we have done every since we<lb/>left Still water</p>
                <p>29th we crossed Laramie Creek<lb/>again swimming as usual &amp; rode<lb/>to Lower
                    Pickaway where we fed our<lb/>Horses. then Proceeded to Still Water<lb/>to
                    Benjamin Iddings where we took<lb/>some refreshment then Crossed Still<lb/>water
                    to Saml. Jones Swimming our<lb/>Horses. we were kindly entertained<lb/>staid
                    there during the night &amp; about 10 OClock<lb/>Set out in Company with our
                    kind host<lb/>toward Dayton intending to Stop at Benjn<lb/>Owings Saml Jones
                    accompanied us about<lb/>4 Miles &amp; left us &amp; we arrived at B.
                    Owings<lb/>about 12 Miles the road mostly very bad [?]<lb/>the Land during this
                    Rout being near<lb/>Still Water River was Excellent &amp; many<lb/>mill seats on
                    pretty Good Streams proceeding<lb/>from springs Generally falling over a
                    <lb/>high bank of 30 or 40 Feet </p>
                <p>[p. 41]</p>
                <p>There was one Mill Built &amp; one More [delete] preparing <lb/>for another. many
                    of the settlers [delete] are prepa-<lb/>-ring to live handsomely. this perhaps
                    is <lb/>as good a settlement as almost any we have<lb/>seen. there is 4 meetings
                    about Still Water<lb/>&amp; one [delete: about] on White Water belonging to
                    West<lb/>Branch Monthly Meeting Still Water is<lb/>navigable [delete: above]
                    many Miles above the<lb/>Settlement of Friends. our Horses are much<lb/>Jaded
                    &amp; we propose staying here. we lodged<lb/>here &amp; were kindly &amp; well
                    entertained</p>
                <p>6 mo the 1st <lb/>we set out about 8 OClock &amp; Rode<lb/>to Stanton about 5
                    miles through very<lb/>rich Land &amp; a tolerable road we crossed<lb/>the River
                    &amp; fed our Horses at Reeds where<lb/>William Kirk lay sick. &amp; had been
                    here <lb/>2 or 3 weeks in that Condition he was so<lb/>well as to be able to
                    Walk about &amp; was in <lb/>hope that he would be able to go to his<lb/>Station
                    in a few Days. we set out from<lb/>Stanton near noon &amp; Rode through a
                    <lb/>Good Country to Mordecai Walkers about<lb/>a Mile from Wainesville</p>
                <p>[p. 42]</p>
                <p>Where we found ourselves at home &amp; set<lb/>down quietly in the course of this
                    afternoons <lb/>ride we had the opportunity of seeing a<lb/>very large Rattle
                    snake in the road. making <lb/>a very great noise with his Rattles
                    David<lb/>Grave killed him &amp; measured round his<lb/>Body with a string &amp;
                    Calculated that it was<lb/>8 Inch in Circumference &amp; 4 Feet in length</p>
                <p>6 mo 2nd. Our Horses are much out of order<lb/>Davids Mare is much out of order
                    Elisha's<lb/>a good deal so my Horses Back is sore &amp;<lb/>my Calculation is
                    that a few days more<lb/>will Settle the [Harsh] with our Horses --<lb/>we left
                    Mordecai Walkers &amp; Rode over<lb/>the Little Miami to Abijah Oneales
                    where<lb/>Joel Wright resides they both accompanied <lb/>us to Jonathan Wrights
                    about 12<lb/>Miles. he has a fine tract of Land.<lb/>&amp; a saw mill built
                    &amp; expects to Build<lb/>a Grist Mill this Summer</p>
                <p>[p. 43] </p>
                <p>his House is of magnitude for this<lb/>Country altho not finished he has
                    four<lb/>Rooms below Stairs with an Entry but<lb/>has not a great deal of land
                    Cleared<lb/>his Daughter Betsey keep a Small School<lb/>in one of the Rooms</p>
                <p>4th of the month &amp; 7th of the Week we went to Monthly Meeting<lb/>at Centre
                    at 2 1/2 Miles from Jonathan Wrights<lb/>intending on our return in the evening
                    to<lb/>have rode about 13 Miles to Vanmetres but<lb/>the London Epistles &amp;
                    Extracts arriving the<lb/>meeting held so late that we concluded to<lb/>stay at
                    J. Wrights until morning. The<lb/>monthly meeting was large consisting of
                    about<lb/>140 or 150 Families &amp; many Friends that<lb/>appear very well Henry
                    Millhous Charity Cook<lb/>&amp; Susannah Hollingsworth appeared in<lb/>Testimony
                    we thought very lively the business<lb/>there was a good many minutes &amp;
                    business<lb/>came in from the Preparatives &amp; the <lb/>whole was requests to
                    be admitted into<lb/>membership &amp; a few Certificates not one<lb/>offender to
                    deal with</p>
                <p>[p. 44]</p>
                <p>the Preparatives are Centre &amp; todds Fork<lb/>in the Evening I went out with
                    Benjamin<lb/>Farquhar &amp; Joel Wright (Son of Jonathan)<lb/>to view a Tract of
                    Land that adjoins<lb/>Jonathan Wrights &amp; concluded if it<lb/>was not too
                    good it might do</p>
                <p>The Settlement of Friends in this lower<lb/>part of the Country consists of 4
                    Monthly</p>
                <p>1 West Branch by name on Still water<lb/>Consisting of 5 meetings &amp; the
                    prospect<lb/>of another shortly</p>
                <p>2 Miami monthly at Wainsville Consisting<lb/>of 5 Meetings</p>
                <p>3 Centre -- at Todds Fork &amp; Cesars Creek<lb/>alternately</p>
                <p>4 Fairfield -- at Lees Creek &amp; Clear<lb/>Creek alternating 3 meetings for
                    Worship</p>
                <p>we intend setting our early tomorrow<lb/>morning &amp; push forward with
                    Vigour</p>
                <p>[p. 45]</p>
                <p>5th we set out early Jonathan Wright<lb/>accompanied us to Vanmetres about
                    14<lb/>Miles we dined at Vanmetres &amp; then rode <lb/>to Seth Smiths 14 miles
                    where we put up<lb/>for the Night the land in this days rout<lb/>generally good
                    tho' some of it too flat<lb/>much of it I suppose to be of the first
                    quality-</p>
                <p>6th. we set out early again &amp; rode to S. Davis's<lb/>10 miles where we
                    Breakfasted much bad roads<lb/>this morning we Crossed Lees Creek &amp;
                    the<lb/>Rattlesnake Fork of paint yesterday.<lb/>this Morning 4-1/2 Miles
                    completed we<lb/>crossed Paint Creek both considerable<lb/>Streams the Land this
                    morning between<lb/>Smiths &amp; Davis's mostly indifferent<lb/>we passed very
                    near Lees Creek meeting house<lb/>yesterday &amp; also near William
                    Luptons<lb/>Saw Mill we continued on about 7<lb/>miles where we fed our Horses
                    and then<lb/>Proceeded to Chilocotha the Land [delete]<lb/>for 5 or 6 Miles
                    toward Chilacotha is<lb/>of the first Quality</p>
                <p>[p. 46]</p>
                <p>we went in the Evening to see Edward Tiffen<lb/>the Late Governor of the State of
                    Ohio &amp; had<lb/>some Conversation with him respecting the<lb/>selling of
                    whiskey to the Indians in this State<lb/>he seems well disposed &amp; said he
                    would use his<lb/>influence with the Leading members of the<lb/>Legislature of
                    this state in order to have a <lb/>Law passed to that effect.</p>
                <p>7th Elisha &amp; David went to see Worthington<lb/>who lives about 1-1/2 Miles
                    out of Town they<lb/>were pretty well satisfied with their visit<lb/>&amp; found
                    Very Friendly &amp; well disposed to<lb/>forward our Views respecting
                    prohibiting Whiskey<lb/>being sold to the Indians after their return<lb/>we
                    staid &amp; dined &amp; in the Evening rode to<lb/>Websters where we lodged</p>
                <p>8 Set out early &amp; Rode to Evans 9 miles<lb/>through a beautiful Country
                    Breakfasted in a very dirty<lb/>House then 10 miles to Lathers where we
                    <lb/>dined he has a Large &amp; delightful plantation<lb/>after dinner we passed
                    through new Lancaster<lb/>about 3 Miles &amp; put up for the Night</p>
                <p>[p. 47]</p>
                <p>9th We proceeded on to new Lancaster about<lb/>33 Miles about 8 Miles back at
                    brooks tavern<lb/>we found an ancient Friend from the lower <lb/>parts of
                    Virginia who was moving out to his<lb/>Creek settlement &amp; took sick on the
                    road he<lb/>had two of his Daughters with him &amp; appeared<lb/>as though he
                    would not continue many Days<lb/>the Young Women were Comely decent
                    Looking<lb/>Friends his name is Gerard Ladd Elisha<lb/>is very unwell we pushed
                    on, the weather this <lb/>Day intensely hot we pushed on &amp; Crossed
                    the<lb/>River Muskingum near to Zanesville &amp; put up at<lb/>Taylors
                    Tavern</p>
                <p>10th The Weather is very hot this morning &amp;<lb/>Elisha overdone so that we
                    have concluded<lb/>to dine here to Day we went over the<lb/>Muskingum after
                    Breakfast to Isaac<lb/>Vanhornes to see Moses Dillon. we found <lb/>him &amp;
                    went him to view his Mill Seat at<lb/>the Mouth of Licking which is a
                    very<lb/>Large Stream &amp; the seat a very good one</p>
                <p>[p. 48]</p>
                <p>the fall about 6-1/2 Feet he said he had<lb/>another above with a Saw mill
                    erected &amp;<lb/>one still higher up being about 4 Miles<lb/>from the Mouth of
                    the Creek where there <lb/>was about 20 Feet fall where he proposed<lb/>erecting
                    a Furnace his property here ap-<lb/>-pears to be very valuable but it will
                    re-<lb/>-quire an immense sum of money to im-<lb/>-prove it to advantage where
                    his resources<lb/>are commensurate for that purpose I must <lb/>leave -- we
                    returned to Zanesville &amp; Dined<lb/>&amp; then set out &amp; rode about 16
                    miles<lb/>where we Lodged at Spears Tavern</p>
                <p>11th we set out early &amp; rode about 7 miles<lb/>to Wills Creek where we
                    Breakfasted &amp; <lb/>then rode to Washington about 10 miles<lb/>where we dined
                    the weather excessively<lb/>hot. Rain coming on we were in doubt<lb/>whether to
                    move or stay but a township<lb/>Election being held for Choosing
                    Justices<lb/>&amp; the people beginning to drink Whiskey<lb/>&amp; talk loud we
                    decamped &amp; rode</p>
                <p/>
                <p><lb/>[p. 49]</p>
                <p>about 7 Miles when another Shower coming<lb/>on we stop'd at Roger's tavern &amp;
                    Lodged</p>
                <p>12th. set out the roads very slippery so that<lb/>we rode with Difficulty &amp;
                    Breakfasted [delete: with]<lb/>at Bradshaws. after Breakfast we rode <lb/>to
                    Joseph Vanlaws near Plainfield meeting<lb/>house arriving about one OClock we
                    <lb/>put up for the Day &amp; were very kindly<lb/>entertained</p>
                <p>13th Set out next morning &amp; Rode<lb/>5 Miles to St. Clairsville mostly
                    called<lb/>Newels town &amp; staid whilst Elisha<lb/>had his Horse Shod. my
                    Horses<lb/>Back was very sore so much so that<lb/>I thought it rather Cruel to
                    ride<lb/>&amp; therefore I exchanged him with Josiah<lb/>Dillon (who is a
                    Senator for the State <lb/>of Ohio) for a Bay Horse of his after<lb/>paying
                    Smart money we then proceeded<lb/>to Horton Howards about 12 Miles<lb/>where we
                    found John Witchell &amp; <lb/>his Wife Mary</p>
                <p>[p. 50]</p>
                <p>who appeared in high Spirits seeming<lb/>pretty well satisfied with the
                    prospect<lb/>of Settling at Wheeling &amp; were likely<lb/>to have a good house
                    to live in on<lb/>Year without rent I left David &amp;<lb/>Elisha at Horton's
                    &amp; went to Brother<lb/>George Kinseys at Short Creek </p>
                <p>14th Staid at George's until after Dinner<lb/>&amp; then went Nathan updegraff
                    &amp;<lb/>thence to Joseph Steers where we<lb/>lodged my Company having
                    overtaken<lb/>me at N. Updegraffs --</p>
                <p>14th Rainy Weather &amp; the Prospect<lb/>unpleasant -- about 9 O Clock<lb/>the
                    rain abating we proceeded &amp;<lb/>in about 5 Miles Crossed the river<lb/>at
                    Warren near the mouth of <lb/>Short Creek. we then proceeded <lb/>about 20 Miles
                    &amp; Lodged at the<lb/>Junction of the Short Creek &amp;</p>
                <p>[p. 51]</p>
                <p>Wheelen Roads</p>
                <p>15th. set out &amp; Rode to Washington<lb/>[delete: at] 5 Miles &amp; Breakfasted
                    at <lb/>Morris's Tavern. then rode about<lb/>20 Miles to Henry Mills's
                    where<lb/>we propose resting some days</p>
                <p>16 - still Here Elisha this day concluded<lb/>that he would be willing to part
                    with<lb/>his Horse his Back being too sore to think<lb/>of riding him home Henry
                    Mills called<lb/>in William Hills who had a Horse He<lb/>thought would suit him.
                    &amp; so they ex-<lb/>-changed Horses &amp; now it looks likely<lb/>that we may
                    proceed on with more <lb/>satisfaction</p>
                <p>17th. we left Henry Mills's early he ac-<lb/>companying us to Blacksmiths
                    shop<lb/>on the road where Elisha had his Horse <lb/>shod we then Proceeded to
                    our Friend<lb/>Jonas Cattle's -</p>
                <p><lb/>[p. 52]</p>
                <p>&amp; Staid there until about 3 O Clock<lb/>when we set out Intending for
                    Beeson<lb/>Town but a Gust coming on we stop'd at<lb/>William Dixons about 5
                    Miles short of the<lb/>Town &amp; staid there during the night</p>
                <p>18th. we set out early &amp; rode to Union Town<lb/>and arrived about the Sixth
                    Hour the<lb/>Weather warm &amp; a probability of more rain<lb/>to day. we
                    Breakfasted [delete: put up at] Collins's Tavern the<lb/>Land thro the rout
                    Yesterday &amp; this morning<lb/>Excellent &amp; pretty well improved
                    generally<lb/>we passed over the Laurer Hill &amp; Dined<lb/>at Inks's, then
                    proceeded &amp; Crossed the<lb/>Youghigana over the Bridge about <lb/>14 Miles
                    to Peter Lenhards, (Brother <lb/>to Henry in Baltimore) &amp; Lodged</p>
                <p>19 -- Set out early thro Bad roads &amp;<lb/>Rain to Browns 5 miles where we
                    <lb/>Breakfasted the land for 20 Miles<lb/>Back pretty good &amp; thickly
                    settled</p>
                <p><lb/>[p. 53]</p>
                <p>We rode to Tomlinsons about 10 Miles &amp;<lb/>Dined then proceeded 10 miles
                    more<lb/>to Musselmans &amp; put up for the Night<lb/>Elisha appeared very much
                    outdone tho<lb/>the distance was small but the weather is <lb/>Warm &amp; the
                    Hills very fatigueing the Improve-<lb/>-ments at this Tavern are very good &amp;
                    <lb/>every thing has the air of neatness &amp; Indu-<lb/>-stry</p>
                <p>20 Set out &amp; Rode to Gwins [?] Where we Break<lb/>-fasted then Rode through
                    Cumberand<lb/>about 12 Miles &amp; dined then proceeded<lb/>through Old Town to
                    Bells Mills where<lb/>we lodged.</p>
                <p>21 Set out early about 8 Miles to<lb/>a Tavern on the Hills {delete: &amp; dined]
                    Breakfasted<lb/>thence after making a Halt at 15 Mile Creek<lb/>we proceed but
                    rain coming in we stop'd<lb/>about 5 Miles after the rain ceased we
                    pro-<lb/>ceeded to Hancock Willits here we <lb/>Lodged at Bean's</p>
                <p>[p 54]</p>
                <p>23rd. Set out early &amp; Rode to Hunters<lb/>to Breakfast &amp; being 10 Miles
                    then to Williams<lb/>-port 14 Miles &amp; Dined then proceeded <lb/>to
                    Boonsborough &amp; Lodged at Comers Inn<lb/>I had pretty Hard work to drag
                    Elisha along<lb/>this Evening as far as my desire to get <lb/>home prompted
                    me.</p>
                <p>24 we rose Early &amp; proceeded to Middle<lb/>-town 8 Miles where we
                    Breakfasted<lb/>the weather very pleasant which has<lb/>been to hot &amp; Gusty
                    for about 10<lb/>Days Back that Elisha is almost worn<lb/>out but it is nothing
                    but exercise to <lb/>me &amp; I feel as pleasant &amp; easy as if I had<lb/>been
                    sitting at Home</p>
                <p/>
            </div>
        </body>



    </text>
</TEI>
