<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Account of the Exercise and Experience of an Indian Man: Electronic
                    Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>NAME</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 24 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so only with the permission of Friends
                        Historical Library of Swarthmore College. This is the case whether the new
                        publication will be made available at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
                <idno type="local">Indian_man</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>New York Yearly Meeting Records</collection>
                        <idno>RG2/NYy/700</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>2 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This manuscript account is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the campus of
                    Swarthmore College. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date>n.d.</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends</item>

                        <item>Indians of North America</item>

                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2015"/>POD, minor edits</item>

            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>
            <div type="narrative"><pb n="1" facs="SW_NYYM_Man_Page_001"/>
                <p>The Following is an account of the Exercise &amp; Experience of an Indian<lb/>
                    Man as Related by him self to a Number of Friends, says I Dont often open<lb/>
                    my mind to any, but I now feel the way is open. and more than a freedom to<lb/>
                    Do it some years Past it was laid upon me to Encourage others to Do well;<lb/> I
                    thought I was a Poore ignorant Indian, I could not Encourage others to Do<lb/>
                    well, so I shoved it away (Puting his hand out as tho he had Put it from
                    him,<lb/> then fetching his hand back again &amp; laying it on his breast, says
                    it was brought back<lb/> again &amp; laid upon me, I then shoved it away again,
                    &amp; so he Did a number of times<lb/> Implying the reasoning state of his Mind
                    It was then opened to my view, that<lb/> the truth was a Very precious thing,
                    very precious Indeed. Oh how Precious it Doth look<lb/> to me. He can say it is
                    innocent, we can say it is Innocent, thats all we can say.<lb/> words cannot say
                    half. I then said with Peter Depart from me O Lord, I am<lb/> a sinful man but
                    it was brought back &amp; laid upon me again some<lb/> morning as I was going to
                    a <orgName key="presby">Prespeterian</orgName> meeting I saw a flock of sheep
                    along<lb/> before me Puting his hand to his Eyes, says I Did not see them with
                    these Eyes.<lb/> they appeard to be traveling a long before me. the foremost
                    ones was half grown<lb/> large, &amp; I heard them talking to one another.
                    Puting his hand to his Ears says but<lb/> not with those Ears saying to one
                    another God speed help you on the way, the<lb/> hindmost looked Poore, small,
                    their heads hund Down seemed allmost ready to<lb/> give out I wondered what it
                    should mean Then something come &amp; talked<lb/> with me Puting his hand to his
                    Breast, says it talked to me here, and told<lb/> me, these are my sheep &amp;
                    this Day you shall see them lift up their heads in<lb/> hope, &amp; feed on the
                    bread of Life Then it said to me, them that are before are<lb/> the Priest &amp;
                    Deacons, they are grown fat &amp; full, they can Encourage one an<lb/> others
                    but they forget the Poore of the flock. I went on to the meeting, the<lb/>
                    Priest Preached, Prayed, &amp; sung &amp; used the Very words, I heard the fat
                    sheep<lb/> use one to another, And after he had Done, I thought it my Duty to
                    tell them<lb/> what I see on the way; so I Did &amp; thought I saw my Vision
                    fulfilled, the Poore<lb/> of the flock, lifted up their heads in hope &amp; fed
                    on the bread of Life, the<lb/> Priest acknowledged in the Presence of the
                    People, that what I said was True<lb/> and that the Truth, had been Declared
                    among them by a Poore Ignorant <gap/><lb/> an; Then I went home Very
                    comfortable, Oh, how comfortable I Did feel<lb/> Then sometimes I feel my mind
                    Drawn in to simpathy with some, I want to<lb/> go &amp; see them, I was <gap/>
                    yet would think it <gap/> other to Do well,<lb/> I Did not want folks to think
                    so I feel such a simpathy for one poore family<lb/> I want to go see them, at I
                    Did not no how to Do, so I thought I would take a<lb/> grist on my back &amp; go
                    <gap/> beyond where they Live, so I Did, &amp; when I come<lb/> back I stop in,
                    It was just night, there was a rich man lived on the other side<lb/> of the
                    road, I suppose I would let me have bed to sleep in, but I thought I<lb/> had
                    rather lay by the <gap/> mans fire, I felt their worth, I wanted to be with
                    them,<lb/> In the morning when I <gap/> going away I asked the women to hand me
                    a bowle<lb/> she was <unclear>unarilling</unclear> I <gap/> the most, she got
                    one for <gap/> I took out Part of my<lb/> meal &amp; left it with her, felt the
                    wants of the Poore Children, so that <gap/> are not<lb/> carry all my meal away
                    <gap/> then I took leave of them &amp; went home Quietly.</p>
                <pb n="2" facs="SW_NYYM_Man_Page_002"/>
                <p>And <unclear>so</unclear> kept along when I feel my mind in simpathy with any, I
                    try some<lb/> way to go &amp; see them, <gap/> began to think I was geting along
                    Prety well, soone Day I was<lb/> thinking I should go to meeting 3 or 4 Days
                    hence, I began to think what I should say<lb/> when I should come there, so I
                    thought It over, I got something fixed in my mind, I<lb/> thought it would Do
                    Prety well, I hung it up, &amp; by &amp; by I took it looked at it again<lb/> I
                    thought it would Do very well, <del>I hung it up</del> so I Did good many times
                    before meeting Day come<lb/> I went to meeting &amp; after the Priest got
                    through, I stood up &amp; said it off as well as I could<lb/> and I thought I
                    said it off Prety well, but Oh how I was Distress &amp; so I Passed along a
                    long<lb/> time, Did not know what the matter was Then something come &amp;
                    talked to me &amp; says, Did<lb/> you ever know a Great man if he want Great
                    Business Done away to Congress, or to<lb/>
                    <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> to send a Poore ignorant unlerned man to Do
                    it No I say I Did not,<lb/> No more wont Great Spirit take you well I thought
                    sure Enough I have been mista<lb/>ken I never have known what good is, And Oh,
                    how I was Distress, but Did not<lb/> know where to find good (This he supposed
                    to be the bad spirit coming at a time<lb/> when he had mised it at the
                    Endeavouring to Persuade him, that he never had kno<lb/>wn what good was, Then
                    says somthing <unclear>&amp; he</unclear> come &amp; talked me, which he
                    sup<lb/>posed was the good spirit, and says Great One knows all things, he can
                    Do all<lb/> things, he knows what is Best, And if a King want great business
                    Done, &amp; he has<lb/> servents under him, if he wants to send one to Do
                    business for him, if he is a wise<lb/> Learned man, he ought to say what the
                    King tell him to say, if he is an ignorant<lb/> unlerned man, if he can talk, he
                    can say over after the King, just what the<lb/> King tell him to say, if it 2, 3
                    or 4 words more or less just as the King says<lb/> just so he ought to say Then
                    it says to one supose one of your neighbour<lb/> have a Piece of <gap/> to him,
                    a very <unclear>got</unclear> when it was give<lb/> to him, he takes it, feels
                    of it, looks at it; handles it; hangs it up, then by &amp; by<lb/> he takes it
                    Down, he feels of it, handles it, looks at it; hangs it up, so he Do a<lb/>
                    great many times, &amp; keep it 3 or 4 Days, til it begins to stink, then he
                    take<lb/> it, cook it &amp; set before you, to Eat, would you Eat it no I say I
                    would not<lb/> Eat it well it says just so your Preaching was the other Day The
                    Great<lb/> spirit wont have it <unclear>folk</unclear> wont have it Then it came
                    in to my<lb/> mind the Passage when there was a Piece of money brought to our
                        <unclear>savious</unclear><lb/> I Don't remember he asked them whose Image
                    &amp; Inscription was on it<lb/> They told him <gap/> well he told them to
                    render to ceasars the things that<lb/> are cesars, &amp; to God things that are
                    God <gap/> I see my Parking had<lb/> Cesar <unclear>inserption</unclear> on it
                    Because it was something of any own Prepareing<lb/> it Did not come from the
                    Great Spirit, therefore it had not his superscripti<lb/>on on it, &amp; he would
                    not have it, &amp; that was the reason I was so troubled; I see<lb/> that Every
                    thing of mans contrivance had cesar superscription on it<lb/> and only that,
                    that comes Immediately from the Great Spirit, that would return<lb/> to him, or
                    that would be food for his True sheep, my <gap/> says christ know any<lb/>
                    <gap/> &amp; they follow but the Voice of a stranger they will not follow<lb/> I
                    thought some time heard a strange Voice, Puting his hand to his Breast<lb/> says
                    Did not feel <gap> </gap> I love to feel it here then</p><pb n="3" facs="SW_NYYM_Man_Page_003"/>
                <p>Then it opened in my mind the Passage where the multitude followed our
                        <unclear>savior</unclear><lb/> in to the <gap/>, the disciples seemed
                    willing to send them away &amp; give them no<lb/>thing; but he knew their wants,
                    he Did not want them to <gap/> by the way he<lb/> caled on the Disciples, &amp;
                    asked them if they had any thing for them, they say we have<lb/> a few loves
                    &amp; a few fishes, but what are they among so many, but he knew what<lb/> he
                    was going to Do, he Directed that the multitude should all sit Down in
                    compane<lb/> on the grass; then he caled on the Disciples &amp; they give all up
                    to him that they<lb/> had, then he took &amp; broke it, &amp; Blessed it; then
                    gave it to the Disciples, after all this<lb/> was Done, then he Commanded them
                    to hand it to the Multitude, then it was food for<lb/> them, they had Enough to
                    spare Just so I see it is now, when the Great spi<lb/>rit is Pleased to brake
                    the bread of life, hand it to his Disciples, &amp; Command them to<lb/> hand it
                    to the People, then it is food for them Now after this it was Laid upon<lb/> me
                    again to Encourage othersto Do well, but the work looked to be so great, &amp;
                    I<lb/> felt like such a Poore Ignorant Indian, that I thought I could not give
                    up to it<lb/> And said to that that talked with one there is a great many that
                    can do better<lb/> than I can, take some this one &amp; Excuse one, It asked me
                    who; I said such a<lb/> one, it told one to fetch him up, I Did in any mind
                    Putting his hand to his breast<lb/> as tho he brought it to the witness in him
                    self, but he would not have him, but<lb/> shoved him away &amp; so in this way
                    he said he broought up a number, but he<lb/> would not have them, &amp; told me
                    I must give up Now I found the Great<lb/> Spirit condescended to <gap/> weak
                    state &amp; opened things to my understanding in<lb/> a way to meet my capacity
                    so I found it was necessary to wait upon him<lb/> to be instructed, what to say,
                    how to say, &amp; when <gap/> and when I could say <gap/><lb/> the servents that
                    was sent out to Invite in to the feast, It is Done Lord as those<lb/> commanded
                    &amp; yet there is room, then I find there is yet room for more Exercise<lb/>
                    more labour, more Invitation, the way is not shut up in any Heart<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>Then it opened in my mind the circumstance of Joseph, how he was sold by<lb/> his
                    brethren, &amp; the reason why they sold him, he was Designd by the great<lb/>
                    spirit to be greater then his brethren, he had some Dreams that seamed to<lb/>
                    lead them to think so, some of them had a mind to kill him, others thought<lb/>
                    best to sell him, &amp; see what would become of his Dreams, so they sold him,
                    he<lb/> was carried <del>Down</del> of to Egypt, &amp; Put into Prison,
                    wrongfully, but the Great spi<lb/>rit was with him there &amp; knew what he was
                    a going to bring abought<lb/>
                    <gap/> get along Pretty well for a while, there was some<lb/>body in Prison with
                    Joseph, and he was released, &amp; Joseph told him when<lb/> he come in the
                    Presence of the King to remember him, but he forgot Jo<lb/>seph till he was
                    brought into a strait, the King had some Dreams<lb/> I cannot read much, I
                    cannot tell just how it was, but I remember he<lb/> Dreamed something about some
                    Ears of corn, Eating up some Ears of<lb/>corn, &amp; there nobody could
                    Interpret his Dreams, then this man<lb/> remembered Joseph, he was sent for, the
                    Great Spirit was with him &amp; knowed<lb/> all things, so he could tell the
                    King the interpretation of his Dreams
                </p><pb n="4" facs="SW_NYYM_Man_Page_004"/>
                <p>So when he told him what was a going to <gap/> the King believed it<lb/> and
                    thought it best to Prepare against the time of Famine, that Joseph<lb/> said was
                    coming, &amp; he thought there was no one so suitable as Joseph<lb/> because the
                    Great Spirit was with him, so he put all Power in to his hand<lb/> only the King
                    was greater, so Joseph ordered store houses to be built &amp; laid<lb/> up Corn
                    for the time of famine that was coming &amp; he had the Keys of the<lb/> stores,
                    now the famine come, his brethren come to want, they had sold<lb/> Joseph, &amp;
                    Did not intend to bow to him, but they heard there was corn in<lb/> Egypt, their
                    father sent some of them Down to buy some, they applyed to Joseph<lb/> he knew
                    them, they Did not know him, he asked if they had any brethren &amp;
                    whe<lb/>ther they had a Father living, they told him about them, so after a
                    while Joseph<lb/> sent for them, they all went Down &amp; bowed to Joseph, for
                    there was no other way for<lb/> them to kept alive Now it looked Plain to me,
                    that we have a measure of<lb/> the good spirit afforded to lead us to Instruct
                    us &amp; it is greater then we are &amp; de<lb/>signed to Rule over us, or we
                    may Do as that tells us, or we may mind the bad spirit<lb/> But if we Do, it
                    will not yeald the Peaceable fruits of rightiousness, &amp; we may say<lb/> to
                    the good spirit, we will not have this man to rule over us, we may Put it
                    away<lb/> and sell it, &amp; it may be Put into Prison, yet a famine will
                    overtake there, &amp; though<lb/> they may go into a far Country, far away from
                    that, that is Right, &amp; and not Even<lb/> know Joseph or this good spirit,
                    yet that will know them, &amp; it will there rise<lb/> up &amp; Plead with them,
                    now there is no other way, but to go back again to that; that<lb/> is wright,
                    &amp; acknowledge Joseph to be greatest he has all Power Commited to him<lb/> he
                    has the Keys of <gap/>, &amp; they that will not <gap/> him, must Die.</p>
                <p>The same Disposition, that was in Josephs Brethren, and in People in the<lb/>
                    Days of the Apostles, is now in People, I have seen some folks, so simple, that
                    they<lb/> got mad with a gun &amp; Broke it all to Pieces, because it had Done
                    some Mischief,<lb/> as tho the Gun was to blame, if it had not been Charged,
                    &amp; then fire Put to it,<lb/> it would not; Done any harm, so when the
                    apostles were Charged with some<lb/>thing &amp; the Fire of Divine love operated
                    on them, her they could Do Execution<lb/> but after it had Passed through them,
                    they were like the Emty Gun, it was<lb/> not they that Did it; it was that flame
                    of Divine love &amp; here the People<lb/> took the apostles, &amp; Put them to
                    Death, as tho they Done it, &amp; thought to<lb/> stop it from spreading, but
                    they could not, for <unclear>it operated</unclear> through
                        <unclear>otherng</unclear><lb/> And it operates the <gap/> purpose
                    <gap/><lb/> PL</p>

            </div>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
