<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Some Account of Rachel Coope [edited by Joshua Sharpless]: Electronic
                    Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Journal transcribed by</resp>
                    <name>Miriam Lise Hauser</name>

                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Tri-Co Digital Humanities Initiative</sponsor>
                <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 102 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">SW_RC1805</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: An Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Foster-Meyers Family Papers</collection>
                        <idno>RG5/221</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>65 pp. (1 volume)</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This Rachel Coope manuscript is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the
                    campus of Swarthmore College. In the fall semester of 2010, Swarthmore students
                    enrolled in English 50A (“Reading Red, White, and In-Between in Early American
                    Literature”) transcribed this manuscript as part of a larger project to make the
                    library’s rich store of Quaker Indian mission writings more accessible. The
                    project was designed by Christopher Densmore, Curator of Friends Historical
                    Library, and Keat Murray, Visiting Assistant Professor of English. Student
                    transcribers included: Miriam Lise Hauser. Transcriptions were compiled and
                    edited in the present form by Professor Murray. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> The transcribers and editor attempted to render the author’s orthography and
                    grammar as they appear on the page of his journal, even when the author’s own
                    spelling and usage are inconsistent. Additionally, many questions remain about
                    spelling the names of his Quaker acquaintances, individual Native Americans who
                    populate his journal, and Indian villages and towns. The transcribers and editor
                    attempted to remain faithful to the author’s Anglicized spellings in all cases. </p>
                <p>This volume is actually a compilation by Rachel Coope's father, Joshua Sharpless,
                    taken after her death from her original journal and correspondence. Journals "a"
                    and "b," also in the collections of Friends Historical Library, represent
                    transcriptions of Rachel Coope’s actual diaries. Journal "a" her “esteemed
                    parents”; however, her mother died before the letter was written, and so it may
                    have been meant for her parents­in­law, to whom she was deeply attached) copied
                    over twice. No version of this letter is included in journal four. Except for
                    this, the differences were small, such as variance in phrasing and spelling, and
                    not in content. It seems as though journal "a" preceded journal "b"; it is less
                    polished. The handwriting seems more rushed and the paper size varies, while in
                    journal "b", the handwriting is neater, and the paper used is consistent. It is
                    possible that these, especially journal three, could have been handwritten by
                    Coope.</p>
                <p>The author of the original journal does not include page numbers on his
                    manuscript; the page numbers have been interpolated by the transcribers to
                    correspond with the manuscript sheets.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1807">1807</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Society of Friends -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America -- Missions</item>
                        <item>Quakers -- Pennsylvania -- Diaries</item>
                        <item>Seneca Indians</item>
                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Relgious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>

        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="preface">
                <pb n="5" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_05"/>
                <lb/>
                <head>Some account of <persName ref="rcoop1">Rachel Coope</persName><lb/> taken from
                    notes that she preserv’d, from<lb/> her letters and from personal
                    knowledge.</head>

                <p> She was the daughter of <persName ref="jshar1">Joshua</persName> and<lb/>
                    <persName ref="eshar1">Edith Sharpless</persName> and was born the 3rd of
                    the<lb/> 5 mo 1771. About the 15th year of her age<lb/> her mother was taken
                    from her by death,<lb/> and the charge of her father’s family as<lb/>
                    housekeeper, very much devolv’d upon<lb/> her; the trial in both respects she
                    very<lb/> sensibly felt, yet was enabled to con-<lb/> duct her charge with
                    stability and pru-<lb/> dence, and bear the loss of her dear mo<lb/> ther, with
                    a becoming fortitude. For<lb/> several years the charge of the family<lb/>
                    rested upon her to which she attended<lb/> like one of riper age. She was
                    cheerful in<lb/> her disposition, and of a lively active turn<lb/> of mind,
                    which being seasoned with the<lb/> baptizing power of Truth, rendered her<lb/>
                    company agreeable and instructive.</p>

                <pb n="6" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_06"/>

                <p> About the 21st year of her age she was<lb/> married to <persName ref="bcoop1"
                        >Benjamin Coope</persName>, and settled<lb/> in the verge of
                        <orgName>Bradford meeting</orgName>, of<lb/> which she was a diligent
                    attender, and<lb/> increas’d in usefulness among them,<lb/> labouring with
                    friends in supporting<lb/> Church discipline, and visiting those who<lb/> miss'd
                    their way. She several years acted<lb/> as clerk to their mo. Meeting.</p>
                <p> In the year <date when="1804">1804</date> information was<lb/> sent down from
                    the yearly meeting to the<lb/> quarterly and monthly meetings that the<lb/>
                    settlement made by friends among the na-<lb/> tives on the <geogName ref="alleg"
                        >Allegany river</geogName> was now so advanced<lb/> as to need the
                    assistance of females <del><unclear/></del><lb/>
                    <del><unclear/></del> in instructing and exampleling<lb/> their sex in domesting
                    concerns. request-<lb/> ing that if a suitably qualifyed friend &amp;<lb/> his
                    companion should feel their minds<lb/> engaged in the concern to come forward as
                    vo-<lb/> lunteers. When <del>it</del> information was spread in the monthly<lb/>
                    and quarterly meetings of which she was a<lb/> member her and her husband’s
                    minds became <lb/>
                    <pb n="7" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_07"/> so impress’d with it as to cause them
                    to<lb/> believe it right to give it place. And on<lb/> closely <add
                        place="above">tending</add> to the concern it so ripened, as to<lb/> make
                    them willing to lay their prospect<lb/> before the friends of their monthly
                    meeting,<lb/> for their sympathy and advise. Tho’ a<lb/> close trial to their
                    friends to part with<lb/> them yet upon weighty deliberation they<lb/> judged it
                    best to leave them at liberty,<lb/> to persue their religious prospects, as
                    way<lb/> might open: which on closely attending<lb/> too they believed it right
                    to prepare for<lb/> the journey, and <del>was</del> were enabled to give up<lb/>
                    a good and comfortable home, the society<lb/> of their friends and near
                    relations to be<lb/> found in the way of their duty. From<lb/> the notes she
                    kept of her journey the follow-<lb/> ing <del>is</del> are extracted.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>


            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-05-20">1805. 5 Month 20th</date><placeName key="bradf"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>
                    <q>After a time of comfortable<lb/> quiet wherein we were favoured to feel
                        the<lb/> overshadowings of Divine regard a number<lb/> of our friends and
                        near relations being pre-<lb/> sent we took leave of them in the feeling <lb/>
                        <pb n="8" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_08"/> embraces of endearing love: <persName
                            ref="ncoop2">Father Coope</persName> bear-<lb/> ing us company to
                            <persName ref="jembr1">James Embree’s</persName>. -- On<lb/> parting
                        with him tears flow’d in an abun-<lb/> dance, under a feeling sympathy
                        with<lb/> him and ardent desires were raised in my<lb/> heart, that he might
                        be enriched with that<lb/> peace, now in his lonesome and advanc’d<lb/>
                        stage of life, that is the precious enjoy-<lb/> ment of the righteous: - We
                        lodged at <persName ref="wtrue1">Wilson<lb/> Truemans</persName> where on my
                        going to bed I<lb/> quietly fell asleep. but waking before three<lb/>
                        Oclock, the remembrance of the parting scene<lb/> so forcibly revived, that
                        tears could not be<lb/> suppress'd, and sleep departed. Thou O my<lb/> God
                            has<add>t</add> at seasons, in thy unmerrited<lb/> goodness, been
                        pleased to make bare thy<lb/> arm, and in times of trial, as patience<lb/>
                        was abode in, offerd sweet consolation; un-<lb/> der a humbling sense
                        thereof, may I a<lb/> little intercede for the renew’d continuence<lb/> of
                        thy love.</q> ---- On the evening of their<lb/> second days journey she
                    remarks.-- My<lb/> attention has been so taken up with viewing <lb/>
                    <pb n="9" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_09"/> the roads &amp; the country, that I have
                    had<lb/> but little serious reflections yet have not<lb/> had unpleasant
                    sensations or enjoyed so<lb/> large a portion of that precious conso-<lb/>
                    lation, which my soul, above all things,<lb/> desires. - O that I may abide in a
                    watch-<lb/> ful state with my eye single to Him<lb/> whose fatherly protection
                    is as a wall<lb/> round about all those who are <unclear>severely</unclear><lb/>
                    devoted to serve him where ever their lots<lb/> may be cast.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline> On the <del><unclear/></del>th <date when="1805-05-28"> 8th day</date>
                    after they set off at the<lb/>
                    <placeName key="bimea">Big Meadows</placeName> on the third fork of <geogName
                        ref="checkPlace">Pine creek</geogName></dateline>
                <p> the country became such a wilderness, the<lb/> road thro' so little improved,
                    being often<lb/> intersected by the fallen timber, as to ren-<lb/> der geting
                    their waggon thro’ at that time<lb/> impracticable, consequently they were
                    oblidgd<lb/> to leave it part of ther bedding, cloathing &amp;c<lb/> and persue
                    their journey mostly on foot their horses<lb/> being loaded with the necessaries
                    of what<lb/> they could take - they were four in number<lb/> a young man who
                    went to assist them <lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_10"/> in going out, and a valuable female
                    friend<lb/> who was a fellow labourer in the work - going<lb/> to reside with
                    them. and they had but 3 horses<lb/> On the 3rd day about noon they arrived at
                        <persName ref="jbell1">John<lb/> Bells</persName> in <placeName ref="ceres"
                        >Kings settlement</placeName>.-- She says, <q>John’s<lb/> wife seeing us,
                        (tho' we were strangers to each<lb/> other) yet she came running to meet us
                        with her<lb/> cheeks bedew'd with tears. - The joy was mu-<lb/> -tual. --
                        How consolating the sight of a friend<lb/> after so fatigueing a journey;
                        having been<lb/> more than two days and nights in the wil-<lb/> derness,
                        since we left the last house. -- Altho<lb/> the journey has been trying yet
                        I felt some-<lb/> thing so animating and encouraging to<lb/> revive, and my
                        heart was fill’d with so<lb/> precious a sweetness, that it was a full
                        com-<lb/> pensation for our most trying seasons.<lb/> Ah may I abide in the
                        patience, with<lb/> my eye single to Him, who knows what<lb/> is best for
                        us.</q> -- On the <date when="1805-06-07">eighteenth day</date><lb/> after
                    leaving home they arived safe and<lb/> in good health at <placeName ref="tunes"
                        >Tunesassah</placeName>, the place<lb/> of their destination. ---- The next
                    day <lb/>
                    <pb n="11" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_11"/> she says- <q>A great many of the natives
                        came to<lb/> see us, thro’ the course of this day; among them<lb/> was
                            <persName ref="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName>’s sister who said; “she
                        was<lb/> glad the Good Spirit had brought us safe thro’<lb/> our long
                        journey.”—which raised sensations so comforta-<lb/> ble and endearing that
                        my heart was<lb/> fill’d with gratitude, and this language,<lb/> in the
                        secret of my spirit, was breathed,<lb/> “Great and marvlous are thy works
                        Lord<lb/> God Almighty.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-06-14">6 Month 14th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> They met the Indians in coun-<lb/> cil, which was opened by one of their
                    chiefs<lb/> expressing thanks to the great Spirit, who<lb/> had brought them
                    safely thro’ so long and<lb/> perilous a journey: - she then says <q>the<lb/>
                        address from the committee relative to<lb/>
                        <hi rend="underline">us</hi> was first read, then part of an epistle<lb/> to
                        their women. -- They were also inform’d<lb/> that, notwithstanding our
                        journey had been<lb/> long and trying, yet we felt peace of mind<lb/> in
                        being with them, and hoped our sis-<lb/> ters the Indian women would be
                        wil-<lb/> ling, when we became more acquainted <lb/>
                        <pb n="12" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_12"/> to be instructed in the ways of the
                        white<lb/> people-- After a considerable time of con-<lb/> ference among
                        themselves they inform’d<lb/> us- We return thanks to the great Spirit<lb/>
                        to see you all well, and that he has preserv’d<lb/> your women thro’ so long
                        a journey, and<lb/> that they have ariv’d safe in our country,-<lb/> and we
                        are much pleas’d they are going to<lb/> stay among us, to instruct our
                        women.<lb/> We return thanks to the great Spirit, that<lb/> he has put this
                        into your hearts, and we<lb/> wish you to make your minds easy.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1805-08-03">8 Month 3rd</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> In a letter to her father <persName ref="ncoop2">Coope</persName><lb/> she
                    writes- <q>Altho this is the first time I<lb/> have attempted to address thee in
                        this<lb/> way since we parted (exceping a few lines<lb/> from <placeName
                            ref="middl">Middletown</placeName>) yet it has not been for<lb/> want of
                        affection, nay verily, the taking<lb/> hold of thy hand when we parted,
                        was<lb/> by far the closest trial I met with among all<lb/> my near
                        relations, and for many miles<lb/> I could not suppress the tears from
                        flow-<lb/> ing -- Our moving here was from a sense <lb/>
                        <pb n="13" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_13"/> of duty.- The impressions were so
                        strong and<lb/> at time would revive with such weight<lb/> that I believ’d
                        it right for me to submit<lb/> our going to our friends; had they
                        discoura-<lb/> ged it I think I should have felt re-<lb/> leased.-- My
                        sincere desire from the first<lb/> was, that we might be guided by that<lb/>
                        hand, that will lead all those rightly<lb/> who rely thereon; and I thought
                        there<lb/> was a comfortable degree of peace experien-<lb/> ced in being
                        resigned: but the near sym-<lb/> pathy I felt for thee, together with
                        the<lb/> many trials I had to meet with, reduced<lb/> me so low that, had my
                        request at a<lb/> weak time been granted, I should not<lb/> now be in a
                        state of mutibility.--<lb/> I am very sensible, that thro’ unwatch-<lb/>
                        fulness I have often err’d from the right<lb/> way; yet have been made truly
                        thank-<lb/> ful, that conviction followed; and at sea-<lb/> sons been
                        enabled to renew covenant--<lb/> but O the natural will, how strong,
                        how<lb/> hard to be kept in its proper subjection, <lb/>
                        <pb n="14" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_14"/> that I have been ready at times to
                        cry<lb/> out, must I always remain in a state<lb/> of bondage.-- Oh may I
                        double my<lb/> warfare and press forward with the hope,<lb/> that, by the
                        aid of my heavenly Father, I<lb/> shall be enabled to become a
                        conquerer;<lb/> remembring <quote type="bible">that in due time ye
                            shall<lb/> reap if ye faint not.</quote>
                        <space/> Being at <placeName ref="phila">Philad a.</placeName><lb/> on
                        business a week before we set off – at a<lb/> friends house we very
                        unexpectedly met<lb/> with <persName>WC</persName>-- who had something
                        peculiarly<lb/> encourag<del>e</del>ing to say to us; signifying that<lb/>
                        he felt so much sympathy and love to<lb/> flow towards us when at dinner
                        that he<lb/> could not go up stairs without expressing<lb/> it tho’ he
                        several times attempted it--<lb/> he address’d my husband with the
                        appela-<lb/> tion of <quote type="bible">beloved brother be not to
                            diffident,<lb/> for thou wilt be an instrument of good<lb/> to that
                            people.</quote> several times repeating<lb/> the words <quote
                            type="bible">go my dear friends and the<lb/> Lord go with you.</quote>
                        -- I thought it very <lb/>
                        <pb n="15" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_15"/> extraordinary after such a season of
                        con-<lb/> flict we had had to pass thro’ that we<lb/> should meet with such
                        encouragement,-<lb/> Tho’ I know dear father <hi rend="underline">that</hi>
                        is not suf-<lb/> ficient to rely upon, yet I have witness’d<lb/> some
                        refreshing seasons since parting<lb/> with thee, particularly in our
                        religious<lb/> opportunities</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1805-10-31">10 Month 31st</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> In a letter to me she says <q>Last<lb/> spring several acres of Oats with
                        Timothy<lb/> and Cloverseed with it were sow’d-- ½ a bushel of<lb/>
                        Buckwheat- and some potatoes and corn<lb/> planted- all grew amazingly-- It
                        has<lb/> been a busy summer with us both men<lb/> and women; the forepart of
                        it we had at<lb/> work a carpenter and mill right and a<lb/> number of
                        Indians diging at the race.<lb/> It is very heavy work to clear land here,
                        &amp;<lb/> it is surprizing to see the quantity of saw<lb/> logs a few acres
                        produces-- About 13 <unclear>acres</unclear><lb/> is put in with wheat. --
                        Potatoes, pump-<lb/> kins and turnips we have in a bundance <lb/>
                        <pb n="16" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_16"/> they will be helpful in the way of
                        fod-<lb/> der. the oats likewise was mow'd for foddering.-<lb/> It has not
                        been in our power to render the<lb/> natives much assistance this summer;
                        yet<lb/> I have no doubt our being here, has been<lb/> useful.- We have spun
                        some stocking wool<lb/> for our own use: to se the wool converted in-<lb/>
                        to stocking has excited their astonishment.<lb/> We have three little wheels
                        ready to run when<lb/> we get flax.-- We purpose this winter puting<lb/> up
                        a house near us for those Indians who<lb/> wish to learn, to spin &amp;c
                        in.- They appear<lb/> desirous to get more comfortable houses to<lb/> live
                        in- and for that purpose have bought<lb/> many 100 ft. of boards.- When the
                        young<lb/> men first came here, the cattle were all the<lb/> Indians had on
                        their river.- They will<lb/> now amount to several 100, a number of<lb/>
                        which are fine oxen which they have <unclear>broke</unclear>.<lb/> I have
                        endeavored to discribe the man-<lb/> ner of our geting along, and what we
                        have<lb/> done. I will intimate a little to thee now <lb/>
                        <pb n="17" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_17"/> how I have fared.- Thou knew it
                        was<lb/> a close tryal to me, to give up to be thus<lb/> separated from you;
                        and I have often been<lb/> made thankful that I <hi rend="underline"
                            >was</hi> favoured to<lb/> get into a state of resignation. I think<lb/>
                        I never enjoy'd a more comfortable state of<lb/> mind, than since residing
                        here.-- One first<lb/> day eve afternoon when they were long I feeling
                        the<lb/> want of society to introduce a new train<lb/> of ideas for the mind
                        to dwell on - a little<lb/> before the sun withdrew from us his rays.<lb/> I
                        walked out alone, seeking for some new<lb/> objects to amuse me and persued
                        the new<lb/> road about ¾ of a mile to the river. as I<lb/> walk'd along my
                        mind unintentionally<lb/> was engaged, in ruminating on my native<lb/> home,
                        my dear relations and friends, and<lb/> why I should be thus seperated
                        from<lb/> them.-- I was satisfy'd that it did not<lb/> proceed from any will
                        of my own but<lb/> much in the cross, and in submission<lb/> to inward
                        impressions.- As I was thus <lb/>
                        <pb n="18" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_18"/> musing my heart was fill'd with a
                        preci-<lb/> ous illumination, and self so reduced, that<lb/> I felt willing
                        to make a full surrender of<lb/> my all, to the great and wise disposer of
                        events<lb/> but alass, this produced awful sensations;<lb/> and I was ready
                        to shudder at the prospect;<lb/> when unexpectedly and unsought for a<lb/>
                        language reviv'd, “Fear thou not neither be<lb/> dismay'd. I will strengthen
                        thee, yea I will<lb/> help thee, my grace is sufficient for thee.”<lb/> O
                        the Divine consolation that fill’d my<lb/> breast.- Tho’ as to the outward
                        it might<lb/> look lonesome; being in the wilderness-<lb/> far from society-
                        some distance from the<lb/> house and nearly dark: yet had I been<lb/> in
                        the midst of my friends no outward<lb/> enjoyment could have been equal to
                        the<lb/> precious sweetness I then experienced--<lb/> my heart overflow'd
                        with gratitude-- any<lb/> subtle petitions asconded for the continu-<lb/>
                        ations of his love, Tho’ felt unworthy of<lb/> the least of the multiplied
                        favours I am <lb/>
                        <pb n="19" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_19"/> receiving: may humility and reverence
                        be<lb/> ascribed to him alone who is forever worthy,<lb/> Amen -- I have my
                        bitters as well as<lb/> my sweets, and tryals are necessary for my<lb/>
                        further refinement, and Oh that their may<lb/> be a willingness to be
                        searched and tried,<lb/> untill every thing that is contrary to the<lb/>
                        pure truth, is done away--</q></p>
                <p> To some near connections <q>Dear Chil-<lb/> dren, we that have been brought up
                        in the<lb/> plentiful enjoyment of this worlds pro-<lb/> duce, and many
                        other advantages, have<lb/> abundant cause to be thankful. Oh how<lb/> I
                        have felt for many poor children that<lb/> I have seen since I left home;
                        particularly<lb/> thro’ the course of our journey, but we<lb/> must leave
                        them to Providence who is<lb/> the great superintendent of the
                        Universe.<lb/> We have mostly since being here enjoy'd<lb/> good health, and
                        live comfortably tho’<lb/> much retired.-- have not got much engag'd<lb/> in
                        instructing the Indians; it will require <lb/>
                        <pb n="20" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_20"/> some time to learn their language
                        and<lb/> to procure materials for spinning</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1805-11-01">11 Month 1st</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To a friend - <q>Thy letter of <date when="1805-07">7 mo</date> last<lb/> came
                        safe to hand. The wholesome counsel<lb/> together with the interesting
                        information,<lb/> was truly acceptable; for it reached me at<lb/> a time
                        when I was very desirous of hearing<lb/> from my native home; being of the
                        latest<lb/> date of any I had received -- I was pleas'd<lb/> to find thou
                        hadst been to see my dear<lb/>
                        <persName ref="ncoop2">father Coope</persName> for whose situation I have
                        near-<lb/> by felt; knowing it was a close trial both<lb/> to him and us, to
                        be thus separated,<lb/> now in his advanced stage of life.<lb/> Indeed when
                        I view'd the prospect not<lb/> only of leaving <hi rend="underline">him</hi>
                        but society in gen-<lb/> eral, with my dear friends and relations,<lb/> to
                        many of whom I have of late felt<lb/> an increasing nearness, with desires
                        for the<lb/> advancement of our Zion, and to live so<lb/> retired in an
                        uncultivated part of the coun-<lb/> try, was so in the cross, that at times
                        I <lb/>
                        <pb n="21" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_21"/> was almost ready to run counter to
                        se-<lb/> cret impressions; but knowing my peace<lb/> consisted in obedience;
                        and remembring<lb/> how it was with good old Jacob: when<lb/> he left his
                        father’s house to go into a<lb/> strange country, that in the course of<lb/>
                        his journey, when alone, he had to ac-<lb/> knowledge, “surely the Lord is
                        in this<lb/> place and I knew it not.”- and how<lb/> he was preserv'd and
                        bless'd, so that on<lb/> his returning, he said, "I am not worthy of
                        the<lb/> least of thy mercies, for with my staff<lb/> I passed over this
                        Jordon, and now I<lb/> am become two bands.”-- As these con-<lb/>
                        siderations reviv'd with renew'd faith,<lb/> that the Divine presence, is
                        still the<lb/> same that ever it was, to those who<lb/> are truly devoted to
                        serve the Most<lb/> High. - my faith was a little<lb/> strengthened, the
                        mountains gradually<lb/> disappear'd and a belief increas'd, that<lb/> if it
                        was the Lords will for us to go, <lb/>
                        <pb n="22" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_22"/> he would support us if our eye
                        were<lb/> fixed upon him. -- Thus as I endea-<lb/> voured to become
                        resigned. I felt at sea-<lb/> sons a comfortable consolation, and have<lb/>
                        experienced, even in this remote part of<lb/> the country, a brook by the
                        way, that<lb/> will refresh the weary traveler.-- Our re-<lb/> ligious
                        opportunities are mostly attended<lb/> with a lively savour. It is
                        encouraging<lb/> to hear that the petitions of those who<lb/> have been <add
                            place="above">&amp; still are</add> as valiants in our Israel are<lb/>
                        ascending on our behalf.- Surely it calls<lb/> for grateful returns of
                        thankfulness to<lb/> the Author of all good.-</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>The natives appear friendly disposed<lb/> and are gradually increasing in the
                        ideas<lb/> of civilized life.-- Some of them are much<lb/> spirited in
                        cultivating their farms and<lb/> in geting more comfortable
                    houses.--</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>The concern feels weighty and impor-<lb/> tant, and I have no doubt but that
                        it<lb/> was rightly founded; and if those engag'd <lb/>
                        <pb n="23" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_23"/> therein are careful to dwell near the
                        Divine<lb/> direction they will be preserved; and may<lb/> at a future day
                        have to view their labours<lb/> with satisfaction.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1805-11-30">11 Month 30th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> In answer to her brother <persName ref="jshar2">JS</persName> who<lb/> desired
                    to be informed of the customs &amp; man-<lb/> -ners of the natives-- says
                        <q>Since the young<lb/> men resided here, the natives had a great<lb/> image
                        cut out of a Pine tree and made<lb/> after the figure of a man, and
                        painted,<lb/> so as to look frightful, which they call'd<lb/> the Great
                        Spirit. They had set times of<lb/> worshiping and dancing before it.
                        But<lb/> as their minds became more enlighten'd<lb/> some of them grew
                        uneasy with<lb/> this image, and they had many confer-<lb/> ences what
                        should be done with it; but<lb/> they were fearful of destroying it,
                        lest<lb/> some evil should befall them.- At<lb/> length one of their chiefs
                        proposed taking<lb/> it into the woods and puting some beans<lb/> and corn
                        by it, to shew their good will <lb/>
                        <pb n="24" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_24"/> for it. Hence after much debate
                            <persName ref="habee1">Henry Obail</persName><lb/> son of <persName
                            ref="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> being permited to speak<lb/> said,
                        why this image you worship was once<lb/> a little sprout that grew out of
                        the ground<lb/> it could neither hear nor speak - well it was<lb/> made like
                        a man and we worship it still<lb/> it can neither hear nor speak- is this
                        the<lb/> sort of Great Spirit we worship, cant hear can’t<lb/> speak - give
                            <hi rend="underline">me</hi> leave and I will make way<lb/> with it.- At
                        length it was given up to<lb/> him, and he tumbled it into the river &amp;<lb/>
                        <add>it</add> floated away -- but they watched him<lb/> thinking some evil
                        would happen him<lb/> for so doing -- Notwithstanding their image<lb/> is
                        gone they still continue regularly twice<lb/> a year their dances, offering
                        sacrafices, some-<lb/> times burning tobacco &amp;c</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-12-23">12mo 23</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> From her diary. <q>It has been snow-<lb/> ing more or less these two days
                    --</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1805-12-25">25th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <q>Various reflections pass'd thro’ my<lb/> mind to day as I sat knitting, of
                        which<lb/> the following is a part-- At this lone- <lb/>
                        <pb n="25" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_25"/> some hour when the watery clouds
                        are<lb/> discharging their whitened substance<lb/> and the trees of the
                        forrest are clad with<lb/> the icy snow- while my mind is un-<lb/> molested
                        with the cares of this life - and<lb/> my thoughts absorbed in awful
                        medita-<lb/> tion- may I view all temporary scenes<lb/> as fading toys, and
                        revere that hand<lb/> from whom all good comes- Now at<lb/> this solemn
                        period attend O my soul<lb/> in humility wait to be learn'd by this<lb/>
                        inward teacher -- O my faultering<lb/> mind, how long wilt thou be
                        blundering<lb/> along in thy journey Heavenward. thou<lb/> hast often seen
                        this insufficience of hu-<lb/> man frailty therefore in full confi-<lb/>
                        dence, rely on that Power which at sea-<lb/> sons, thou hast felt to be
                        precious.--<lb/> And now O Lord permit me to intercede<lb/> for a renewal of
                        thy holy aid, that<lb/> when thou in thy wisdom may see<lb/> mete to hide,
                        as it were, thy face from <lb/>
                        <pb n="26" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_26"/> me I may be enabled, in patience<lb/>
                        and humility to wait for thy coming;<lb/> and when thou art pleased to be
                        near<lb/> and feed me I may not slide from<lb/> the true path; for in thee
                        and thee<lb/> alone is safety.</q>-</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-01-07">1806 1 Month 7th</date><placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>
                    <q>All things as to the out-<lb/> ward glide comfortably along but I<lb/> have
                        often to pass thro’ seasons of deep<lb/> humiliation. -- Thou <add
                            place="above">only</add> Lord knows the<lb/> anguish of my spirit and
                        sincerity of<lb/> my heart, that I desire above all things<lb/> to serve
                        thee but, the cross and the assault<lb/> of the enemy. - Will I never be
                        able to<lb/> overcome the many hindering things!<lb/> Thou hast at seasons O
                        Father clearly man-<lb/> ifested to me thy will-- and sweet peace<lb/> has
                        accompanied faithfulness thereto<lb/> Then Oh my soul why dost thou
                        doubt.<lb/> dwell low; in humility wait. let not<lb/> thy faith fail, that
                        so in the littleness thou<lb/> mayest be enabled to do the Lords
                    will.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="27" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_27"/>
                <dateline><date when="1806-01-23">23rd</date> and first of the week-- <placeName
                        key="tunes"/></dateline>



                <p>
                    <q>My mind<lb/> when favour'd to get into the quiet has<lb/> enjoy'd a
                        comfortable state of tranquility;<lb/> but thro’ sundry requests of the
                        natives<lb/> also as the white people in passing up &amp;<lb/> down this
                            <geogName ref="alleg">river</geogName> make this house a stoping<lb/>
                        place -and many travelers latterly calling<lb/> some being detain'd- has
                        occaisoned us<lb/> some difficulty in sitting quietly down<lb/> in our
                        religious opportunities. Oh that<lb/> we may be enabled thro’ all
                        difficulties to<lb/> dwell near that fountain, from whence<lb/> preservation
                        and heavenly instruction<lb/> flows</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-01-29">1 mo 29</date><placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> - From her Diary –- forward 9 leaves:</p>

                <p>
                    <date when="1806-02-22">2 Month 22nd</date> To her sister <persName ref="mshar1"
                        >MS</persName>. <q>When I wrote<lb/> to <persName ref="jshar1"
                            >father</persName> I mentioned that we expected<lb/> to build a house
                        neart this, for a school<lb/> house which is now accomplished, and<lb/>
                        altho’ the weather much of the time since<lb/> has been stormy and the
                            <geogName ref="alleg">river</geogName> difficult<lb/> to cross, yet we
                        have not been unimploy'd.</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>As soap making is a novel to most <lb/>
                        <pb n="28" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_28"/> of the Indians nay many of them<lb/>
                        seldom or never wash their clothes or even<lb/> their hands or face- To
                        impress their<lb/> minds with <space/> habits of cleanliness appear'd<lb/>
                        to us the first necessary and important<lb/> step- accordingly in the fall
                        we proposed<lb/> to them, to save their ashes and fat, and when<lb/> our
                        house was ready we would teach them<lb/> to make soap – for when they bring
                        their grists<lb/> to mill in their canoes the materials could<lb/> easily be
                        brought with in them – for they<lb/>
                        <del>generally</del> live 10 or 12 m each way generally on the<lb/> oppesite
                        side of the <geogName ref="alleg">river</geogName>. tho’ their
                        principal<lb/> town is within 3 m.- There has been several<lb/> girls out of
                        6 or 8 families who have at<lb/> different times attended, and who
                        appear'd<lb/> anxious to learn- they were much pleas'd<lb/> with having a
                        considerable quantity of<lb/> good soap to take home with them.<lb/> between
                        whiles they nit and spin a little.<lb/> they bring provisions and cook for
                        themselves;<lb/> we shew'd them our way to make indian bread <lb/>
                        <pb n="29" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_29"/> and they say they like it much the
                        best-<lb/> if way opens we mean to teach them to<lb/> spell-- The plan
                        appeared to be well re-<lb/> ceiv'd by both sexes-one of the chiefs
                        said<lb/> “That was the very thing” -- If half a do-<lb/> zen of our <add
                            place="above">girls</add> in their native dress should un-<lb/>
                        expectedly pass thro’ the entry at <placeName>West Town</placeName><lb/>
                        what an admiration it would raise- for the<lb/> contrast is great.- and
                        their is a satisfaction<lb/> in trying to instruct them- notwithstand-<lb/>
                        ing their great ignorance- their souls also<lb/> are equally as precious in
                        the sight of the<lb/> Supreme Being as ours. -- At unexpect-<lb/> edly
                        receiving a packet of letters she says<lb/> Well dear sister I have been
                        endeavour-<lb/> ing in all things to be instructed whether<lb/> to be full
                        or empty, to abound or suffer<lb/> want - I find you have entertain'd
                        an<lb/> idea that I have enjoy'd some comfot-<lb/> able hours since my
                        residence in this<lb/> solatery abode, which has truly been<lb/> the case:
                        but alass! an uninterrupted <lb/>
                        <pb n="30" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_30"/> sunshine is not always best for
                        us.<lb/> The time of the arival of the last pack-<lb/> et, and the preceding
                        week was a proving<lb/> season-- here I was, no change of society,<lb/> no
                        neighbouring meeting where perhaps<lb/> I might receive a crum - Well it
                        will<lb/> cause me to get deeper and to know<lb/> that my dependance must
                        alone be on<lb/> Divine help. -- I trust it was a season<lb/> of renew'd
                        instruction to me.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1806-03-22">3 Month 22nd</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <q>Dear cousin, Previous to the<lb/> reception of thy letter, the tidings
                        of<lb/> the decease of your precious sister had<lb/> reached us- and I
                        feelingly sympathiz'd<lb/> with you. Truly it must be a great con-<lb/>
                        solation in believing she was prepar'd<lb/> for her awful change, which I
                        have no<lb/> doubt was the case. Oh that it may<lb/> have an awakening
                        tendency on those of<lb/> her contemporaries who attended the<lb/> solemn
                        scene. Tryals of this sort and<lb/> many others frequently occur during <lb/>
                        <pb n="31" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_31"/> our pilgrimage thro’ life; but it
                        is<lb/> written all things will work together<lb/> for good to them who love
                        and fear the<lb/> Lord.</q> --</p>
                <p>
                    <q>The Indians are increasing in in-<lb/> dustreous habits. At a late council<lb/>
                        <del>they</del> held among themselves they agreed<lb/> and information was
                        sent to the absent<lb/> tees - that at a certain stated time<lb/> each one
                        mut relinquesh their hunting<lb/> and be in readiness to attend to the<lb/>
                        labors of the field, being sensible that<lb/> last spring a loss was
                        sustained by<lb/> not earlier applying themselves to it</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1806-05-11">5 Month 11</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To me <q>Thou requested an infor-<lb/> matory letter respecting both ourselves
                        &amp;<lb/> the improvements of the natives: as to<lb/> the latter but little
                        advancement is yet<lb/> made among the females-not owing I<lb/> think to our
                        neglect- the charge we are<lb/> intrusted with by our society and
                        expect<lb/> ed to give samples of its concern we often <lb/>
                        <pb n="32" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_32"/> feel weighty and important - and
                        have<lb/> set times to confer together with a<lb/> view, to keep the subject
                        lively, and to<lb/> seek after a plan, that may be most<lb/> conducive to
                        their improvement.- and<lb/> often among ourselves express a concern<lb/>
                        that we do so little.- yet when we reflect<lb/> that we are endeavouring to
                        do the best<lb/> we can, labouring to keep in the patience,<lb/> improving
                        every favourable opportunity<lb/> that may offer - way may yet open for<lb/>
                        our encouragement -- The children<lb/> of Israel in their journey thro’ the
                        wil-<lb/> derness were directed when they saw<lb/> no way to go forward to
                        stand still.<lb/> and way open'd beyond their expectation.</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>I have had for some time past hum-<lb/> bly to crave for patience both
                        inwardly<lb/> and outwardly, and have laboured to<lb/> seek after that
                        wisdom that is able to<lb/> direct-- Thou knowest there are sea-<lb/> sons
                        when discouragements will assails us in <lb/>
                        <pb n="33" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_33"/> all weighty undertakings but if we
                        en-<lb/>deavor to dwell near to the fountain<lb/> of life, light may be
                        permitted to<lb/> shine as our of a dark place -- and to<lb/> own the
                        necessity of those proving sea-<lb/>sons and not to glory in any act of<lb/>
                        our own—</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>I do not mean to convey discourage-<lb/>ments relative to the concern-- for I
                        think<lb/> the work is progressing-- but great matters<lb/> all at once must
                        not be looked for.<lb/> Many of the men this spring appear in<lb/> good
                        earnest to have more cleared land<lb/> and enclosed fields, but they long
                        esta<lb/>blished custom of having the women in<lb/> their cornfield is not
                        easily relinquish'd.<lb/> With respect to ourselves we enjoy good
                        health,<lb/> live agreeably, have a comfortable hose &amp;c.<lb/> the
                        prospect of a good crop of grain (but<lb/> a barn to receive it will have to
                        be built)<lb/> the improvements that are gradually<lb/> making on our farm
                        looks pleasant which <lb/>
                        <pb n="34" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_34"/> added to the returning spring, feels
                        animat-<lb/> ing-- The sawmill has steadily been<lb/> kept going and many
                        thousand feet of<lb/> boards set in rafts down the river to
                                <unclear><placeName ref="pitts"
                        >Pitt[sburgh]</placeName></unclear></q>-</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1806-05-25">5 mo 25th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To her Uncle <persName>WS</persName>. <q>We have lately<lb/> had a visit from
                        the <persName ref="ichap1">Agent</persName> placed by gov-<lb/> ernment of
                        the six nations.- he resides at<lb/>
                        <placeName ref="buffa">Buffoloe</placeName> about 80 miles from this
                        place-<lb/> The Indians on this <geogName ref="alleg">river</geogName> had
                        not receiv'd<lb/> a visit from him since he was intrusted<lb/> with his
                        office- and we being entire strain-<lb/> gers to him and his sentiments,
                        respecting<lb/> our being here on the errent we are- we were<lb/> anxious to
                        have an interview with him.<lb/> The next day after his arival at <placeName
                            ref="colds">Cold spring</placeName><lb/> he had the Indians collected
                        (our men at-<lb/> tended). He communicated many pertinent<lb/> remarks to
                        them, suitably adapted to their<lb/> capacities; endeavouring to impress on
                        their<lb/> minds, the advantage of industry and<lb/> sobriety, and the
                        cultivation of their land.<lb/> Requesting them to be careful to bring <lb/>
                        <pb n="35" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_35"/> up their children to labor;
                        endeavouring<lb/> to convince them of the advantage it<lb/> is to farmers to
                        live seperate from each<lb/> other and not in little towns. -- A sil-<lb/>
                        versmith had made many exertions<lb/> to settle among the Indians,
                        which<lb/> we entirely disapproved - - The <persName ref="ichap1"
                            >Agent</persName><lb/> desired them not to suffer him to come<lb/> on
                        their land, for we would get their<lb/> money for broaches and bobs
                        that<lb/> would be of no use to them. for when<lb/> they wanted a yoke of
                        oxen, if they<lb/> had money they could go among the<lb/> white people and
                        get them, but if<lb/> you take a basketfull of these broach-<lb/> es they
                        will not take them.- he also descanted<lb/> on the great benifit of having
                        the Qua-<lb/> kers among them, and the advantages<lb/> of the mills;
                        signifying there were no<lb/> people who had done more for them<lb/> than
                        they had-- He came home with<lb/> our young men, and the eve was spent <lb/>
                        <pb n="36" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_36"/> in agreeable conversation. he
                        intimated<lb/> that the experiment of civilizing a na-<lb/> tion of Indians
                        he had not seen ful-<lb/> ly tryed - but could discouver no more<lb/> of a
                        wild nature in them <space/> than pre-<lb/> vaild among the whites. provide
                        the oppor-<lb/> tunity of education was the same.<lb/> He said it was a
                        great undertaking for<lb/> us to leave our near connections and fri<add
                            place="above">[en]ds</add><lb/> but necesity call'd loudly for some<lb/>
                        attention to be given them- signifying<lb/> he had heard of our society
                        giving them<lb/> some assistance, but had no idea so much<lb/> was done-- On
                        parting with him we<lb/> had his good will and wishes for our<lb/>
                        success</q>--</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-06-20">6 mo 20</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> from her diary <q>A fine refreshing<lb/> rain after a week of warm dry
                        weather<lb/> all kinds of vegitation is revived<lb/> but my poor mind feels
                        dull and lan-<lb/> guid, and the necessity of having faith<lb/> and patience
                        under every dispensation <lb/>
                        <pb n="37" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_37"/> that may be alloted me. that thro’
                        heights<lb/> and depths I may at seasons, be favour'd<lb/> to partake, if
                        but a crumb of that bread,<lb/> that nourishes and strengthens the
                        soul;<lb/> is what my spirit earnestly breaths for</q>-</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1806-06-26">6 mo 26th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To her sister <persName ref="eshar1">ES</persName> -- <q>The recital of thy<lb/>
                        short excersion in the country revived a<lb/> recent visit made by me to
                            <placeName ref="colds">Cold Spring</placeName><lb/> an Indian town- and
                        I was led to<lb/> view the contrast- As true a picture of<lb/> mine cannot
                        be formed in <add place="above">thy</add> ideas, as<lb/> thine can in mine--
                        however to make<lb/> a begining -- As the cornfields have lately<lb/> call'd
                        the attention of the women from<lb/> their spining it afforded us some
                        leisure;<lb/> and I seized the opportunity to visit<lb/>
                        <space/> them in their own houses- <persName ref="jtayl1">Jacob
                            Taylor</persName><lb/> going on business to the town, and offer'd<lb/>
                        to escort me there-- when we came to the<lb/>
                        <geogName ref="alleg">river</geogName> an Indian with a canoe being
                        there<lb/> who cheerfully took us across- I had a<lb/> pleasant walk up the
                            <geogName ref="alleg">river</geogName>, viewing the <lb/>
                        <pb n="38" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_38"/>
                        <geogName ref="allmo">mountains</geogName> on the opposite side
                        intermix'd<lb/> with narrow vallies clothed with spontaness<lb/> herbage for
                        the nourishment of the dumb<lb/> beasts-- when we arived in the
                        subburbs<lb/> of the town we were haild by some of the<lb/> inhabitants to
                        know where we were bound<lb/> to- <persName ref="jtayl1">Jacob</persName>
                        inform'd them that I purposed<lb/> spending the day among them, and by
                        and<lb/> by would call on <hi rend="underline">them</hi>- as his business
                        did<lb/> not lead him far thro’ the town, he shew me the house I was<lb/>
                        bound too then left me- Mockensons I<lb/> have found to be a pleasant
                        covering for<lb/> the feet in dry weather and my last sum-<lb/> mers pair
                        being worn out, I call'd on this<lb/> woman who made them, to be speak
                        an-<lb/> other pair-- when I came to the door, I<lb/> saluted her in their
                        way. <hi rend="underline">schano</hi> ah schano<lb/> she reply'd- looking
                        pleasantly- her five<lb/> little folks being aroud- I invited my<lb/> self
                        in, also to a seat which I took on<lb/> the end of a long bench- the day
                        was<lb/> warm yet she was churning close by the <lb/>
                        <pb n="39" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_39"/> fire-- I regreted the want of their
                        lan-<lb/> guage to instruct her how to manage it.<lb/> I cannot converse
                        with them tho’ make<lb/> some awkward attempts-- when she was<lb/>
                        <add>done</add> she took her seat by me admiring my knit-<lb/> ting which I
                        had in my hand- I also<lb/> (on purpose for them to try) had provided<lb/>
                        an other stocking which I then handed<lb/> her, using my utmost endeavours
                        to instruct<lb/> her. she was, tho’ intent in learning very<lb/> awkward-
                        one of her neighbours coming in<lb/> tryed it also - but to return - after
                        churn-<lb/> ing was done she washed a bowl, and with<lb/> the assistance of
                        a ladle collected and<lb/> slightly worked the butter- then pour'd<lb/> it
                        (for it was like oil) into a pail of<lb/> water, where it remained a few
                        minutes<lb/> then she again worked it with her ladle<lb/> and salting it she
                        sat it by me on the<lb/> end of the bench (there being perhaps 4lb)<lb/>
                        with a piece of unleavened corn bread<lb/> and an old knife, and invited me
                        to dine <lb/>
                        <pb n="40" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_40"/> giving me for drink- buttermilk (how
                        differ<lb/> ent from thy dinner at Aunts) in the mean<lb/> time two girls
                        (perhaps 10 and 12 years of age)<lb/> who had frequently been at <placeName
                            ref="tunes">Tunesassah</placeName> came<lb/> inviting me to their house.
                        they ran before<lb/> and prepared a seat for me by their mo-<lb/> ther who
                        was sitting at the door weaving<lb/> a belt curiously decorated with
                        beads.<lb/> The eldest impatient to try <hi rend="underline">her</hi> hand
                        at<lb/> knitting-and her sister <del>clost by</del> on her knees<lb/> clost
                        by gazing with pleasing attention to<lb/> to see the dexterity of her
                        fingers- in a few<lb/> minutes she performed much better than<lb/> the woman
                        did in half an hour-- when<lb/> she got in the way of it I left it with
                        her<lb/> and made several visits in the upper<lb/> part of the town. When I
                        return'd she<lb/> told me by her fingers that she had knit<lb/> six needles-
                        and that 30 stitches were on a<lb/> needle-- she reluctantly parted with
                        it<lb/> but time urged me homewards, having<lb/> on my way several calls yet
                        to make</q></p>

                <pb n="41" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_41"/>

                <p>
                    <q>I had victuals at another place set for me<lb/> which my paper, as I have in
                        view some other<lb/> thing to mention to thee, will give me no<lb/> room to
                        describe. I got thro’ and to the<lb/> fording place about six- where 2
                        families<lb/> live who in turn were to share of my visit<lb/> and who I
                        expected to take me across the<lb/>
                        <geogName rend="alleg">river</geogName> - but my expectations were
                        erroneous<lb/> for the houses were shut and no one to take<lb/> me over--
                        here alone, I took my seat and bun-<lb/> dle of shingles waiting for some
                        favour-<lb/> able event -- with which in ½ an hour I was finish-<lb/> ed,
                        for an Indian coming to the opposite<lb/> side got a canoe and took me over-
                        and<lb/> I returned much pleased with my visits--<lb/> ------ We had the
                        assistance of 10 or more<lb/> Indians for 2 day in raising a barn - the<lb/>
                        day of the eclipse proved to be one- the<lb/> Indians had been told some
                        time before<lb/> that on this day the sun would grow<lb/> dark- but some
                        said “they were sure white<lb/> people could tell no such things,” however <lb/>
                        <pb n="42" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_42"/> when the obscuration began it
                        continued<lb/> growing darker and darker untill for a<lb/> few minutes it
                        became total the atmos-<lb/> phere resembled dark twilight and a<lb/> number
                        of stars made their appearances.<lb/> well says one of the Indians the
                        white<lb/> folks <hi rend="underline">does</hi> know more than us--
                        another<lb/> said he expected a great many of the<lb/> women were a crying,
                        and he had a mind<lb/> to cry too for it look so strange.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1806"/><placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> Copied<lb/>
                    <del><date when="1806-06-30">6 Month 30th</date> To her brother <persName
                            ref="nshar1">NS</persName>.<lb/></del>
                    <q>After passing thru a long winter &amp; part of the spring with<lb/>
                        <del>We were favored after passing, with</del><lb/> but little intercourse,
                        we were favoured to<lb/>
                        <del>but little intercourse (thro’ a long win-</del><lb/>
                        <del><del>ter and part of the spring)</del> to receive<lb/> a number of
                            letters and <del>was</del> were much<lb/> pleased with finding <space/>
                            among<lb/> them one from thee. - and may tell thee and dear sister, tho’ we<lb/>
                            <hi rend="underline">are</hi> far seperated from the bosom<lb/> of
                            society, partaking of many hours<lb/> of retirement that formerly
                            we</del>
                        <lb/>
                        <pb n="43" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_43"/>
                        <del>were in a degree straingers to. yet<lb/> I am thankful that mostly I
                            en-<lb/> joy a quiet resigned mind, and have<lb/> not in the most trying
                            dispensations<lb/> I have experienced since being here,<lb/> thought my
                            lot hard, nor dare indulge<lb/> one murmering thought. -- my relish<lb/>
                            for reading and meditation is much<lb/> increased, and can truly say
                            that ma<lb/> ny comfortable hours have been sacri-<lb/> ficed to these
                            desires-- Altho I<lb/> often feel poor and striped yet as<lb/> patience
                            is abode in the comfort-<lb/> able belief, <del>will</del> prevails that
                            the streams of Divine<lb/> love are extended, to all the sincere
                            hearted<lb/> wherever scatter'd or how ever <del>far</del> remote
                            from<lb/> the bosom of society. <del>will prevail.</del><lb/> The query
                            the yong man put to his Lord<lb/> has of late affectingly accompanied
                            my<lb/> mind. “Good Master what good thing shall<lb/> I do to inherit
                            eternal life-” after enumerat-<lb/> ing several things he added “go sell
                            that thou<lb/> hast and come &amp; follow me.” this was a hard</del>
                        <lb/>
                        <pb n="44" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_44"/>
                        <del>saying to the natural part.- Oh that we<lb/> may have our minds so
                            disengaged from<lb/> the encumbering things of this world that<lb/> the
                            growth of the pure seed may not in the<lb/> least be retarded. -- The
                            station of parents<lb/> are very important. -- children <add
                                place="above">are</add> often improperly<lb/> desiring
                                <del>wanting</del> those things they see on others<lb/> when they
                            are young is the time to guard against future dif-<lb/> ficulties by
                            nipping things in the bud, and endeavouring<lb/> to instill useful
                            instruction into their tender minds. You<lb/> feel the charge then why
                            should I thus write.</del></q>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-01-29">1806 <add>1 mo</add> 29th</date><placeName
                        key="tunes"/></dateline>

                <p>
                    <del>From her diary -- <q>Letters were receiv'd<lb/> to day informing of the
                            death of dear cousin<lb/>
                            <persName ref="hjack2">Hannah Jacksons</persName> mother-- she is now
                            no<lb/> doubt reaping the benefit of a wellspent<lb/> life-- may we who
                            are left behind so fol-<lb/> low her footsteps that when our final<lb/>
                            change comes, we may be prepared; -<lb/> time to us all is uncertain,
                            and the<lb/> period when we shall be call'd hence<lb/> we know
                        not.</q></del>
                    <add>turn back 9 leaves</add></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-18">9 mo 18th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To <persName ref="jshar1">me</persName>
                    <q>I dwell but little on the<lb/> subject of receiving visits from my friends or
                        when I shall <lb/>
                        <pb n="45" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_45"/> again be with you-- In regard to
                        thy<lb/> debilitated situation and want of health<lb/> or whether we shall
                        again meet in muta-<lb/> bility, I hope submission and fortitude<lb/> will
                        be my companions and not only<lb/> in <hi rend="underline">that</hi>, but
                        thro’ the varied dispensations<lb/> that may be my lot to encounter.
                        but<lb/> dear father pleas to accept of the feeble<lb/> breathings of thy
                        daughter, that as thy<lb/> natural abilities fail, and infirmities<lb/> with
                        age come on thou mayest be<lb/> preserved a live in that that will
                        endure<lb/> beyond time. -- I was pleased to hear<lb/> from my dear aged
                            <persName ref="mmend1">grandmother</persName> and<lb/> wish to be
                        affectionately remembred to<lb/> her. I have often reverted to sensa-<lb/>
                        tions impressed on my mind when<lb/> in company with some dear friends<lb/>
                        near their close of time here, also on<lb/> visiting some infirm ones who
                        were<lb/> confin'd and for these I often feel a<lb/> lively
                    sympathy.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="46" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_46"/>
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-27">27th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>



                <p> From her diary <space/>
                    <q>This eve my dear<lb/> brother <persName ref="jshar1">JS</persName>. arived.
                        it was a joyful meet-<lb/> ing to us both. -- he brought me a num-<lb/> ber
                        of letters from my dear connexions<lb/> Oh how many blessing do I
                        receive.<lb/> may I ever walk worthy thereof and<lb/> quietly acquies in the
                        way cast up<lb/> for me - with a heart devoted to love<lb/> fear and obey my
                        Heavenly Father, is<lb/> the frequent breathing of my spirit.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-28">28th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To her sister <persName ref="pshar1">P.S.</persName> -- <q>If our school
                        house<lb/> could be fill'd with girls learning to spin<lb/> knit &amp;c the
                        days would pass pleasantly away.<lb/> A number when their corn is gathered
                        gives<lb/> us to expect their company. -- The man’s<lb/> wife who has the
                        sawmill is a weaver- and<lb/> could we have a piece of the Indians
                        spin-<lb/> ing for her this winter to weave, it would<lb/> prove a strong
                        incitement for more of<lb/> them next spring to sow flax. The com-<lb/>
                        mittee who has lately been among us <lb/>
                        <pb n="47" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_47"/> say they are much improved in
                        cleanli-<lb/> ness- and in many little matters <hi rend="underline"
                        >I</hi><lb/> think they have gaind instruction, which<lb/> will open the way
                        for greater. It is<lb/> no small task - to begin with girls 13,<lb/> 14 and
                        15 years of age - who are ignorant<lb/> of all most every thing but howing
                        corn<lb/> and chipping wood-- the wheel runs<lb/> back - the yarn tangles -
                        it twists into<lb/> curls, the end runs down, and such<lb/> like-- which
                        requires patience both for<lb/> the teacher and learner -- Our know-<lb/>
                        ledge of their language is still very<lb/> limited - so that we have shew
                        them<lb/> by signs - we have to keep up a plea-<lb/> sant countenance- and
                        repeating the<lb/> words by and by you will get in the<lb/> way of it -
                        considerable improvement<lb/> in different branches is already made<lb/> by
                        some</q> --</p>
                <note resp="undetermined"> Not in <persName ref="jshar1">Joshua's</persName></note>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1806-09-30">30th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To a near relation. -- <q>Not without<lb/> casting a longing desire for a free <lb/>
                        <pb n="48" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_48"/> access to those hidden treasures in
                        store<lb/> for the faithful.” is a sentiment<lb/> express'd in closing a
                        subject in thy last-<lb/> and feeling the energy and sincerity<lb/> in which
                        it was penn'd-that my spi-<lb/> rit said amen -- Well knowing if faith-<lb/>
                        fulness is adhered to what this desire<lb/> will produce-- Thou hast pass'd
                        thro’<lb/> some close proving seasons all intended<lb/> for the trial of thy
                        faith and to<lb/> fit thee for further usefulness in thy<lb/> day-- then let
                        not the cross stand in<lb/> the way but give up and the enjoy-<lb/> ment of
                        sweet peace will be thy reward.<lb/> I speak from a small degree of
                        expe<lb/> rience, for after I was given up to this<lb/> service some little
                        prospects opened upon<lb/> my mind accompaned with the belief<lb/> that it
                        was my duty to perform previous<lb/> to leaving my native home-- but
                        alas<lb/> they were like mountains to the natural<lb/> will. In thankfulness
                        I may acknow- <lb/>
                        <pb n="49" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_49"/> ledge that as I laboured to get into
                        the<lb/> quiet, and <del>faith</del> have a resigned mind- I was<lb/>
                        strengthened far beyond my expectation<lb/> to do the little that presented
                        -- my con-<lb/> solation at times has been great, feeling<lb/> that the
                        Divine presence was near when<lb/> the glimmer of light was small. I<lb/>
                        feel cautious of dwelling long on this<lb/> subject lest I squander the
                        little good<lb/> that I conceive has encreas since I be-<lb/> gan to
                        write</q> -</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-10-06">10 mo 3rd in the other 6th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <q>About two weeks ago the com-<lb/> mittee left us, and three days since
                        my<lb/> dear <persName ref="jshar2">brother</persName>. I sensibly feel the
                        strip,<lb/> the sweets that are to be derived from<lb/> society, and in the
                        company of our near<lb/> relations assumed their native force,<lb/> and so
                        powerfully prevailed that had I<lb/> indulged those impressions they
                        would<lb/> soon have made me discontented and<lb/> unhappy in my present
                        retired situati-<lb/> on, and for a season they did unsettle <lb/>
                        <pb n="50" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_50"/> my mind; but as I endeavoured to
                        cast<lb/> them of and seek for that resignation<lb/> which had heretofore
                        not only proved as a<lb/> consolation but at seasons as a healing<lb/>
                        cordial to my relaxed mind, I was<lb/> led to view the motive and cause why
                        I<lb/> was thus sepperated and a comfortable<lb/> submission ensued. I was
                        favour'd to<lb/> experience the precious overshadowing of<lb/> Divine love,
                        my mind was humbled<lb/> under the Heavenly canopy, and for a few<lb/> days
                        I seldom have experienc'd so quiet a<lb/> repose. Oh may I be enabled to
                        render<lb/> the gratitude that is due to my great and<lb/> good Benefactor
                        for the many favours<lb/> dispens'd to me a poor unworthy creature.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1806-10-19">19th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <q>For near two weeks past I have<lb/> had a painful gathering in my thumb.<lb/>
                        I have had in this slight affliction re-<lb/>
                        <unclear>newedly</unclear> to seek for patience <lb/>
                        <pb n="51" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_51"/> and to crave thro’ all trials I may
                        be<lb/> preserved from the least shadow of mur-<lb/> muring - and a ray of
                        hope reviv'd with<lb/> a renewal of strength.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline>1807<lb/>
                    <date when="1807-02-21">2 Month 21st</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <q>To a niece who had lately lost her<lb/> companion. -- The perusal of thy
                        val-<lb/> uable letter was truly satisfactory. It<lb/> was comfortable to
                        find that thou was<lb/> favoured with so much fortitude and<lb/>
                        resignation. It is enough my dear to<lb/> experience a Physician near to
                        heal all<lb/> our maladies; may we in our varied<lb/> allotments daily
                        endeavour so to walk,<lb/> as to witness our minds more and more<lb/>
                        redeemed from the perishing enjoyments<lb/> of this world. For what is self
                        with all its<lb/> acquired arts or what is there here that<lb/> is worth
                        placing our dependance on.</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>The winter thus far with us has been<lb/> very severe -- The ground these
                        three months<lb/> past been covered with snow. - but we have <lb/>
                        <pb n="52" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_52"/> a good warm house to shelter us from
                        the<lb/> northern blasts.</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>A number of Indian girls has this<lb/> winter given us their company -
                        some<lb/> of whom has made an incouraging prog-<lb/> ress - a short piece is
                        now in the loom<lb/> principally the industry of two girls.<lb/> - another
                        piece is on the way - and a con-<lb/> siderable quantity of very good
                        thread<lb/> has been manufacter'd and distributed<lb/> among them generally.
                        - Those two<lb/> girls are desirous of having wheels of<lb/> their own, and
                        spin at home - and<lb/> their request we mean to grant.</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>Altho’ the disposition among the<lb/> men to relieve their women in the<lb/>
                        labour of the field, has greatly en-<lb/> creas'd; yet when the time for
                        plant-<lb/> ing corn comes, the females have to<lb/> give their assistance
                        more or less, thro’<lb/> the summer. still there are intervals<lb/> if they
                        were so disposed, that might <lb/>
                        <pb n="53" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_53"/> be devoted to spinning knitting
                        &amp;c<lb/> an increas of exertion on their part<lb/> would <space/> be
                        satisfactory, but pati-<lb/> ence on ours is necessary.</q></p>
                <note resp="undetermined"> Not in the other</note>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1807-05-24">5 mo 24th</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To her parents. -- <q>I have<lb/> been thinkin whether in my situa-<lb/> tion,
                        it would not be advisable to<lb/> request of our kind friend <persName
                            ref="fking1">Francis King</persName><lb/> the liberty of making his
                        house my<lb/> home, for a part of this summer,<lb/> where I could have the
                        company of<lb/> my own sort of people. but upon<lb/> weighing the prospect
                        the preponder-<lb/> ating scale was in favour of remain<lb/> ing in my
                        present place. I hope<lb/> you will not be uneasy about me. my<lb/> health
                        is mostly good, and my<lb/> mind resign'd, for which favours<lb/> I am truly
                        thankful. The pro-<lb/> posed visit from some of you cre<lb/> ates pleasant
                        sensations, but when<lb/> I view the distance, the roughness of <lb/>
                        <pb n="54" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_54"/> of the road, and how unaccustom'd you
                        have<lb/> latterly been of riding on horseback, I<lb/> feel unworthy of such
                        attention.<lb/> yet I do count on having sister <persName ref="eshar1"
                            >Edith</persName>’s<lb/> company, and as for thine my dear-<lb/> ly
                        belov'd <persName ref="jshar1">father</persName> thou knowest thy abil-<lb/>
                        ity to encounter such a journey better<lb/> than I do. I hope prudence will
                        dictate<lb/> rightly. and tho’ it will be a close trial<lb/> to my dear
                            <persName ref="atrim1">mother</persName> to give the up yet<lb/> if it
                        is right <del><unclear>I Hope</unclear></del> she will receive<lb/> strength
                        so to do. and if we are favour'd<lb/> to <add place="above">meet</add> my
                        desire for myself is to be in a<lb/> compos'd state of mind.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline><date when="1807-07-03">7 mo 3</date>. <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> To her <persName ref="atrim1">mother</persName> -- <q>I anticipate<lb/> in about
                        two weeks the arival of some<lb/> of our near relations. To know
                        whether<lb/> they are coming and the time of setting off<lb/> would be
                        gratifying to me. A fear<lb/> at times assails me mind least I shall<lb/>
                        lack of that patience and fortitude my<lb/> present situation demands. Tho’
                        of <lb/>
                        <pb n="55" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_55"/> late time has pass'd comfortably
                        along<lb/> feeling my <space/> faith a little strengthen'd<lb/> and my trust
                        in the alone source of<lb/> preservation renew'd</q>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1807-07-22">7 mo 22nd</date>
                    <placeName key="tunes"/></dateline>
                <p> From her diary -- <q>A number<lb/> of circumstances has latterly accured<lb/>
                        that has felt trying yet thro’ all I have<lb/> endeavour'd to keep quiet,
                        believing a<lb/> way will be made for that which is<lb/> right; and to be
                        resign'd to the event<lb/> be it as it may is what I ardently<lb/>
                    wish.</q></p>
                <lb/>
                <p> This is the last account kept by<lb/> her self or we have from any of her<lb/>
                    letters. Believing her situation claimd<lb/> the company of some of her
                    relations<lb/> my daughter <persName ref="eshar1">Edith</persName> and myself
                    pre-<lb/> par'd and the <date when="1807-07-12">12 of the 7 mo 1807</date>
                    left<lb/> home and in 13 days ariv'd at <placeName ref="tunes">Tunasas-<lb/>
                        sah</placeName>. The family received us with express-<lb/> ions of joy in
                    their countenances. particular- <lb/>
                    <pb n="56" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_56"/> -ly gratifying was our arival to <persName
                        ref="rcoop1">Rachel</persName><lb/> for her mind was sinking under
                    discou-<lb/> ragements and at the point of desparing<lb/> of our <del>not</del>
                    geting there. She with the<lb/> rest of the family were in the enjoyment<lb/> of
                    health. Eleven day were agreeably spent<lb/> in free conversation, mutually glad
                    after<lb/> a sepparation of more than two years<lb/> to be in each other’s
                    society</p>
            </div>
            <div type="narrative">
                <dateline><date when="1807-08-05">The 5th of the 8 mo</date>. <placeName key="tunes"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> She was taken un-<lb/> well, and in two days <del>in</del> the <del>day
                        was</del><lb/>
                    <del><unclear/></del> prospect of her recovery look'd<lb/> gloomy. She was given
                    over by the Dr.<lb/> at this moving period. I thought it<lb/> best to make her
                    acquainted with her<lb/> critical situation, that the probability<lb/> of her
                    being raised was small.<lb/> after a<lb/> short pause she reply'd - <q>I would
                        have<lb/> been willing to have continued a while<lb/> longer with my dear
                        husband assisted<lb/> in the concern we came here about, and<lb/> to have
                        return'd with him to our friends; <lb/>
                        <pb n="57" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_57"/> but if it is not to be so I feel
                        resign'd.<lb/> I said my dear child I hope and believe<lb/> thou art
                        prepared to leave this world.<lb/></q> with much composure and a solid
                    coun-<lb/> tenance she answered, <q>I have been en-<lb/> deavouring to stand
                        resign'd and have<lb/> my mind prepared if such a change<lb/> should take
                        place- and I now feel quite<lb/> easy under a full belief that there is
                        a<lb/> place of rest prepared for me.</q> A while<lb/> after she looked very
                    affectionately at me<lb/> and said <q>My dear father, I am glad<lb/> thou art
                        here. I heard of thy being poor-<lb/> ly, and was fearful thou wouldst
                        not<lb/> be able to encounter so ardious a journey<lb/> therefore could
                        never urge thy coming<lb/> but I am glad thou art here, and I<lb/> hope thou
                        will get safely home.</q></p>
                <p> Notwithstanding her very tryed situation<lb/> her mind seem'd carried above it
                    compos'd<lb/> and resign'd with no dejection in her<lb/> countenance. -- The
                    advice of another <lb/>
                    <pb n="58" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_58"/> Physician being needful and one
                    living<lb/> within 30 miles, tho' thro' a wilderness<lb/> mountainous country,
                    he was sent for.<lb/> The Doctors on confering together, believ'd<lb/> it not in
                    their power to give her relief.<lb/> After they had come to this conclusion<lb/>
                    I took my seat by her bedside. she<lb/> look'd a few minutes at me then,<lb/>
                    with her natural voice and much sim-<lb/> plicity asked me what the doctors
                    thought<lb/> of her. I told her, her situation was<lb/> so difficult they
                    apprehended they could<lb/> administer no relief. she reply'd<lb/> why do they
                    think so? - then pausing<lb/> awhile said <q>I must be content</q> and<lb/> in a
                    short time adding, <q>I feel resign'd.</q></p>
                <p> She delivered herself with much ease and<lb/> freedom, not appearing to be
                    distress'd<lb/> or cast down, no heaviness in her<lb/> countenance or fear in
                    her eyes. Shortly<lb/> after her first Physician came to<lb/> take leave of her,
                    and taking her <lb/>
                    <pb n="59" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_59"/> by the hand said, <q>Well Rachel I
                        have<lb/> thought of going, are you willing?<lb/></q> She answered <q>I do
                        not see any thing<lb/> more thou canst do for me, I believe<lb/> thou hast
                        done the best thou couldst.<lb/></q> he then asked her if she felt
                        <q>resign'd to<lb/> her fate.</q> she said she thought she did;<lb/>
                    <q>but it is a trial to me to leave my<lb/> dear husband so far from his
                        friends<lb/> yet we are poor dependant beings we<lb/> must submit.</q> Then
                    pausing she added<lb/>
                    <q>Doctor thou seest there is no age ex-<lb/> empt from death, the middle
                        aged<lb/> are call'd away as well as those further<lb/> advanced. how
                        necessary then for us always<lb/> to be prepar'd.</q> -- Being some
                    reliev'd<lb/> the forepart of this (which was the third<lb/> of her sickness)
                    she was cheerful tho’ very<lb/> sweet giving her sister directions about<lb/>
                    some things, also saying to her sister<lb/>
                    <q>it is my request that you will ever<lb/> remember my dear <persName
                            ref="bcoop1">Benjamin</persName> as a <lb/>
                        <pb n="60" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_60"/> brother for he has been a very kind
                        hus-<lb/> band to me and I have often profited<lb/> by his instructive
                        conversation.</q></p>
                <p> On the fourth day of her illness a change<lb/> took place and for a few day the
                    flattering<lb/> expectation that her life would be pre-<lb/> serv'd was
                    indulged, but a fever with<lb/> some other unfavourable symptoms seiz'd<lb/> her
                    which seemed to baffle all the efforts<lb/> that was given for her relief, and
                    felt nature<lb/> not having strength to resist yielded to their<lb/> powerful
                    assaults. -- she weaken'd fast<lb/> yet appear'd to lay with an easy mind.<lb/>
                    her bodily pain was great and hav-<lb/> ing found some relief by being
                    mov'd<lb/> often made the request. She would<lb/> look very affectionately at me
                    at times<lb/> and say, <q>Well father I feel very un-<lb/> easy, I believe I
                        must be mov'd a little,<lb/> I suppose thou wilt think me very<lb/>
                        bothersome, but it gives me some relief.</q><lb/> Tho’ it was moving to see
                    her so <lb/>
                    <pb n="61" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_61"/> afflicted yet I was glad I was with<lb/>
                    her, she appear'd so much in the inno-<lb/> cency, no anxiety manifested
                    concern-<lb/> ing her situation, her mind much<lb/> resign'd and a willingness
                    to comply<lb/> and act just as was thought best.</p>
                <p> The day she deceas'd her pain much<lb/> abating, she lay more easy tho’ a
                    high<lb/> fever was still her companion which<lb/> so affected her mind as to
                    cause it to<lb/> be much affloat particularly when in<lb/> a doze. About three
                    Oclock she appear'd<lb/> in fervent supplication tho’ not clearly<lb/>
                    understood, and frequently in the few<lb/> remaining hours that she continued
                    with<lb/> us her mind was similarly engag'd<lb/> not only interceding for
                    herself but others<lb/> which fully evinced that her day would<lb/> close in
                    peace. About this time her<lb/> hands and feet began to grow cold,<lb/> and her
                    pulse to beat more feebly tho’<lb/> very quick. I ask'd her if she knew <lb/>
                    <pb n="62" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_62"/> we were waiting to see her close. she<lb/>
                    said where are you waiting? I answer’d<lb/> around her bed. She reply'd <q>I am
                        very<lb/> low</q> -- About half an hour before her<lb/> departure I took
                    hold of her hand to<lb/> feel if she had a pulse, apprehending<lb/> she was too
                    far gone to notice it, but<lb/> she asked if she had any fever. I replied<lb/>
                    not much -- I then ask'd if she felt<lb/> very sick she answer'd no. I think
                    I<lb/> feel a little recruited, am pretty easy<lb/> and if I had a good place to
                    lay I<lb/> could go to sleep - I said <q>my dear child,<lb/> thou wilt soon be
                        in a sweet sleep.<lb/></q> she replied <q>I believe I shall</q> -- at<lb/>
                    this time a cold sweat was pouring<lb/> from her - and shortly after she said<lb/>
                    <q>I am in such a perspiration that<lb/> I cannot get my mind composed.<lb/> I
                        want to have it settled</q>- having<lb/> frequently thro’ the course of the
                    day<lb/> expressed the same desire -- she present- <lb/>
                    <pb n="63" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_63"/> -ly call'd for a cup of tea - which
                    was<lb/> brought to her - but she was in so great<lb/> a tremor that it was with
                    much diffi-<lb/> culty she drank it, and being sensible of<lb/> her situation
                    she said, <q>I am so discom-<lb/> posed that I can scarcely drink it.</q><lb/>
                    then having a little more she said <q>that<lb/> is sufficient.</q> -- she then
                    altered very<lb/> fast, - and in a few minutes without<lb/> struggle, sigh or
                    groan quietly breath'd<lb/> her last. ---- Thus this hand-<lb/> maid of the
                    Lord, in the meridian of<lb/> life, being in the 36th year of her age<lb/>
                    closed her days and is now without a<lb/> doubt receiving the rewards of her
                    faith-<lb/> fulness.</p>
                <p> A number of the Indian women<lb/> from the first of her illness untill her<lb/>
                    close manifested much concern for her<lb/> recovery, - bringing different kinds
                    of<lb/> herbs and roots for her relief as well as<lb/> giving from time to time
                    their best <lb/>
                    <pb n="64" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_64"/> advice; and when they heard she was<lb/>
                    no more, their countenances manifest-<lb/> ed much sorrow. ---- She departed<lb/>
                    <date when="1807-08-16">16 of the 8mo 1807</date>, ---- the next<lb/> day being
                    fixed on for her burial, invi-<lb/> tations were sent among the In-<lb/> dians,
                    &amp; near 20 of the graver sort attend'd<lb/> principally women, a number
                    coming<lb/> into the room, and after looking at the<lb/> corps in much
                    brokenness quietly took<lb/> their seats untill it was closed, which<lb/> was
                    not untill after a time of solemn<lb/> silence.- Several of the Indians who<lb/>
                    did not come in sent their excuse<lb/> saying, They could not bear to see
                    her<lb/> for the sight would overcome them and<lb/> they would weep aloud. They
                    follow'd<lb/> to the grave in the same becoming<lb/> manner. -- They return’d
                    into the room<lb/> and took their seats for I suppose<lb/> 15 minutes. They were
                    then serv'd with<lb/> fresh bread and in a few minutes <lb/>
                    <pb n="65" facs="SW_RC1805_Page_65"/> after individually shook ha<add
                        place="above">n</add>ds with<lb/> us and bade us farewell, some of<lb/> them
                    saying to us that they were very<lb/> sorry Rachel was taken away but en-<lb/>
                    couraged us to bear the trial patiently<lb/> for such things must happen to
                    the<lb/> white people as well as the Indians.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> lived down the <geogName
                        ref="alleg">river</geogName><lb/> about 12 miles and he came in a few<lb/>
                    days to see us. his countenance mani-<lb/> fested him to be a true
                    sympathizer.<lb/> he said he was very sorry for what<lb/> had happened among us
                    and hoped<lb/> we would not be discourage for this<lb/> was the first since the
                    settlement<lb/> was made among them and that<lb/> such tryals would be the lot
                    of white<lb/> folks as well as Indians. he took<lb/> leave of us with tears in
                    his eyes.</p>


            </div>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI>
