<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei-print.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/tei.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" hkey="global.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Wm. Hartshorne's Journal of Journey to Detroit 1793: Electronic
                    Version</title>

                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Conor Heins</name>
                    <name>Emma Remsberg</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 221 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>This work is the property of the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore
                        College. It may be copied freely by individuals for personal use, research,
                        and teaching (including distribution to classes) as long as this statement
                        of availability is included in the text. It may be linked to freely in
                        Internet editions of all kinds, including for—profit works.</p>
                    <p>Publishers, libraries, and other information providers interested in
                        providing this text in a commercial or non—profit product or from an
                        information server must contact Swarthmore College for licensing and cost
                        information.</p>
                    <p> Scholars interested in changing or adding to these texts by, for example,
                        creating a new edition of the text (electronically or in print) with
                        substantive editorial changes, may do so with the permission of Swarthmore
                        College. This is the case whether the new publication will be made available
                        at a cost or free of charge.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2014">2014</date>
                <idno type="local">Hartshorne_1793</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Native Americans and Quakers: Electronic
                    Collection</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Journals</collection>
                        <idno>Mss003/152</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>1 vol.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>


        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Hartshorne journal is housed at Friends Historical Library, on the campus of
                    Swarthmore College. During 2014 staff of Friends Historical Library and
                    Swarthmore College students began a project to encode seventeen journals which
                    document interaction between Quakers and Native Americans in New York State and
                    Ohio between 1793 and 1806.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Spelling and puncuation are rendered as close as possible to the original.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1793">1793</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Quakers -- Ohio</item>

                        <item>Church and state--Ohio</item>

                        <item>Indian reservations</item>
                        <item>Indians of North America--Missions</item>

                        <item>Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of the Religious Society of Friends</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries</item>
                        <item>Quakers--Political activity</item>

                        <item>Society of Friends--Missions</item>
                        <item>Voyages and Travels</item>

                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>


            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="1" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_03"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-04"/><placeName key="newyo"/></dateline>
                <p> On First Day the <date when="1793-05-04">4th of the 5th Mo 1793</date> at<lb/> 9
                    o'clock in the evening left New York in order<lb/> to attend the Treaty to be
                    held with the Indians<lb/> at <placeName key="sandu">Sandusky</placeName>, near
                    the West end of <geogName key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName>.</p>
                <p> Our company who were going the same<lb/> rout consisted of <persName
                        key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName>, <persName key="wsave1">William
                        Savery</persName>,<lb/>
                    <persName key="rhill1">Rich'd Hillary</persName>, a young Englishman, <persName
                        key="jheck1">John Hackenwelder</persName>, a Minister among the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="moravian">Moravians</orgName>, <persName key="wmcco1">Dr. William
                        McCoskry</persName>, and Captain<lb/> Scott, Commissary to the
                    Commissioners.<lb/> We had an indifferent passage<lb/> up the river, part of the
                    way being<lb/> in the Night, and arrived at <placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName> on the 8th,<lb/> about 5 in the morning.- <placeName
                        key="alban">Albany</placeName> appears<lb/> to be a place of considerable
                    trade, some of<lb/> the Houses are well Built, the streets mostly<lb/> paved,
                    but some of them very narrow and<lb/> irregularly laid out -- here the Low
                    Dutch<lb/> Language is generally spoken, and the<lb/> manners of the inhabitants
                    not esteemed<lb/> very pleasing. At <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> we
                    found <persName key="glinc1">General <lb/>Lincoln</persName>, one of the
                    commissioners, and ChS Stover,<lb/> their Secretary -- upon our arrival with
                    the<lb/> Stores, <persName key="glinc1">General Lincoln</persName> was desirous
                    of going<lb/> immediately to <placeName key="schen">Schenectady</placeName>, and
                    with considerable<lb/> difficulty, and many hours delay, at length<lb/> procured
                    a Horse and Chair, and without an<lb/> Attendant, about 6 in the Evening, set
                    off for that<lb/>
                    <pb n="2" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_05"/> that place -- we tarried all night and<lb/>
                    found very indifferent entertainment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-09">9th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Having procured Waggons we left <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName><lb/>
                    about 8 A.M. and went to <placeName key="schen">Schenectady</placeName>
                    were<lb/> we arrived about 11 -- <placeName key="schen">Schenectady</placeName>
                    lays about<lb/> l6 ½ miles N.W. from <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName>,
                    is a pretty well<lb/> built handsome inland Town, a place of con-<lb/>siderable
                    Trade, being the carrying place between<lb/> the <geogName key="mohaw"
                        >Mohawk</geogName> and <geogName key="huds">Hudson</geogName>'s Rivers --
                    here, as at<lb/>
                    <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName>, the language is Low Dutch. – The
                    Land<lb/> between <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="schen">Schenectady</placeName> is Sandy &amp; poor,<lb/> Timbered
                    chiefly with Pine.- At <placeName key="schen">Schenectady</placeName><lb/> we
                    found prepared for us Eight Boats or Batteaux,<lb/> Six for the Baggage and
                    Stores, that would carry about<lb/> a Ton and a half each, and two larger
                    with<lb/> Awnings for the passengers: We embarked in our<lb/> Boat about 4 P.M.
                    and proceeded seven miles up the <geogName key="mohaw">Mo-<lb/>hawk</geogName>
                    River to Mabee’s, where we lodged.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-10">10th</date>. <placeName key="fhunt"/></dateline>
                <p> We proceeded up the River 15 miles &amp; encamp’d<lb/> near the remains of old
                        <placeName key="fhunt">Fort Hunter</placeName>; two or three<lb/> miles
                    below which we passed by the place formerly<lb/> the residence of <persName
                        key="wjohn1">Sir William Johnson</persName> – We found<lb/> the stream this
                    day very rapid – the Land<lb/> on the Banks of the River between this &amp;
                        <placeName key="schen">Schenectady</placeName><lb/> being very beautiful and
                    fertile – the high Land at a<lb/> distance appearing more rough and
                    uncultivated.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-11">11th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Embark’d about sunrise, with a fair Wind,<lb/> and having most of the way a
                    gentle current,<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_05"/> we hoisted our sails and run 20 miles
                    up<lb/> the River to <persName key="cfry1">Col. Fry</persName>’s, where we
                    dined, a few<lb/> miles below we pass’d by a place call’d <placeName key="fplan"
                        >Fort<lb/> Plane</placeName>, where is a handsome Worship House and
                    other<lb/> good Buildings –- After Dinner proceeded 8 miles<lb/> to Nellis’s
                    Tavern where we lay all Night.- At<lb/> this place were inform’d we were
                    but<lb/> 15 miles from the Waters of <geogName key="susqu"
                        >Susquehanna</geogName>, and<lb/> about 40 from Delaware -
                        <del><gap/></del><lb/><del><gap/></del><lb/>
                    <del>Dutch</del>- Our way this day being through a<lb/> most beautiful and
                    fertile country -- the<lb/> Inhabitants between this and <placeName key="schen"
                        >Schenectady</placeName> are <del>being</del><lb/> mostly low Dutch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="lfall"/></dateline>
                <p> Got to the Little Falls about Noon (call'd 60 miles<lb/> from <placeName
                        key="schen">Schenectady</placeName>) -- here is a carrying Place of<lb/>
                    about one Mile -- the Falls altogether are about<lb/> 40 feet, preparations are
                    now making to<lb/> render them navigable by Locks -- along these<lb/> Falls are
                    fine mill seats, on one of which <persName key="jport1">John<lb/> Porteous
                        Esqr</persName> has erected a very good Grist Mill &amp; saw<lb/> Mill --
                        <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName> and myself were kindly<lb/>
                    entertained by <persName key="fdeza1">Major de Zeng</persName>, superintendent
                    of<lb/> the Canal business at this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-13">13th</date>. <placeName key="gerfl"/></dateline>
                <p> Got our Boats goods, &amp;ca. above the Falls<lb/> and proceeded up the River
                    about 6 miles<lb/> to a place call'd <placeName key="gefla">Fort Herkimar, or
                        the German<lb/> Flatts</placeName> -- The Country hereabout being very<lb/>
                    <pb n="4" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_06"/> very beautiful, and has the appearance of
                    great<lb/> fertility -­ the inhabitants chiefly the descendants<lb/> of Germans
                    by whom the high Dutch Language is<lb/> mostly spoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="fschy"/></dateline>
                <p> In our progress this day we found the Country<lb/> but thinly inhabited, but we
                    were informed the<lb/> number of settlers were rapidly increasing<lb/>
                    principally by immigration from New England<lb/> and there is every reason to
                    believe that in a few<lb/> years it will become well cultivated and
                    plentiful<lb/> -- in the evening we stopt at <placeName key="fschy">Fort
                        Schuyler</placeName><lb/> 24 miles from <placeName key="gefla">Fort
                        Herkimar</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="fstan"/></dateline>
                <p> After breakfast several of us went 4 miles<lb/> up the River on foot to
                        <placeName key="white">Whites Town</placeName>, the residence<lb/> of
                        <persName key="abree1">Arthur Breese</persName>, to whom I had letters --
                    it<lb/> is quite a new settlement but has the appear-<lb/>ance of becoming a
                    place of note, being<lb/> situated in a fast improving Country, and<lb/> has
                    already in it large Stores, and the finest<lb/> Pot Ash works that we have yet
                    seen -- at 4<lb/> P.M. stopt at <persName key="bsteu1">Baron
                    Steuben</persName>'s Landing on the<lb/> North side of the River, from which to
                    his House<lb/> we were inform'd the distance was 7 miles<lb/> and 9 to
                        <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName>.- At 7 in the evening<lb/>
                    arrived at the Carrying Place at <placeName key="fstan">Fort
                    Stanwix</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-16">16th</date>. <geogName key="wcree"/></dateline>
                <p> The situation of <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName>, (although
                    upon<lb/> a 1evel plain, almost surrounded by low Marshey<lb/>
                    <pb n="5" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_06"/> Land), must be very much elevated, as
                    it<lb/> lays about half way between the <geogName key="mohaw">Mohock</geogName> &amp;<lb/>
                    <geogName key="wcree">Wood Creek</geogName>, the first taking an eastern
                    course<lb/> to the sea, the latter running Westerly to the<lb/> Lakes.­ We were
                    inform 'd a Town was<lb/> laid out near the old Fort, and that preparations<lb/>
                    ware making to erect Buildings.- a Canal<lb/> is intended to be out perhaps the
                    ensuing Summer<lb/> from the <geogName key="mohaw">Mohock</geogName> to
                        <geogName key="wcree">Wood Creek</geogName>.- The price of<lb/> Land on
                        <del>from</del> the <geogName key="mohaw">Mohock</geogName> from the
                        <placeName key="gefla">German Flatts</placeName><lb/> to <placeName
                        key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName> we were told was from 2<lb/> Dollars to
                    20 pr Acre, according to the quality<lb/> and State of cultivation.- The course from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="schen">Schenectady</placeName> to <placeName key="fstan">Fort
                        Stanwix</placeName>, I suppose to be<lb/> about W.N.W., distance by water
                    about 120<lb/> miles.- this day got our batteaux &amp;ca.<lb/> over to <geogName
                        key="wcree">Wood Creek</geogName>-- <geogName key="wcree">Wood
                        Creek</geogName> at this place<lb/> being no more than a shallow Brook
                    of<lb/> about 10 or 12 feet wide. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-17">17th</date>. <geogName key="wcree"/></dateline>
                <p> About 7 this morning, having previously<lb/> hoisted the Gates of a Mill Dam a
                    little above the<lb/> batteaux floated down the Creek,- One Waggon<lb/> Load of
                    Goods, and another with passengers, going<lb/> by Land down to <geogName
                        key="ccree">Canada Creek</geogName> -- 4 miles below<lb/>
                    <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName> is the remains of <placeName
                        key="fbull">Fort Bull</placeName>, opposite<lb/> to which on the South side
                    of <geogName key="wcree">Wood Creek</geogName> is the N.E. corner of the
                        <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName> reserve<lb/> seven<lb/>
                    <pb n="6" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_08"/> seven miles below <placeName key="fstan"
                        >Fort Stanwix</placeName> is <geogName key="ccree">Canada
                    Creek</geogName><lb/> opposite to the mouth of which, on the South side<lb/> of
                        <geogName key="wcree">Wood Creek</geogName> is the remains of <placeName
                        key="frick">Fort Ricky</placeName> -- the Land between<lb/>
                    <placeName key="frick"><placeName key="fstan">Fort
                        Stanwix</placeName></placeName> and <geogName key="ccree">Canada
                        Creek</geogName> is low &amp; marshy,<lb/> much inferior to that on the
                        <geogName key="mohaw">Mohock</geogName> -- The<lb/> Timber consists of large
                    *Maple, Birch, Beach,<lb/> Pine &amp;ca., no Oak or Chestnut as yet<lb/> to be
                    seen.– at 6 in the evening encamped<lb/> at a place call'd the Oak Orchard, 18
                    miles by<lb/> water from <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName>.- here
                    is a high spot<lb/> on which are a few Oak Trees – the Land below<lb/>
                    <geogName key="ccree">Canada Creek</geogName> appears much better than that
                    above<lb/> -- the Timber, Maple, Butternut, Poplar, Beach,<lb/> Ash, Elm, Lindon
                    (or Bass Wood), and some Oak<lb/> -- very little Pine or Hemlock.- On the
                    Banks<lb/> of the River are considerable quantities of wild<lb/> Hops, equal to
                    any in the Brewing business.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-18">18th</date>. <placeName key="fbrewl"/></dateline>
                <p> About 6 A.M. embark'd and proceeded down<lb/> the Creek to the <geogName
                        key="oneil">Oneida Lake</geogName>, being about 18 miles<lb/> -- the Land on
                    the sides of the Creek being much<lb/> the same as that below <geogName
                        key="ccree">Canada Creek</geogName>.- The Course<lb/> from <placeName
                        key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName> to the Mouth of <geogName key="wcree"
                        >Wood Creek</geogName> on the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="oneil">Oneida Lake</geogName>, I suppose to be about W.b.S.,
                    the<lb/> distance by water 36 miles, and by Land about<lb/> 18 miles. - About 2
                    P.M. the Wind blowing fresh<lb/> to the Westward, we pitched our Tents on the
                    Bank<lb/> near the Mouth of <geogName key="wcree">Wood Creek</geogName> -- Here
                    we were</p>
                <p> *N.B. Whenever I speak of Maple sugar Maple is meant.</p>
                <pb n="7" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_08"/>
                <p> visited by <persName key="clewi1">Col Lewis</persName>, Beach Tree, and
                    Captain<lb/> John, three chiefs of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida
                        Indians</orgName> -- a<lb/> very sensible speech was delivered by Beach
                    Tree,<lb/> a grave old man, in which he congratulated<lb/>
                    <persName key="glinc1">Gen'l Lincoln</persName> on his arrival, and express'd
                    his<lb/> hearty concurrence with the Commissioners in<lb/> the object of their
                    mission, saying he was an<lb/> old Man and very near the Grave, and as the<lb/>
                    Work of peace was a good work, the few remain-<lb/>ing Days he had to Live
                    should all be spent<lb/> in the promotion of it.- <persName key="cjohn1">Captain
                        John</persName><lb/> made a short speech to the same effect, and<lb/> also
                    express'd his particular satisfaction in<lb/> seeing a number of Friends on
                    their way to<lb/> the Treaty.- <geogName key="wcree">Wood Creek</geogName> runs
                    into the <geogName key="oneil">Oneida<lb/> Lake</geogName> near the East end,
                    the Land upon the N.<lb/> side appears low and level, the Timber Pitch<lb/> Pine
                    intermixed with Oak and other wood, the<lb/> soil whereon we encamp'd sandy and
                    poor.<lb/>-On the south side the Country wore a more<lb/> pleasant &amp; fertile
                    appearance with a range<lb/> of high hills at a considerable distance to
                    the<lb/> South East, from which to the Lake, the<lb/> Land appeared well
                    Timbered and level--<lb/> It falling calm in the evening we struck<lb/> our
                    Tents and embark'd about 7 and proceeded down<lb/>
                    <pb n="8" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_09"/> down the <geogName key="oneil"
                        >Lake</geogName>,- a fair Wind springing<lb/> up about Midnight, we arrived
                    about 4<lb/> A.M. at the entrance of the Onandago or Oswego<lb/> River, near the
                    remains of <placeName key="fbrewl">Fort Brewerton</placeName><lb/>--our Passage
                    being all the way in the Night<lb/> can give no further description of the
                    Lake<lb/>–-the Course from the mouth of <geogName key="wcree">Wood
                        Creek</geogName><lb/> being about WbN., the distance 30 miles –<lb/> the
                    width of the Lake being from 7 to 9<lb/> miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><placeName key=""/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <date when="1793-05-19">19th</date>. Left <placeName key="fbrewl">Fort
                        Brewerton</placeName> about 7 o’clock in the<lb/> morning and proceeded with
                    the current 18<lb/> miles to where the <geogName key="senec">Seneca</geogName>
                    unites with the <geogName key="onori">Onan-<lb/>dago River</geogName>, at a
                    place call’d the three points, here<lb/> we found a settlement, stopt and got
                    our Dinners<lb/> –- the Land on both sides very low, some<lb/> appearing good,
                    other but indifferent –- the<lb/> Timber Oak, shag bark Hickory, Maple,
                    Ash,<lb/> Beach, Birch, Pine &amp;ca.- about 4 P.M. proceeded<lb/> down to the
                        <geogName key="oswef">Falls of Oswego</geogName>, and encamp’d on the<lb/>
                    North side near the Falls.- We have found plenty<lb/> of Fish ever since we
                    enter'd the <geogName key="onori">Onondago River</geogName> --<lb/> saw Cat Fish
                    at <placeName key="fbrewl">Fort Brewerton</placeName> that would weigh 15
                    to<lb/> 20 lb.- and a very good Fish they call Black Bass.<lb/> --at the Falls
                    we purchased of some Indians<lb/> very excellent Salmon –- The River at the
                    Falls is<lb/> about 200 yards wide, and the Fall over the Rock<lb/>
                    <pb n="9" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_09"/> about 8 feet perpendicular – the Course of
                    the<lb/> River at the Falls about N.N.W. –- The Banks<lb/> of the River higher
                    near the Falls than at the<lb/> entrance of the River – on the South side
                    the<lb/> Land appears fertile, and the banks about 40<lb/> feet high, on the N.
                    side the bank not so high<lb/> nor the land so good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-20">20th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Drag’d our Batteaux, without unloading<lb/> them, about 60 yards on the Land,
                    and launched<lb/> them into the River just below the Falls, from whence<lb/> to
                    the distance of about One Mile, the River is very<lb/> Rapid and not without the
                    appearance of danger<lb/> – we found several other Rapids in our way<lb/> down
                    to <placeName key="oswft">Oswego Fort</placeName>, where we arrived about<lb/> 2
                    P.M. – the distance from <placeName key="fbrewl">Fort
                    Brewerton</placeName><lb/>I think about 36 miles by water. – <placeName
                        key="oswft">Oswego</placeName><lb/> is pleasantly situated on a high point
                    on the<lb/> East side of the River, having the Lake to the<lb/> North. – We were
                    kindly entertained by <persName key="cwick1">Capt.<lb/> Wickham</persName> the
                    British Commander, during the<lb/> few hours we staid, with whom we dined<lb/> –
                    having no tidings of any Vessell to carry<lb/> us to <placeName key="niaga"
                        >Niagara</placeName>. <persName key="glinc1">General Lincoln</persName>
                    determined<lb/> to proceed on in our Batteaux, accordingly<lb/> it being a fine
                    Calm afternoon, about 4<lb/> P.M. we went out upon <geogName key="lakeo">Lake
                        Ontario</geogName>, and<lb/> about 7 pitch’d our Tents upon the Beach<lb/>
                    <pb n="10" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_10"/> about 15 miles from <placeName key="oswft"
                        >Oswego</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-21">21st</date>. <placeName key="apple"/></dateline>
                <p> It being a fine calm morning about<lb/> 8 o’Clock embark'd, and in the evening
                    en-<lb/>camped at a place call'd the <placeName key="apple">Apple
                        Boom</placeName>, a<lb/> good harbour for Boats, about 40 miles from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="oswft">Oswego</placeName>.- about 30 miles from <placeName
                        key="oswft">Oswego</placeName> on<lb/> the south side of the Lake, is
                        <geogName key="sodus">Great Sodus River</geogName><lb/> a good harbour for
                    Vessells.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-22">22nd</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Rain last night - in the morning a fresh<lb/> Breeze about West which prevented
                    our moving<lb/> untill about 4 P.M. when we again Launch'd<lb/> our Boats and
                    proceeded about 7 miles, then<lb/> landed and encamped on the Shore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-23">23rd</date>. <placeName key="oakor"/></dateline>
                <p> About 5 A.M. embark'd and went 6 miles,<lb/> then landed and got breakfast, in
                    the mean<lb/> time a fair Wind sprung up which we,<lb/> hoisting our Sails, made
                    use of - about<lb/> 10 A.M. opposite the Mouth of <geogName key="genes2">Genesee
                        River</geogName><lb/> (here we saw a House, being the only settlement we
                    discovered on the Lake) which is call’d 65 miles from Oswego – 10<lb/> miles to
                    the Westward of <geogName key="genes2">Genesee</geogName> is Braddock’s<lb/>
                    Bay, where we stopt to dine – this appear’d<lb/> to be the most pleasant spot we
                    have as yet found upon<lb/> the Lake – on both sides the Creek fine Meadows<lb/>
                    and the upland has the appearance of fertility<lb/> – The Timber chiefly Oak,
                    with some Chesnut<lb/> Hickory and Maple.- The Bank of the Lake<lb/> from Oswego
                    to Braddocks Bay is mostly low,<lb/> and level, not to exceed 40 feet in the
                    highest places,<lb/>
                    <pb n="11" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_10"/> --the Timber chiefly Hemlock, Maple,
                    Birch,<lb/> Beach &amp;ca.- After dinner again proceeded<lb/> on our Way, and
                    about 8 P.M. encamp'd at<lb/> a place called the <placeName key="oakor">Oak
                        Orchard</placeName>, being about<lb/> 50 miles from where we lay last night
                    &amp;<lb/> 40 from <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-24">24th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About 8 A.M. embark'd with a fair Wind<lb/> which encreas'd and blew hard about
                    Noon,<lb/> we were obliged to Land at a place call'd 18 mile<lb/>Creek.- The
                    Land from Braddocks Bay to this<lb/> place very low and swampy. - here we<lb/>
                    found a fine pleasant Bank 20 or 30 feet high, the<lb/> soil tolerable good,
                    covered chiefly with Oak<lb/> Timber - while at this place we saw two Schooners
                    pass by<lb/> which we supposed were from <placeName key="kings"
                        >Kingston</placeName>, on<lb/> the St.Lawrence, bound to <placeName
                        key="niaga">Niagara</placeName> - The<lb/> wind continuing to blow hard we
                    pitch'd<lb/> our Tents.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-25">25th</date>. <placeName key="newar"/></dateline>
                <p> About 1 A.M. it being Calm, we<lb/> again moved forward and about 6 arriv'd<lb/>
                    at the Fort of <placeName key="fniag">Niagara</placeName> - the shore, the<lb/>
                    last 18 miles, being very pleasant, a level<lb/> flat Bank about 20 feet high -
                    the Timber<lb/> which we take to be Oak appearing very<lb/> tall and fine. - The
                    distance from Oswego to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="fniag">Niagara</placeName> as we coasted it, along the south side<lb/>
                    <pb n="12" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_11"/> side of <geogName key="lakeo">Lake
                        Ontario</geogName>, being reckoned 160 miles<lb/> - <placeName key="niaga"
                        >Niagara</placeName> Fort is very pleasantly situated on<lb/> a high point
                    of Land, having <geogName key="lakeo">Lake Ontario</geogName> on<lb/> the North,
                    and the Gut, or <geogName key="niagr">Niagara River</geogName> on the<lb/>
                    west.- After having refresh'd ourselves at a<lb/> Tavern in the Garrison, where
                    the entertainment<lb/> was but indifferent, and the Charge very high,<lb/> we
                    cross'd over the River to the New Town of<lb/>
                    <placeName key="newar">Newark</placeName>, <persName key="cpick1">Col.
                        Pickering</persName> having previously<lb/> engaged a House, wherein we
                    could spread<lb/> our Mattrasses, and Cook our Victuals. - when<lb/> we landed
                    at <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName> we found a Vessell with<lb/> her
                    Sails loose, and just on the point of sailing<lb/> for Oswego, in order to bring
                    us to <placeName key="fniag">Niagara</placeName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-26">26th</date>.<placeName key="newar"/></dateline>
                <p> - First day - Remained all day at <placeName key="newar"
                        >New-<lb/>ark</placeName>, which is situated nearly opposite to the<lb/>
                    Fort, the River, or Gut, between them being about<lb/> three quarters of a Mile
                    wide, the Town con-<lb/>tains about 20 houses, and others building<lb/> – the
                    Land in the vicinity but indifferent,<lb/> much inferiour to that near the Fort
                    – at<lb/> this place we met with <persName key="grand1">Governor
                        Randolph</persName><lb/> and <persName key="cpick1">Col.
                        Pickering</persName>, the other two Commissioners<lb/> who, with <persName
                        key="glinc1">General Lincoln</persName>, the Secretary &amp; <persName
                        key="rhill1">Rich’d<lb/> Hillery</persName> are entertain’d by <persName
                        key="gsimc1">Governor Simcoe</persName>.–<lb/> At our arrival here we were
                    inform’d the Indians<lb/>
                    <pb n="13" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_11"/> Indians would not be ready to attend
                    the<lb/> treaty before the last of next month.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-27">27th.</date>
                    <placeName key="kisto"/></dateline>
                <p>In the morning before breakfast had a Visit<lb/> from <persName key="gsimc1"
                        >Governor Simcoe</persName>, who had some Conversation<lb/> with Friends
                    respecting the Militia Laws, and<lb/> appeared very desirous that they might be
                    so mo-<lb/>delled in this Government as to be as little oppressive<lb/> as
                    possible - about 8 A.M. embark'd in our Boats<lb/> and at 11 Landed at the
                        <placeName key="kisto">Kings Stores</placeName> 9 miles from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="fniag">Niagara</placeName> - the Banks on both sides, all the
                    way<lb/> up, being high and steep, and the shores very<lb/> bold, so that there
                    are but few places <del>where</del>that are<lb/> convenient for Landing - to
                    this place the River<lb/> is navigable for large Vessells - here in the<lb/>
                    afternoon we had the satisfaction to meet<lb/> with our Friends <persName
                        key="jparr1">John Parish</persName>, <persName key="jmoor3">Joseph
                        Moore</persName><lb/> and <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName>,
                    who came from Philadelphia<lb/> in Company with <persName key="grand1">Govern’r
                        Rand olph</persName> &amp; <persName key="cpick1"><persName key="cpick1"
                            >Col. Pickering</persName></persName><lb/> - Our Baggage, Stores,
                    &amp;ca. were deposited in<lb/> the Kings Stores, and we pitch'd our Tents<lb/>
                    upon the Hill above the Landing, a number<lb/> of soldiers lay in Huts on the
                    low grounds<lb/> below, who are very sickly, numbers dying<lb/> daily with the
                    Dysentery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-28">28th</date>. <placeName key="kisto"/></dateline>
                <p> Our small Batteaux were all dis-<lb/>charged and sent back to <placeName
                        key="schen">Schenectady</placeName> - about<lb/>
                    <pb n="14" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_12"/> about 11 this morning we were visited by<lb/>
                    <persName key="gsimc1">Govr Simcoe</persName>, <persName key="grand1">Govr
                        Randolph</persName>, <persName key="cpick1">Col Pickering</persName><lb/>
                        &amp;ca.-<persName key="gsimc1">Governor Simcoe</persName> kindly offered us
                    the use<lb/> of his House, which stands empty among the<lb/> Soldiers Huts at
                    the foot of the Hill, but it being<lb/> an unhealthy situation, we acknowledged
                    his<lb/> kindness, and abode in our Tents - The poor<lb/> sickly Soldiers were
                    also removed from this<lb/> unhealthy spot, and encamp'd on the Top<lb/> of a
                    Hill, about half a Mile from us - this<lb/> afternoon <persName key="jmoor1"
                        >Jos. Moore</persName> &amp; <persName key="jlind1">J. Lindley</persName>
                    left us in order<lb/> to visit some People in the Neighbourhood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-29">29th</date>. <placeName key="kisto"/></dateline>
                <p> Steady Rain the greatest part of the Day -<lb/> some of our Company went down to
                    Navy Hall to<lb/> visit the Commissioners, where it was concluded<lb/> that
                    Friends, together with <persName key="jheck1">J.Hackenwelder</persName> and<lb/>
                    <persName key="wmcco1">Dr. McCoskry</persName> might be at Liberty to proceed to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>, and there remain until the time<lb/>
                    of the Treaty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-30">30th</date>. <placeName key="kisto"/></dateline>
                <p> The Rain still continued all the last Night<lb/> and the greatest part of this
                    Day - <persName key="wmcco1">Dr. McCoskry</persName> went<lb/> down to Navy Hall
                    and procured our passports to<lb/>
                    <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName> - in the evening we were joined by
                        <persName key="jlind1">Jacb.<lb/> Lindley</persName>, and had a visit from
                        <persName key="wbran1">William Brandt</persName><lb/> a <orgName
                        key="tuscarora"> Tuscarora</orgName> Chief, who appear'd to be a
                    sensible<lb/> and well behaved Man - he resides at a Village<lb/> about 3 miles
                    from this place on the East Side<lb/> of the River - <persName key="jparr1">J.
                        Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jelli1">J. Elliott</persName> and
                        <persName key="wsave1">W.Savery</persName><lb/>
                    <pb n="15" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_12"/> removed their Mattrasses into a House
                    on<lb/> account of the Rain, the rest of us kept in our<lb/> Tents in which we
                    lay dry and comfortable.<lb/> Some remarkable expressions which dropt<lb/> from
                        <persName key="gsimc1">Governor Simcoe</persName>, in the Visit, mentioned
                    in<lb/> the Morning of the <date when="1793-05-27">27th</date>, being omited in
                    the proper<lb/> place, are in substance as follows - He said that<lb/>
                    falsehoods had been intimated by American Com-<lb/>missioners at former treaties
                    with the Indians, in<lb/> respect to the British Government ceeding to the<lb/>
                    United States the absolute property of the Indian<lb/> Country, as the price of
                    Peace, - nothing more<lb/> being intended by that Article of the Treaty,
                    than<lb/> the right of preemption, which he fully acknow<lb/>-ledged, and said
                    that the British Government had no<lb/> right to purchase Lands of the Indians
                    within<lb/> the limits mark'd out by the Treaty - He fur-<lb/>ther said that the
                    Indians had been treated<lb/> with cruelty and injustice, and that it was<lb/>
                    his opinion they never would make peace<lb/> except the <geogName key="ohior"
                        >River Ohio</geogName> was made the boundary<lb/> line. - He further said
                    that scandalous<lb/> falsehoods had been propagated in the News<lb/> papers of
                    the United States, respecting the<lb/> British still keeping possession of the
                    West-<lb/>ern Ports, that the only reason was the<lb/>
                    <pb n="16" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_13"/> the noncompliance of the United States
                    with<lb/> two Articles of the Treaty of Peace - let these<lb/> Articles be
                    complied with and the Forte shall<lb/> be immediately <del>complied with</del>
                    evacuated,<lb/> and, he added, with some degree of warmth<lb/> - <said
                        who="gsimc1">I know the disposition of your people, - what<lb/> signifies
                        that Pidgeon House</said> - pointing to the<lb/> Fort - <said who="gsimc1">I
                        know you can take it - it is not<lb/> in the strength the place that I put
                        my<lb/> dependance, but it is in this, that we have<lb/> Boston, <placeName
                            key="newyo">New York</placeName> and Philadelphia in<lb/> Mortgage for
                        your peaceable behaviour.</said>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-05-31">31st</date>. <placeName key="kisto"/></dateline>
                <p> Rain all these 24 hours almost without<lb/> intermission - <persName
                        key="jheck1">J. Heckenwelder</persName> and <persName key="wmcco1">Doctr.
                        MoCoskry</persName><lb/> set off for <placeName key="ferie">Fort
                        Erie</placeName> in order to enquire after a<lb/> passage to Detroit. - This
                    day <persName key="jmoor1">J.Moore</persName> join'd us,<lb/> and we were
                    visited by <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendrick</persName> and<lb/> some of
                    the <orgName key="stockbridge"> Stockbridge Indians</orgName>, most of whom<lb/>
                    speak good English, and appear to be a civil well-<lb/>-behaved people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-01">6mo. 1st.</date>
                    <placeName key="niagf"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning the Rain abated - took<lb/> a walk up the River.- immediately from
                    the<lb/> Landing the Bank rises to the heigth of more than<lb/> 150 feet above
                    the surface of the Water, - the<lb/> range of high Land, extending each way
                    from<lb/> the River, about an East and West course - the Land<lb/> below towards
                        <geogName key="lakeo">Lake Ontario</geogName>, being a Level plain,<lb/>
                    <pb n="17" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_13"/> the greatest part well-timbered and
                    fertile, many<lb/> beautiful settlements on the West bank of the<lb/> River
                    towards <placeName key="newar">Newark</placeName>. - the Land after<lb/> rising
                    the Hill above, towards <geogName key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName>,<lb/> being
                    also a plain level Country, equal in<lb/> beauty and fertility to that below -
                    as far<lb/> as I could discover, the Banks of the River,<lb/> from the Landing
                    to the Falls, <del><gap/></del><lb/> of the heigth, perhaps from 150 to 200
                    feet,<lb/>are almost perpendicular, the greatest part<lb/>of solid Rock, it
                    being the opinion of many,<lb/> that the Falls were originally near the Landing,
                    but the<lb/> prodigious Body of Water that precipitates down<lb/> them, has worn
                    the channel, 6 or 7 miles up<lb/> to its present situation – from a high
                    point<lb/> on the West Bank, had a view of the River<lb/> down to the Lake, and
                    by a small pocket<lb/> Compass found that Fort <placeName key="niaga"
                        >Niagara</placeName> bore from<lb/> one N. by W. – In the afternoon
                        <persName key="wsave1">Wm. Savery</persName><lb/> and myself went on Horse
                    Back to see<lb/> the <geogName key="niagf">great Falls</geogName>, on the way
                    found the country thickly<lb/> inhabited, all new settlements.- The River<lb/>
                    just above the Falls I suppose to be a mile<lb/> wide, and the depth in some
                    places 6 or 8 feet,<lb/> this prodigious body of water, conjectured to be<lb/>
                    more than double the quantity that comes down<lb/> the Falls of Delaware near
                    Trenton, with<lb/>
                    <pb n="18" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_14"/> amazing rapiddity shoots over the edge of
                    a<lb/> solid perpendicular Rock, and Falls (according to<lb/>
                    <persName key="aelli1">A. Elliotts</persName> account) 137 feet
                        -<del><gap/></del><lb/><del><gap/></del><lb/> - for about a mile above the
                    great Fall, there is<lb/> a continued succession of Cataracts, some of<lb/> them
                    3 or 4 feet perpendicular, this greatly en-<lb/>creases the rapiddity of the
                    current, until it comes<lb/> to the edge of the Precipice, over which it dashes
                        -<del><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/></del></p>
                <p> The River at the Falls is divided by a small<lb/> flat Island, of perhaps 250
                    yards in width, and twice<lb/> that number in length - the sides and upper
                    end,<lb/> not much elevated above the surface of the River<lb/> above the Falls,
                    the lower end, which is on a line<lb/> with the Falls, is a smooth perpendicular
                    Rook, I suppose<lb/> of about 150 feet high.- The edge of the Rock over<lb/>
                    which the water Falls, on the East side of the Island,<lb/><del><gap/></del>, is
                    nearly a straight line,<lb/> and the River, on that side, I suppose to be 250
                    yards<lb/> wide, but the Water not so deep as on the West side<lb/>
                    <pb n="19" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_14"/> where its width is the
                        same<del><gap/></del> - the<lb/> edge of the Rook, on this side, forms near
                        about<del><gap/></del><lb/> half a Circle, the convex side
                        upwards<del><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/></del><lb/> --The quantity of Water
                    that passes on the West side,<lb/> I suppose to be double that which passes on
                    the<lb/> East side of the Island, being in the middle 6 or 8<lb/> feet deep
                    above the Falls.- It is said that by<lb/> actual survey there is found to be 50
                    feet fall in the<lb/> one mile of Rapids just above the Falls, and<lb/> from
                    thence down to the Landing, 6 or 7 miles,<lb/> the rappidity of the River
                    renders it altogether<lb/> impassable, in that distance the fall must be<lb/>
                    very considerable, so that taking the whole<lb/> into view, we may conclude,
                    that the surface<lb/> of the Water of <geogName key="lakee">Lake
                    Erie</geogName>, is nearly 300 feet above<lb/> that of <geogName key="lakeo"
                        >Lake Ontario</geogName>, the distance between these<lb/> Lakes being only
                    36 miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-02">2nd</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> This being the first day of the Week we<lb/> attended a Meeting appointed by
                    Friends, held in<lb/> a Barn, about 2 miles from the Falls, at which<lb/> were
                    gathered a considerable number of sober<lb/> well-behaved People, and ended much
                    to satisfac-<lb/>tion - in the evening return'd to our Encamp-<lb/>ment, and
                    were visited by <persName key="cornp2">Cornplanter</persName> the Seneca<lb/>
                    Chief.- This, and the preceeding day found plenty<lb/> of ripe Strawberries.</p>
                <pb n="20" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_15"/>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-03">3d</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Hearing of a Vessell laying at <placeName key="ferie">Fort
                    Erie</placeName>,<lb/> ready to Sail for <placeName key="detro"
                        >Detroit</placeName> we this morning got one of our<lb/> Batteaux carried by
                    Land to the mouth of<lb/>
                    <geogName key="chipp">Chippeway Creek</geogName> two miles above the Falls,<lb/>
                    the distance 9 miles. [Cartage of Goods 2/N. York<lb/> Carr'd. J Au.]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-04">4th</date>. <placeName key="ferie"/></dateline>
                <p> Embark'd in our Batteaux and pushed up<lb/> against a rapid Stream 18 miles to
                        <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>,<lb/> where we embark'd on
                    board a Kings Vessell,<lb/> a schooner of about 100 Tons burthen, called<lb/>
                    the Dunmore, commanded by <persName key="cford1">Captain Ford</persName>,<lb/>
                    whose conduct towards us was civil and obliging.<lb/>- The Country from
                        <geogName key="chipp">Chippeway Creek</geogName>, on the<lb/> West side, up
                    to <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, is very thickly inhabited<lb/>
                    chiefly by new settlers from the united States.-<lb/> We had on board the
                    Dunmore 12 passengers<lb/> in the Cabbin, several in the Steerage and<lb/>
                    upwards of 60 Indians, of different Tribes, on Deck,<lb/> which with the
                    Sailors, Marines etc., made the<lb/> whole number on board, amount to upwards
                    of<lb/> 90 Souls - the River from <geogName key="chipp">Chippeway</geogName> to
                        <placeName key="ferie">Fort<lb/> Erie</placeName> is from l ¼ to 2 miles
                    wide, in which<lb/> are several fine Islands - the Course nearly<lb/> North and
                    South.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-05">5th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About 2 P.M.a fair wind springing<lb/> up made Sail and got out into the
                    Lake</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-08"/><placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <pb n="21" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_15"/>
                <p>
                    <date when="1793-06-06">6th</date>, <date when="1793-06-07">7th</date> and <date
                        when="1793-06-08">8th</date>. Variable Winds, <del>and</del> mostly<lb/>
                    >from the Southward with some Rain.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-09">9th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> At Noon passed the <geogName key="bassi">Bass Islands</geogName> through<lb/>
                    the Northermost Channell, in which we found<lb/> from 3 to 7 fathoms of Water.-
                    The <geogName key="bassi">Bass Islands</geogName><lb/> extend quite across the
                    Lake about 40 miles<lb/> below the mouth of <geogName key="detroir">Detroit
                        River</geogName> and make<lb/> a very beautiful appearance, some of<lb/>
                    them are 6 or 7 miles in length, and<lb/> we were informed are well cover'd
                    with<lb/> Timber and of an excellent soil - the<lb/> smaller ones produce
                    excellent Red<lb/> Cedar Ship Timber - this being first Day<lb/> had a Meeting
                    in the Cabbin, with the Passengers<lb/> and some of the Chiefs among the
                    Indians, -<lb/> which appear'd to give general satisfaction<lb/> - about 11 P.M.
                    came to an Anchor in <geogName key="detroir">De-<lb/>-troit River</geogName> -
                    distance from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="detro">Detroit</placeName> 285 m---</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-10">10th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> On coming upon Deck this morning we<lb/> were agree­ably surprised to find
                    ourselves sailing<lb/> up a fine River, with Plantations of new settlers<lb/> on
                    both sides - the father we advanced up, the<lb/> beauty of the prospect
                    increased, and when we<lb/> came within 6 or 7 miles of the Town, a sight<lb/>
                    of the kind more pleasing, I think I never saw.</p>
                <pb n="22" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_16"/>
                <p> The Country here was first settled<lb/> by the French, it is said above one
                    hundred years ago,<lb/> whose decendants, in a general way, are still the<lb/>
                    Proprietors, and by whom that Language (with<lb/> but few exceptions) is only
                    spoken. - The front<lb/> of each Lot on the River being but narrow, is<lb/>
                    almost wholly taken up with Buildings, Gardens<lb/> and fine thrifty orchards,
                    so that it has almost<lb/> the appearance oft one continu­ ous Village quite
                    up<lb/> to the Town - we sometimes could count four<lb/> or five Windmills in
                    sight at once, and a<lb/> pretty large Romish Chapple stands on the East<lb/>
                    side of the River, about 4 miles above the town.<lb/>- about 9 A.M. came to an
                    Anchor before<lb/> the Town of <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>, - the
                    distance from the<lb/> mouth of the River 18 miles - course N b E<lb/> - Detroit
                    stands on the west side of the River, is<lb/> a compact dirty little Town,
                    containing about 100<lb/> small Houses, entirely surrounded by a picquet<lb/>
                    Wall, having several Gates which are always shut at 9 oClo.<lb/> - The Merchants
                    of this place carry on a great<lb/> Trade with the Indians, 8 or 10 Vessells
                    being em-<lb/>ployed by them on the Lakes, who sail from <placeName key="ferie"
                        >Fort<lb/> Erie</placeName> in a Circuitous rout, sometimes to the
                    dis-<lb/>tance of above 1000 miles to the Westward.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-06-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Upon our arrival at <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>, after<lb/> some
                    enquiry, took up our quarters at the<lb/>
                    <pb n="23" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_16"/> house of <persName key="mdols1">Matthew
                        Dolsen</persName>, who keeps a good<lb/> table and an orderly House, - we
                    lay upon our<lb/> own Mattresses, and pay 4/ per day each, for<lb/> our diet,
                    exclusive of Liquor - Imported Goods<lb/> are double the price they are in
                    the<lb/> United States, and Country produce nearly<lb/> as high - a good calf is
                    sold for £4.10 N.Y. Curr.,<lb/> a Cow for £15.-, - Wheat 12/ per Bushel, -<lb/>
                    Salt 60/ per bushel. Soon after our arrival<lb/> went out to visit Captain John
                    a Chief<lb/> of the <geogName key="mohaw">Mohawk</geogName>s, and other Indians,
                    who were<lb/> our fellow passengers on board the Dunmore,<lb/> we found them
                    sober, and had some friendly<lb/> conversation with them, endeavoring to<lb/>
                    inform them of our motives of leaving<lb/> home, with which they seemed well
                    pleas'd,<lb/> and assured us of their hearty friendship<lb/> - but the next day
                    exhibited a very different<lb/> scene - the War dance­ Captain John<lb/> and
                    most of his party were drunk - they<lb/> were almost naked and frightfully
                    painted<lb/> which with their Yells, musick and Tomahocks<lb/> afforded an
                    entertainment, by no means<lb/> pleasing - before they came to the door of<lb/>
                    our Lodging, Captain John, who did<lb/>
                    <pb n="24" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_17"/> not join in the Dance, came forward, to
                    assure<lb/> us, that no injury was intended - We were obliged<lb/> to give them
                    a little Cyder and Tobacco. - It is a<lb/> regulation in this Garrison that no
                    Indian is<lb/> allowed to remain within the Picquet all night,<lb/>- on the 13th
                    Captain John, and his party, set<lb/> off to attend the great Council of
                    Indian<lb/> Tribes, to be held, previous to the Treaty, at the<lb/> Rapids of
                    the <geogName key="miamr">Miami River</geogName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning breakfasted with <persName key="melli1">Matthew
                    Elliott</persName>,<lb/> Deputy superintendant of Indian Affairs, and on<lb/>
                    our return went to see a party of <orgName key="ojibwe"
                    >Chippeways</orgName>,<lb/> who had just came down from <placeName key="michi"
                        >Michillamackanac</placeName>,<lb/> and were on their way to the great
                    Council<lb/> --we found them drunk--at first they shook<lb/> hands with us, but
                    soon grew furious, calling<lb/> us in their way, long knife, and on our
                    going<lb/> away, two of them came after us, and with furi-<lb/>ous countenances,
                    and violent gestures, insisted<lb/> upon our returning, which we declined
                    doing,<lb/> and walk'd away - we were afterwards<lb/> informed, by a person who
                    accidentally happened<lb/> to be present, and understood their Language,<lb/>
                    that they said they wanted us to go back that<lb/> they might take our scalps -
                    One of the two<lb/> that followed us had his face painted black,<lb/>
                    <pb n="25" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_17"/> his head decorated with black feathers,
                    and<lb/> a Scalp hanging at one Ear.-- this day we<lb/> were invited to Dine
                    with the officers of the<lb/> 24th Regiment, who treated us with great<lb/>
                    politeness, and hospitality, there was near<lb/> 15 officers at Dinner besides
                    their guest.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="haupa1">Captain Hendrick</persName>, and his party, went off
                    towards<lb/> the <geogName key="miamr">Miami</geogName> - <persName key="haupa1"
                        >Captain Hendrick</persName> appears to be the most<lb/> thoughtful and
                    civilized Indian we have met<lb/> with, and almost the only one that we
                    have<lb/> not seen drunk since we came to this place<lb/> - we this day had a
                    visit from some of the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="wyandot">Wiandots</orgName>, who reside not far from hence, they
                    appear<lb/> to have some knowledge of our society, and were<lb/>very
                    friendly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-16">16th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning Captain Ford sailed for <placeName key="ferie">Fort
                        Erie</placeName><lb/> - by him I wrote to New York - at 10 A.M.our
                    friends<lb/> had a large satisfactory Meeting at <placeName key="detro"
                        >Detroit</placeName>, at<lb/> which many Officers and Soldiers
                    attended-<lb/> in the afternoon at 4 oClock had another Meeting<lb/> about 6
                    miles down on the east side of the<lb/> River, at which were gathered a
                    considerable<lb/> number of well­behaved People - This day<lb/> the <orgName
                        key="ojibwe">Chippeways</orgName> went on to the Council, at<lb/> their
                    departure, they sang the War Song,<lb/> with great shouting etc. - in the
                    evening<lb/> arrived the Snow <orgName key="ojibwe">Chippeway</orgName> from
                        <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, in<lb/>
                    <pb n="26" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_18"/> this Vessell a number of the Six Nation
                    Indians<lb/> came Passengers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-17">17th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Accounts are circulating here, and generally<lb/> believed, that <persName
                        key="gwayn1">General Wayne</persName> has advanced his<lb/> Army, a
                    considerable distance from <placeName key="fwash1">Fort
                        Washing<lb/>-ton</placeName>, toward the Indian Country - this, it is
                    said,<lb/> adds greatly to the jealousy and rage of the Indians<lb/> - several
                    Tribes, on the strength of these reports,<lb/> we are inform'd, are return'd
                    back to their<lb/> Towns - the circulation of these reports, which<lb/> is
                    generally done by deserters from the American<lb/> Army, will, in all
                    probability, protract the time<lb/> of holding <del>of <gap/> which</del> the
                    Treaty <del>made <gap/></del>, if not<lb/> totally defeat this desirable event -
                    some in<lb/> this place have thrown out hints as if the<lb/> Commissioners
                    already <del>were</del> began to be apprehensive of<lb/> personal danger, and
                    meant not to advance any<lb/> further. - <persName key="jparr1">John
                        Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jmoor3">Joseph Moore</persName>, and
                        <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName><lb/> having some days ago
                    dined with <persName key="cengl1">Col. England</persName>,<lb/> the Commandant,
                        <persName key="jlind1">Jacob Lindley</persName>, <persName key="wsave1"
                        >W.Savery</persName> and<lb/> myself, were this day, with much
                    politeness,<lb/> kindly entertained by the same Gentleman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-18">18th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Much pestered with visits from the Indians<lb/> whose chief motives for these
                    civilites, is to get<lb/> a little Rum, but in this they are disappointed,<lb/>
                    we having come to a resolution to give them<lb/> none, but put them off with a
                    little Tobacco etc.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">

                <pb n="27" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_18"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-19">19th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Cross'd the River with <persName key="jparr1">J. Parrish</persName>, <persName
                        key="jlind1">J. Lindley</persName>,<lb/>
                    <persName key="jmoor3">J. Moore</persName> and <persName key="jelli1">J.
                        Elliott</persName>, (<persName key="wsave1">W.Savery</persName> being
                    unwell)<lb/> and went down about 6 miles on the East<lb/> side - the good Land
                    on the banks of the River<lb/> on both sides does not extend above a mile<lb/>
                    back, beyond that it is low and marshy,<lb/> little or none of it cultivated. -
                    saw some <del>beau</del><lb/> beautiful pieces of wheat, fine orchards,
                    full<lb/> of fruit, Cherries ripe, and Cucumber vines<lb/> just beginning to
                    run.- The Land being rather<lb/> low, their Indian corn is very short, about 8
                    or 9<lb/> inches high in general. - We dined at <persName key="farno1"
                        >Fredk.<lb/> Arnolds</persName>, one of the society of the Dunkards,
                        <del>who</del><lb/> a native of Germany, who formerly lived in<lb/>
                    Pensylvania, he inform'd me he purchased the<lb/> place he now lives on, an old
                    French settlement<lb/> containing about 100 acres, with a tolerable good<lb/>
                    House, Barn and Orchard, for 300 N.Y. Currency.<lb/> ­ He also let me see his
                    Certificates, from<lb/> Government, for Lands granted to him and his<lb/>
                    Children, by which I find they (the Certificates) are not, in<lb/> any shape,
                    transferable, either by sale, <del>assign</del><lb/> assignment, or Donation,
                    and that the Titles<lb/> are to be given upon such <emph rend="underline"
                        >Conditions</emph> as may<lb/> be the Kings pleasure. - At 5 P.M. had a<lb/>
                    solid satisfactory Meeting with a few of the<lb/> Inhabitants, at the House of
                        <persName key="jmess1">John Mesemer</persName>,<lb/>
                    <pb n="28" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_19"/> where we tarried all night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-20">20th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> We proposed returning to Detroit this<lb/> morning, but the wind coming a head,
                    and<lb/> blowing hard, prevented us - we went to<lb/>
                    <persName key="fcorn1">Francis Cornwalls</persName>, a Connecticut Man,
                    were<lb/> we dined, and <persName key="jmoor3">J.M.</persName> and myself, were
                    kindly<lb/> entertained at his house all night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-21">21st</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Wind still at N.E. with much Rain<lb/> and very cold for the season - the
                    transitions<lb/> from heat to cold, in this country, being very<lb/> frequent,
                    and I think to a much greater degree than<lb/> in New Jersey - about 5 in the
                    afternoon it began<lb/> to clear away, but the wind still against us, <persName
                        key="jlind1">Jacob<lb/> Lindley</persName> and <persName key="jelli1">John
                        Elliott</persName> left us and went on foot<lb/> up to Detroit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-22">22d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> A fine pleasant morning - after breakfast<lb/> we embark'd in our Canoe, and
                    with the assist-<lb/>ance of <persName key="farno1">Fred Arnold</persName>,
                    pushed up against the<lb/> current to <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>
                    - A young Canadian we met<lb/> with at <persName key="fcorn1">F.
                        Cornwall's</persName> inform'd us he had been<lb/> several voyage's in the
                    N.W. Trade, that they<lb/> generally left Montreal in the begining of the<lb/>
                    5th month, and that, without <del><gap/></del> any stop<lb/> but making the best
                    of their way, it took them so late<lb/> in the fall, that the Rivers were often
                    frose, before they<lb/> got to their Journeys end. - the Indians they met
                    with<lb/> there were mostly a harmless honest People. Their<lb/>
                    <pb n="29" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_19"/> Tents and dress being chiefly
                        <del>mostly</del> made of Buffaloe Skins<lb/> - he says the distance they
                    went with their<lb/> Canoe's taking the Course of the Lakes and Rivers<lb/> was
                    more than 2000 Leagues from Montreal. - this evening<lb/> we were all invited to
                    sup with the officers at<lb/> the mess Room.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-23">23d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <orgName key="ojibwe">Some Indians of the Chippeway Nation</orgName><lb/> came
                    in from the great Council at Miami<lb/> who bring accounts, as we are told, that
                    the<lb/> Indians are very backward in gathering, few<lb/> or none from the S.W.
                    having yet come in,<lb/> owing, it is said, to the injudicious movement<lb/> of
                        <persName key="gwayn1">General Wayne</persName>. - <persName key="melli1"
                        >Matthew Elliott</persName> gives it<lb/> as his opinion, that the treaty
                    will not com-<lb/>mence before the middle of next Month - at<lb/> 10 this
                    morning had a Meeting in the Kings<lb/> Sail Loft, in which some experienced
                    their<lb/> strength to be renew'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-06-24">24th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Various are the reports that we daily hear,<lb/> some of them exceedingly
                    discouraging, insomuch<lb/> that some of our Friends of this place, in the most
                    serious<lb/> manner, advise us not to think of attending<lb/> the Treaty.- This
                    day <persName key="jheck1">J. Hacken­ welder</persName>, with<lb/> a number of
                    his Brethren, the <orgName key="moraind">Moravian Indians</orgName>,<lb/> came
                    to the Garrison from their settlement on<lb/> the River La Trench, about 70
                    miles from hence,<lb/> by them we understand that the said Indians<lb/>
                    <pb n="30" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_20"/> Indians to the number of 140, were
                    much<lb/> distress'd for want of provisions, occasioned by<lb/> their being
                    frequently removed from place to<lb/> place, since their first forcible
                    removal<lb/> from <placeName key="muski1">Muskingum</placeName> - their
                    approaching Crops, they<lb/> say, are very promising, but their main<lb/>
                    dependance, in the meantime, is upon<lb/> such vegetables as the Fields and
                    Woods <del><gap/></del> afford,<lb/>
                    <del><gap/></del>, having but a very poor chance of<lb/> hunting in their new
                    settlement - Friends<lb/> have it in contemplation to afford them<lb/> a little
                    assistance - the price of Indian Corn<lb/> here, we are inform'd is 10/ per
                    bushel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-25">25th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning went down to the wharf<lb/> to see a Wolf that was kill'd last
                    Night upon<lb/> an Island about 3 miles from this place, it had<lb/> by some
                    means got there last Winter in the<lb/> time of the Frost, and had done a great
                    deal<lb/> of damage, insomuch that the proprietor had<lb/> offered a Reward of
                    twenty Dollars for killing<lb/> him. - he was much larger than a large<lb/> Dog,
                    of a grey or grisly colour. - his legs<lb/> were as long as those of a large
                    Deer, his Tail long<lb/> and tapering, thinly covered with long hair, and<lb/>
                    his head in shape between that of a Dog and Fox.</p>
                <pb n="31" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_20"/>
                <p> this evening <del>morning</del> arrived three large bark<lb/> Canoes, with
                    Twenty Eight <orgName key="ojibwe">Chippeways</orgName>, from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="michi">Michillamackanac</placeName>, on their way to Miami.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-26">26th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning sail'd the Snow <orgName key="ojibwe">Chippeway</orgName><lb/> for
                        <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, in whom went passenger
                        <persName key="rhill1">Richd.<lb/> Hillery</persName>, by whom I wrote to
                    New York.</p>
                <p> Friends agreed with <persName key="mdols1">M.Dolsen</persName> to supply<lb/>
                    the <orgName key="moraind">Moravian Indians</orgName> with Corn and Flour,<lb/>
                    to the value of one hundred Dollars, part of<lb/> which was this morning
                    delivered,<lb/> for which they appear'd to be very grateful.</p>
                <p> Dined with <persName key="jaski1">John Askin</persName> Esqr., a Merchant<lb/>
                    of this place, by whom we were very agreeably<lb/> entertained. - he, in some
                    measure, corrobe-<lb/>rated the account given by the Canadian on<lb/> the 22nd
                    respecting the North West Trade - he<lb/> says that from a place called the
                    Grand Portage,<lb/> at the upper end of the Lakes, they travel above<lb/> 2000
                    miles to the Westward, in small bark<lb/> Canoes so light that two Men carry
                    them <del><gap/></del> - all the pro-<lb/>vision, allowed to each Man for this
                    long<lb/> voyage, being no more than one bushel of<lb/> Indian Corn, that has
                    been boil'd in Lye and hull'd<lb/>
                    <pb n="32" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_21"/> and a little greese* (of what kind I know
                    not)<lb/> to mix with it.- this stock of corn is reserved<lb/> for extraordinary
                    occasions when they can<lb/> neither get Fish or kill anything with their
                    Guns.<lb/>- the Labouring People, in these long and tedious<lb/> journeys, are
                    all Canadians, who eat their<lb/> Fish and Flesh without either bread or
                        <del>and</del> Salt<lb/> - at Dinner we had fresh Fish brought in<lb/> a
                    Sloop, six days from <geogName key="lakes">Lake Superior</geogName>, they<lb/>
                    were the White Fish and Salmon trout, they<lb/> would weigh about 6 lb. each,
                    both exceeding good, but<lb/> the White Fish, I think, rather preferable -
                    in<lb/> the afternoon arrived the Sloop Felicity from<lb/>
                    <geogName key="grand">Grand River</geogName> on <geogName key="lakee">Lake
                        Erie</geogName>, in her came a<lb/> number of Indians <del>Passengers</del>
                    - in conversation<lb/> with <persName key="melli1">M.Elliott</persName>, he gave
                    it as his opinion, that<lb/> four weeks would yet elapse before the
                        <del>commi</del><lb/> Treaty began.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-06-27">27th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> had some conversation with <persName key="cdrak1">Capt Drake</persName>,<lb/> an
                    intelligent Man, who has for several years<lb/> navigated a Vessell on the
                    Lakes, by him was<lb/> inform'd that from Detroit to the entrance of Lake</p>
                <p>~~~~~~~~~~</p>
                <p>*Hogs Lard and Tallow mixt together</p>
                <pb n="33" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_21"/>
                <p>
                    <geogName key="lakst">Lake St.Clair</geogName> was about 6 miles, the
                    length<lb/> of said Lake 21 miles, from the N.W. end of<lb/>
                    <geogName key="lakst">Lake St. Clair</geogName> to the entrance of <geogName
                        key="lakeh">Lake Huron</geogName>,<lb/> through a very beautiful River, 15
                    Leagues, from<lb/> the lower end of <geogName key="lakeh">Lake Huron</geogName>
                    to the rapids<lb/> of St.Mary's (the entrance into <geogName key="lakes">Lake
                        Superior</geogName>),<lb/> 72 Leagues, at the rapids of St.Mary's there<lb/>
                    is a portage of a mile and a half, when goods<lb/> are again shipped in large
                    Vessells, who<lb/> carry them 100 Leagues up <geogName key="lakes">Lake
                        Superior</geogName> to what is called<lb/> the Grand Portage, from whence
                    they go<lb/> in small Canoes, to the North west.- He says<lb/> that there are
                    above One thousand Men<lb/> constantly employed in the N.W. Trade<lb/> above the
                    Grand Portage. - He further says<lb/> there are many mistakes in the drafts
                    heretofore<lb/> made of the Lakes, they not being done from<lb/> actual surveys,
                    but principally from<lb/> the vague reports of Canadian traders &amp;ca. -
                    that<lb/> the tales that have been told respecting <del>Thund</del><lb/> Thunder
                    Bay in <geogName key="lakeh">Lake Huron</geogName> is altogether a<lb/> farce,
                    that in the course of many years, which<lb/> he has <del>now</del> sail'd upon
                    that Lake, he never<lb/>
                    <pb n="34" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_22"/> was sensible of more thunder there, than
                    at<lb/> any other place on the Lake - that the<lb/> length of <geogName
                        key="lakes">Lake Superior</geogName> ie much less than<lb/> generally
                    represented, and that from two<lb/> opposite points, about the middle of
                    said<lb/> Lake, the width does not exceed 70 miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-28">28th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Very warm and sultry with Thunder<lb/> and rain. - about 10 at Night<lb/> five
                    or six Guns were fired just without the<lb/> Pickets, which, at first, as we lay
                    in Bed,<lb/> alarmed us not a little, but we were desired<lb/> to make ourselves
                    easy, as, in all probability,<lb/> it was nothing more than some people who<lb/>
                    had been watching for Wolves, or <emph rend="underline">shooting<lb/>at
                        Indians</emph> who were robbing Cherry Trees</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-29">29th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Visited by a Chief of the <orgName key="wyandot">Wiandot Indians</orgName><lb/>
                    who was sober and intelligent, he spoke<lb/> respectfully of our Society, and
                    said that<lb/> many Belts of Wampum, and other <del>mem</del><lb/> memorials of
                    ancient Friendship received<lb/> from them, were still carefully preserved<lb/>
                    by their Nation. - expressed the satisfaction he<lb/>
                    <pb n="35" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_22"/> felt in seeing so many of the people
                    call'd<lb/> Quakers, and said, as the Great Spirit had<lb/> been with them,
                    brought them so far -<lb/> through the Wilderness, and preserved them<lb/> all
                    in good health, so he hoped, he would still<lb/> continue to be their rotector
                    through every<lb/> danger, and carry them safe home.</p>
                <p> being in Company with <persName key="nwill1">Nathan<lb/> Williams</persName>, a
                    sensible Man who had<lb/> formerly been a Trader, and well
                    <del>acquain</del><lb/> acquainted with the Indians - he express'd<lb/> his
                    apprehensions on our account,<lb/> and openly gave it as his opinion, that<lb/>
                    if we attended the Treaty, we should either<lb/> be kill'd, or detained as
                    Prisoners.</p>
                <p> were informed that the Guns we heard <del><gap/></del><lb/> last Night, were
                    fired at Wolves, by People who<lb/> were watching <del>for them</del>, near the
                    Carcases<lb/> of several dead Sheep <del>which were</del> kill'd<lb/> by them
                    the Night before</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-06-30">30th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> First day - early this morning had a<lb/> Visit from the Blind Chief, a head Man among<lb/>
                    <pb n="36" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_24"/> among the <orgName key="wyandot"
                        >Wiandots</orgName>, with several of<lb/> his attendants, they were sober,
                    and what<lb/> is remarkable, neither these Men, nor<lb/> those that visited us
                    yesterday, made any<lb/> request for Rum. - at 10 A.M. had a<lb/> Meeting in the
                    Sail Loft, and another at<lb/> the same place at 5 in the Afternoon, at<lb/>
                    both of which were a pretty large number<lb/> of Soldiers, and Towns people, and
                    a few<lb/> of the officers of the Garrison, their conduct<lb/> generally was
                        <del>very</del> commendable, and<lb/> the Meetings, in the main, solid
                    and<lb/> satisfactory.- In the evening there<lb/> was a Marriage at our
                    Lodgings, - the<lb/> Young Man is a settler upon the River<lb/> La Trench, and a
                    Nephew to our Landlord<lb/>
                    <persName key="mdols1">M.Dolsen</persName>, the Young Woman is a Native<lb/> of
                    Virginia who was taken a Prisoner by<lb/> the Indians, from whom she made
                    her<lb/> escape. - the Ceremony was perform'd by<lb/>
                    <persName key="jarke1">J. Arken Esqt</persName>, and the whole decently
                        <del>condu</del><lb/> conducted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">

                <pb n="37" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_24"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-01">7 mo. 1st.</date>
                    <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> was an Eye witness of a Funeral in<lb/> the Popish Style
                        <del><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/><lb/><gap/></del>
                    -- This afternoon<lb/> arrived the <orgName key="ottawa">Snow Ottaway</orgName>
                    from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, by<lb/> this Vessell, we
                    learn, that the day before she<lb/> sail'd, an Express came to the
                    Commissioners<lb/> from Philadelphia, and another from <placeName key="fpitt1"
                        >Fort<lb/> Pitt</placeName>, - various are the reports here, some<lb/>
                    favourable, others exceedingly discouraging,<lb/> but having no accounts from
                    the Commissioner<lb/> we re anxiously waiting the next arrival<lb/> for further
                    intelligence. - The Ottaway<lb/> brought a great number of Indians from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, all of whom were <del>whom
                        were</del> Landed at the<lb/> Mouth of the <geogName key="miamr"
                        >Miami</geogName>, except 17 of the <orgName key="oneida">Oneida</orgName><lb/>
                    <pb n="38" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_25"/> Nation, whom <persName key="cbutl1">Colt
                        Butler</persName> would not<lb/> permit to be left <del>landed</del> there,
                    alleging they<lb/> were in danger of being killed by the other<lb/> Indians.- We
                    had a Letter from a person,<lb/> who happened accidentally to be in company<lb/>
                    with <persName key="cbutl1">Colonel Butler</persName>, he inform'd us
                        <del>that</del><lb/> he heard him say, that, if the demands of the<lb/>
                    Indians were not complyed with, it was<lb/> his opinion, <del>that</del> the
                    Commissioners, and the<lb/> whole of their Retinue, would be massacre'd<lb/> -
                    we also had a Letter from <persName key="cmcke1">Col.McKee</persName>, the<lb/>
                    British Agent, in answer to one wrote him.<lb/>- he dates his Letter from the
                    Foot of the Rapids<lb/> of the <geogName key="miamr">Miami River</geogName>, and
                    promises to give us<lb/> the earliest intelligence of the time when the<lb/>
                    Treaty will likely commence</p>

                <p> The following Account is taken from<lb/> a Quebec Almanac, for the Year <date
                        when="1792">1792</date></p>

                <p>The Names of all the different Indian<lb/> Nations in North America (hitherto
                    discover 'd )<lb/> the situation of their Countries, with the<lb/> Number of
                    their Fighting Men.</p>
                <pb n="39" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_25"/>
                <table cols="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="choctaw">Choctaw</orgName> or Flatheads,<lb/>The
                            Natches...<lb/>The Chickesaws...</cell>
                        <cell>on the Mobile<lb/> &amp; Mississipe</cell>
                        <cell>4,500<lb/>150<lb/>750</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell><orgName key="cherokee">The Cherokees</orgName>...</cell>
                        <cell>So. Carolina</cell>
                        <cell>2,500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="catawba">Catawbas</orgName> between No. and So.
                            Carolina</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="piantia">Piantias</orgName>, a wandering Tribe on
                            both sides of the Missisipi</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>800</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The Kasquiriasguiae, or <orgName key="kaska">Illinois</orgName> in
                            general on<lb/> the Illinois River, &amp; between the Ouabache,
                            &amp;<lb/> the Missisipi</cell>
                        <cell>(some say, 40)</cell>
                        <cell>600</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="piank">Piankeshaws</orgName><lb/>The
                            Onachtenons<lb/>The <orgName key="kicka">Kickapous</orgName></cell>
                        <cell>On the Quabache</cell>
                        <cell>[100]...250 <lb/>250...400 <lb/>500...300</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="shawnee">Shawnese</orgName> on the Siotta</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="delaware">Delewares</orgName> on the W. of the
                            Ohio</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="miami">Maimis</orgName> on the Miami river falling
                            into Lake Erie &amp; the Miamis</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>350</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><orgName key="creek">The Upper Creeks back of Georgia,<lb/>The Middle
                                Creeks behind West Florida<lb/>The Lower Creeks in East
                                Florida</orgName></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>4000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="creek">Caouitas</orgName>, on the East of the River
                            Albamous</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>700</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="arkansas">Arkansas</orgName> on the Arkansas River
                            falling<lb/>into the Mississipi on the West side</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="anjuer">Anjuer</orgName>, north of the
                            Missouri</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="paddonia">Paddonias</orgName> West of the
                            Mississipi</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The White <orgName key="pawnee">Panies</orgName>,<lb/>The pickled or
                            prickles Panies</cell>
                        <cell>So. of the Mississipi</cell>
                        <cell>2000<lb/>2000</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Carried forward...</cell>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline">24,350</emph></cell>
                    </row>

                    <pb n="40" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_26"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>brought forward...</cell>
                        <cell>24,350</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="canves">Canves</orgName>...<lb/>The <orgName
                                key="osage">Osayes</orgName>...<lb/>The <orgName key="grandeaux"
                                >Grand Eaux</orgName>...</cell>
                        <cell>South of the Missouri</cell>
                        <cell>1,600,<lb/>600 <lb/>1000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="missouri">Missouri</orgName> on the River
                            Missouri...</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>3,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="sioux">Sioux</orgName> of the Woods <lb/>The Sioux
                            of the Meadows</cell>
                        <cell>towards the heads<lb/>of the Missippi</cell>
                        <cell>1800 <lb/>2,500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The Blancs Barbus, or <orgName key="whiteind">White
                            Indians</orgName><lb/>with Beards</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>1,500</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="assiniboine﻿">Assiniboils</orgName>
                            <lb/>The <orgName key="cree">Christineaux</orgName></cell>
                        <cell>far North, near the...<lb/>Lakes of the  same name</cell>
                        <cell>1,500<lb/>3,000</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="ouiscon">Quisconsins</orgName>, </cell>
                        <cell>on  a River of that Name that<lb/>falls into the Missisippi on the
                            east side...</cell>
                        <cell>550 </cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>The  <orgName key="mascouten">Mascontens</orgName>...<lb/>The <orgName
                                key="sacks">Sakis</orgName>...<lb/>The  Michekonakis</cell>
                        <cell>South of Puans Bay...</cell>
                        <cell>500<lb/> 400<lb/> 250</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="menominee">Folle Avoine</orgName>,<lb/>The
                            Puans...</cell>
                        <cell>or the wild oat Indians...<lb/>(near Puans Bay)...</cell>
                        <cell>350<lb/>700</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="potaw">Powtowatamis</orgName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>near St. Joseph's River...<lb/>and <placeName key="detro"
                                >Detroit</placeName></cell>
                        <cell>350</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="missisauga">Missesaguis</orgName>,  or River Indians
                            being...<lb/>wandering Tribes on the <geogName key="lakeh">Lakes
                                Huron</geogName> and <geogName key="lakes"
                            >Superior</geogName></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>2,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="ottawa">Ottahwas</orgName>...<lb/>The  <orgName
                                key="ojibwe">Chipewas</orgName>...</cell>
                        <cell>near <geogName key="lakes">Lake Superior</geogName> and <geogName
                                key="lakem">Michigan</geogName></cell>
                        <cell>900<lb/>5,000</cell>
                    </row>


                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="wyandot">Wiandots</orgName>, near <geogName
                                key="lakee">Lake Erie</geogName></cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="sxntns">Six nations</orgName>, or the <orgName
                                key="iroquois">Iroquois</orgName></cell>
                        <cell>on the <lb/>Frontiers of  New York...</cell>
                        <cell>1,500</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="roundhd">Roundheaded Indians</orgName> near the head
                            of<lb/>the  <geogName key="ottar">Ottahwa River</geogName>...</cell>
                        <cell>2,500</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell><orgName key="algonquin">Algonquins</orgName>, </cell>
                        <cell>near the above...</cell>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline"> 300 </emph></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>56,450</cell>
                    </row>

                    <pb n="41" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_26"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>brought forward..</cell>
                        <cell>56,450</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="nipissing">Nipissins</orgName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>near the <geogName key="ottar">Ottahwa  River</geogName>...</cell>
                        <cell>400</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="chalas">Chalas</orgName>...<lb/>The <orgName
                                key="amelestes">Amelistes</orgName>... <lb/>The <orgName
                                key="miemick">Miemicks</orgName>... <lb/>The <orgName key="abenaki"
                                >Abenaquies</orgName>... <lb/></cell>
                        <cell>St. Lawrence Indians<lb/> on the back  of<lb/>Nova Scotia...</cell>
                        <cell>130<lb/>550<lb/>700 <lb/>350</cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell>The <orgName key="mohawk">Conawaybrunas</orgName>, </cell>
                        <cell>near the  Falls<lb/>of St. Lewis...</cell>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline"> 200 </emph></cell>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Total amount...</cell>
                        <cell>58,780</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-02">7 mo.2nd.</date>
                    <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The weather for several days past<lb/> being very sultry, Our Landlord invited
                    the<lb/> whole of our Company, viz. Six Friends,<lb/>
                    <persName key="wwils1">Wm.Wilson</persName>, (Merchant from <placeName
                        key="fpitt1">Fort Pitt</placeName> &amp; Indian<lb/> interpretter,)
                        <persName key="wmcco1">Doctor McCoskry</persName>, &amp; <persName
                        key="jheck1">J. Heckenvelder</persName>,<lb/> to spend the Day at his Farm
                    about five<lb/> miles below on the opposite side of the<lb/> River.- We set off
                    about 9 oClock, taking<lb/> with us provision &amp;ca., and spent an<lb/>
                    agreeable day under a pleasant Shade on<lb/> the Banks of the River, - returning
                    home<lb/> in the afternoon we cross'd the River, and<lb/> some of us landed at
                    the Spring Well &amp; walk'd<lb/> home, the distance being three miles, and
                    the<lb/> Road very pleasant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-03">3d.</date>
                    <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <pb n="42" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_27"/>
                <p> Perplex'd with various reports, and<lb/> contradictory opinions.- it is said,
                    the<lb/> American A:rmy ie still advancing, and<lb/> that an encampment is form
                    'd, in front of<lb/>
                    <placeName key="fjeff">Fort Jefferson</placeName>, within 30 miles of where
                    the<lb/> last Battle was fought.- that the Indians<lb/> are more &amp; more
                    settled in their <del><gap/></del><lb/> determination, that nothing short of
                    the<lb/> boundary line being fixt on the <geogName key="ohior">River
                        Ohio</geogName>,<lb/> will ever induce them to lay down the<lb/> Hatchet, -
                    that, in consequence of this<lb/> resolution, they have sent a deputation<lb/>
                    to the Commissioners at <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>, in
                    order,<lb/> if their instructions does not impower<lb/> them to make such a
                    Cession, to prevent<lb/> their taking the unnecessary trouble of<lb/> coming
                    forward any further.- indeed,<lb/> it seems to be the prevailing opinion of<lb/>
                    the day, that there will be no Treaty at<lb/> all. - A number of Philadelphia
                    and<lb/> New York News Papers came to <persName key="cengl1">Colt
                        England</persName><lb/> by the Ottaway, some as late as the <date
                        when="1793-06-23">23d</date> of<lb/> last Month, <del>since</del> we have
                    been favour'd<lb/>
                    <pb n="43" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_27"/> with the perusal of most of them - we<lb/>
                    were sorry to find some irritating and<lb/> inflamatory pieces, particularly
                    one, which<lb/> censures the Government of the United States,<lb/> for
                    attempting to Treat with the Indians,<lb/> under British influence, ungenerously<lb/>
                    <del><gap/></del> branding the whole of that Nation with<lb/> the opprobious
                    epithet of Cut Throats. - all<lb/> the officers, that we have as yet heard
                    speak<lb/> upon the subject, make light of it, and<lb/> say, it is but little
                    more than what, at<lb/> times, appear in their own prints -<lb/> whither it is
                    really their contempt of<lb/> such scandalous pieces, or their politeness,<lb/>
                    which will not permit them to give us<lb/> uneasiness, that makes them
                    appear<lb/> so indifferent, is what I will not determine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-04">4th.</date>
                    <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Extremely Warm &amp; sultry, light airs of<lb/> Wind from the South West. -
                        <persName key="cmons1">Captn. Monsey</persName><lb/> inform 'd us that the
                    Thermometer belonging<lb/> to the Officers was, in the Shade, up to 100,<lb/> in
                    the Sun it rose to 117 degrees.</p>
                <pb n="44" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_28"/>
                <p> from the best information I can gather it<lb/> appears that a great proportion
                    of the Country<lb/> around the Lakes is low and Marshy, so as to<lb/> be wholly
                    incapable of cultivation, and in<lb/> many places, of great extent, almost<lb/>
                    intirely cover 'd with Water, in which grow <lb/>the Timber and long Grass,
                    affording shelter<lb/> for wild Beasts, and Vermin, in abundance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-05">5th.</date>
                    <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Had an interview with a Young <orgName key="shawnee">Shaw-<lb/>-nese</orgName>
                    Warrior, who is lately from the Council<lb/> at the Rapids - his Brother is a
                    head Man<lb/> amongst them, and he being often with<lb/> them in Council, is
                    acquainted with the result<lb/> of their deliberations, so far as they have
                    come<lb/> to a conclusion among themselves - he inform'd<lb/> us, there are
                    about 1200 collected at the Rapids,<lb/> mostly the Northern Indians, and 700
                    of<lb/> the Southern Indians, are embodied at<lb/> another place, a considerable
                    distance,<lb/> up the same River, watching the motions of <persName key="gwayn1"
                        >General Waynes</persName><lb/> Army.­ he confirms the account of a<lb/>
                    Deputation being sent to the Commissioners,<lb/> and that the object of their
                    Mission was, in<lb/> substance, the same as has already been<lb/> noted - that
                    they have most decidedly come<lb/>
                    <pb n="45" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_28"/> to a resolution, to accept of no terms
                    short of<lb/> making the <geogName key="ohior">Ohio</geogName> the boundary
                    line. - Our<lb/> Interpretter was formerly a Prisoner among the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="shawnee">Shawnese</orgName>, and had been adopted into the
                    family<lb/> of this Young Man, in the place of his Father,<lb/> and in their
                    discourse the Indian gave him<lb/> that appellation, saying, <said
                        who="undetermined">my Father, I will<lb/> tell you what I know, and speak
                        the truth - in<lb/> the begining of the World, this Land was given<lb/> to
                        the Indians, and the White People were placed<lb/> beyond the great water -
                        when the white Men<lb/> first came to this Land, the wise old Men<lb/> among
                        the Indians, told their People, that if<lb/> they received anything of the
                        white Men, they<lb/> would be destroyed,­ "the bitter Water was made<lb/>
                        for white folks, but the Water of the Brooks and<lb/> Rivers for, the
                        Indians</said>, - but not regarding<lb/> this advice, many of the Nations
                    Traded with<lb/> the Whites, took their Hatchets, Knives and<lb/> Rum, and gave
                    up their Land for trifles,<lb/> and, according to the ancient prediction,
                    they<lb/> have wasted away, and some of them -<lb/> become quite extinct, and
                    the few that<lb/> are remaining are driven, almost to<lb/>
                    <pb n="46" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_29"/> to where the sun sets, but they are
                    now<lb/> determined to be driven no further, should<lb/> they go to where the
                    Sun sets, they would<lb/> all be lost forever. - The Congress must<lb/> remove
                    their Forts, and all their People over<lb/> the River, and then the Indians will
                    take<lb/> them by the hand, and become their true<lb/> friends - but should the
                    Commissioners<lb/> meet the Indians in Council, and there<lb/> pretend that they
                    have conquered their<lb/> Country, and will not remove out of it, in<lb/> that
                    case, the Indians will withdraw from<lb/> the Council, and then, instantly, fall
                    upon<lb/> the opposite party, and destroy them all -<lb/> this is the substance
                    of what he said as<lb/> intrepretted by <persName key="sash1">Sylvester
                        Ash</persName>
                    <del>Sylv Ash</del>, as near as I can re-<lb/>member. -- This day the Ottaway
                    sail'd<lb/> for <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, in whom <persName
                        key="melli1">M.Elliott</persName> embark'd,<lb/> to be landed at the Mouth
                    of. the <geogName key="miamr">Miami River</geogName><lb/> - Thermometer, in the
                    Shade 102, in the<lb/> Sun 123 - In the evening after having<lb/> made the above
                    remarks, the <orgName key="shawnee">Shawen-<lb/>ese</orgName> Warriour
                    abovementioned return'd to our<lb/>
                    <pb n="47" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_29"/> our Lodgings, being in Liquor, he
                    desired<lb/> to enquire of the Landlord whither<lb/> he could tarry in hie House
                    all Night, but<lb/> being told that it was contrary to the regulations<lb/> of
                    the Garrison, he seemed to be displeased, and<lb/> ask'd for his Tomahawk, which
                        <persName key="sash1">Ash</persName> had in<lb/> keeping, and going up
                    stairs to get it, the<lb/> Indian followed him, and on receiving it,<lb/> said
                    he was Drunk, and did not know what<lb/> might happen before Night - then
                    lifting<lb/> his Tomahawk, attempted to strike <persName key="sash1"
                        >Ash</persName>,<lb/> who being upon his guard, seized his arm<lb/> and
                    pushed him down Stairs - he then<lb/> went up to <persName key="mdols1">M.
                        Dolsen</persName>, knock'd off his Hat,<lb/> and in the Indian tongue, bid
                    him be<lb/> Strong, and see if he could turn him<lb/> out, and made a stroke, in
                    which the<lb/> Hatchet flew off the halve. - <persName key="mdols1"
                        >Dolsen</persName> im-<lb/>-mediately seized him, turned him out of<lb/> the
                    House, and bruized him pretty much,<lb/> the Indian seeing his blood run,
                    and<lb/> having recovered his Tomahawk, flourished<lb/> it about in a great
                    rage, and in all<lb/>
                    <pb n="48" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_30"/> probability, had not <persName
                        key="cmons1">Capt. Munsey</persName>, an<lb/> officer of the Garrison, been
                    present, some<lb/> mischief would <del><gap/></del> have been done, but<lb/> the
                    captain took away his Tomahawk,<lb/> and sent for a Guard, who turn'd him
                    out<lb/> of the Fort.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-06">6th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Arrived the Sloop Felicity from the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="miamr">Miami River</geogName> - people here are more<lb/> and
                    more confirmed in the belief that it<lb/> will not be safe for us to
                        <del>attend</del> meet the<lb/> Indians at <placeName key="sandu"
                        >Sandusky</placeName>. - this day also<lb/> arrived the Schooner Nancy from <lb/>
                    <placeName key="michi">Michillamackanac</placeName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-07-07">7th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> being first day had a satisfactory<lb/> Meeting, at the usual place and
                    time,<lb/> in the Morning, and also Friends had<lb/> another at 4 in the
                    afternoon, five or<lb/> six miles from hence, at the <geogName key="rouger"
                        >River Rouge</geogName>,<lb/> at which, not being very well, I was<lb/> not
                    present. - <persName key="cjohn1">Captain John</persName> a Chief<lb/> of the
                        <orgName key="mohawk">Mohawk</orgName>s arrived from the Council<lb/> at the
                        <geogName key="miamr">Miami River</geogName>, and also two or three<lb/>
                    <pb n="49" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_30"/>
                    <orgName key="stockbridge">Indians of the Stockbridge Nation</orgName>,
                    with<lb/> a Letter from <persName key="haupa1"><persName key="haupa1">Captain
                            Hendrick</persName>s</persName>, their Chief<lb/> - they confirm the
                    accounts, already <del>receiv'd</del><lb/> received, of a deputation being set
                    down<lb/> to the Commissioners</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-08">8th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Had a visit from <persName key="dkenn1">David Kennedy</persName>, a<lb/> half
                    Indian, of the <orgName key="mohawk">Mohawk</orgName> Nation, who had<lb/> been
                    Educated in Scotland, sensible well-informed<lb/> Man, but too much adicted to
                    the vice so<lb/> prevalent among the Indians, the Love of<lb/> Rum, - he came in
                    company with <persName key="cjohn1">Capt.<lb/> John</persName> from the Council
                    - says he was<lb/> not admited into the secret Council of the<lb/> Indians, but
                    from what he could gather, was<lb/> not without a hope that peace may be<lb/>
                    established. - The <orgName key="stockbridge"> Stockbridge Indians</orgName>
                    <del>return'd</del><lb/> return'd to their Chief at the <geogName key="miamr"
                        >Miami</geogName>, with<lb/> a small supply of necessaries, afforded<lb/>
                    them by Friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-09">9th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Captain <persName key="bljac1">Blue Jacket</persName>, the famous Chief<lb/> of
                    the <orgName key="shawnee">Shawnese</orgName>, who commanded at the<lb/> defeat
                    of <persName key="gstcl">General St. Clair</persName>, paid us a Visit<lb/> this
                    morning, - he is a stout well-looking<lb/> Man of about 45 years of age, Dress'd in<lb/>
                    <pb n="50" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_31"/> in a Shirt, scarlet Coat, with gold
                    apaulets<lb/> and a Gold laced Hat, Leggins and Mockasins,<lb/> but, as all
                    other Indians are, without Breeches.<lb/> -He was very cautious of speaking
                    upon<lb/> public affairs, said he was not the Head-<lb/>Man of his Nation, but
                    only a War-chief,<lb/> as such he had given his <del>opinions
                        with</del><lb/><del>them</del> sentiments to the Council, and now<lb/> left
                    it with them; whose business it was, to<lb/> determine as they might think
                    proper<lb/> - said he had heard we were in Detroit,<lb/> and having some
                    business this way, came<lb/> to see us, but had nothing to say on Public<lb/>
                    matters - he had often heard of Quakers, he<lb/> said, but had never seen any of
                    them be-<lb/>fore, and, expressing his regard for them,<lb/> and satisfaction
                    with the Visit, took his<lb/> leave. - Friends had a desire to be more<lb/>
                    particular with him, in regard to the Objects<lb/> which induced them to take
                    this long Jour-<lb/>ney, but the Interpretter not seeming to<lb/> be disposed to
                    gratify them in that respect,<lb/> they were constrained, after expressing a
                    little<lb/> of their desires for the Peace and wellfare of <del>man kin</del><lb/>
                    <pb n="51" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_31"/> mankind, to be silent. - <persName
                        key="bljac1">Blue Jacket</persName><lb/> said that should the Commissioners
                    &amp; Indians<lb/> meet at a Treaty, and matters like to be ac-<lb/>-commodated,
                    it was his opinion it would<lb/> be two Months before the business would be<lb/>
                    compleated. - this day sail'd the Schooner<lb/> Nancy for <placeName key="ferie"
                        >Fort Erie</placeName>, a Merchant Vessell, with<lb/> a Cargo of Peltry, and
                    Indian-made Maple-<lb/> Sugar, by this it may appear, that a greater<lb/>
                    quantity of Sugar is procured from the Indians<lb/> than is consumed in this
                    part of the Country,<lb/>how much lower down, the Country
                        <del>is</del><lb/><del><gap/></del> is <del>not</del> supplied <del>in</del>
                    the same way,<lb/> is what I cannot determine, but from the<lb/> best
                    information, I am ready to think, that<lb/> very little foreign Sugar, if any,
                        <del>if any foreign sugar</del> (except refined)<lb/> is consumed in Upper
                    Canada.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-10">10th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Arrived the Sloop Detroit from <placeName key="ferie">Fort<lb/>
                    Erie</placeName>, we hear by this Vessell that the-<lb/>Commissioners had taken
                    their passage<lb/> in the Dunmore, and may be hourly<lb/> expected.- The
                        <orgName key="ojibwe">Chippeways</orgName> in which the<lb/>
                    <pb n="52" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_32"/> the Indian Deputies embark'd, had not<lb/>
                    arrived at <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName> when the Detroit
                    Sail'd.<lb/> - We are told the Commissioners are not<lb/> to come to this
                    Garrison, but to Land, and<lb/> encamp, at the mouth of the River, there<lb/> to
                    wait the proper time to proceed to <placeName key="sandu"
                    >Sandusky</placeName><lb/> - in the Detroit came up the Cordage for a<lb/> new
                    Vessell, now building on Lake Superior</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-11">11th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Dined at <persName key="jabbo1">James Abbotts</persName>, a Merchant of
                    this<lb/> place, we were kindly entertained, and spent<lb/> an agreeable
                    afternoon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Spent the Day at <persName key="mdols1">M.Dolsen</persName>'s place on<lb/> the
                    East side of the River.- In the afternoon<lb/> sail'd the Sloop Detroit for the
                    Falls of St.Mary's,<lb/> and about the time arrived the<lb/> Sloop Saganough
                    from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, by this<lb/> Vessell we were
                    informed that the Commissioners<lb/> were all on on board the Dunmore,
                    ready<lb/> to sail, and only waiting for a Wind, when<lb/> the <orgName
                        key="ojibwe">Chippeway</orgName> arrived with the Indian<lb/> deputies, on
                    which a Council was held, the<lb/> result was, that, at the request of the Indians,<lb/>
                    <pb n="53" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_32"/> the Commissioners were to return to
                    Navy<lb/> Hall, in order that <persName key="gsimc1">Governor Simcoe</persName>
                    might<lb/> be present at the conference.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-13">13th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> was invited by <persName key="wbake1">Wm. Baker</persName>, late of New<lb/>
                    York, shipwright, to take a sail up the<lb/> River as far as <geogName
                        key="sincll">Lake Sinclair</geogName> - set off about<lb/> 9 oClock and had
                    a pleasant run up<lb/> to the upper end of Hog Island, from whence<lb/> we had a
                    view of <geogName key="sincll">Lake Sinclair</geogName>, and<lb/> return'd home
                    in the evening - for<lb/> about the distance of 10 miles, nothing<lb/> of the
                    kind, that ever I saw, exceeds the<lb/> banks of this River for the beauty of
                    its<lb/> prospects, - The Lots are all regularly laid<lb/> out, being in front
                    three square Acres<lb/> only in breadth, on which are the build-<lb/>-ings,
                    Gardens and Orchards.- In the<lb/> afternoon of this day arrived the Sloop<lb/>
                    Speedwell from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, who furnished<lb/>
                    us with intelligence from various-<lb/> quarters.- we had several Letters
                    from<lb/> Philadelphia address'd to our Company<lb/>
                    <pb n="54" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_33"/> jointly, and most of our friends had<lb/>
                    particular accounts from their dear<lb/> connections at Home. - we had also<lb/>
                    a joint letter from <persName key="cpick1">Col Pickering</persName>, in<lb/>
                    behalf of the Commissioners, with a large<lb/> bundle of Philadelphia Newspapers
                    as<lb/> late as the 6th ultimo. -- <persName key="cpick1">Col.
                        Pickering</persName><lb/> informs us they were all on board, and<lb/> ready
                    to Sail, when the Indian Deputies<lb/> arrived, who informed the
                    Commissioners,<lb/> their business was to have a conference<lb/> with them in
                    the presence of <persName key="gsimc1">Governor<lb/> Simcoe</persName>, this he
                    says will unavoidably<lb/> occasion a delay of some days, if not<lb/> supersede
                    the intended Treaty.- we<lb/> are now anxiously waiting the arrival<lb/> of the
                    Dunmore, who in all probability,<lb/> will either bring forward the
                    Commissioners,<lb/> or information that all hopes of a<lb/> Treaty are
                    vanished.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-14">14th</date>
                    <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> - Being first day had a Meeting in the<lb/> Sail Loft, which was large and
                        <del>on</del><lb/>
                    <pb n="55" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_33"/> on the whole satisfactory</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The Weather for these several Days past<lb/> has been cool and pleasant, the
                    wind N.W.<lb/> with a clear and serene sky­ Wheat Harvest<lb/> is now begun in
                    this neighbourhood</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-16">16th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Friends being a little uneasy with being<lb/> so long <del>in a state</del>
                    detained in a state of<lb/> idleness, waited upon <persName key="melli1">Matthew
                        Elliott</persName>, to<lb/> know his sentiments, in respect to our<lb/>
                    visiting the Indians assembled at the <geogName key="miamr"
                    >Miami</geogName><lb/> - he gave it as his opinion, that, as they<lb/> were now
                    holding a Council on their own<lb/> affairs, it would not be prudent, without
                    an<lb/> invitation from them, to take such a step;<lb/><del>but if Friends</del>
                    but, as he expected to go there<lb/> himself in a Day or two, if Friends
                    had<lb/> an inclination to send them a Message,<lb/> he would punctually deliver
                    it. - This<lb/> being taken into consideration, and there<lb/> being a
                    probability that we may not<lb/> have another opportunity of communicating<lb/>
                    our sentiments, and the motives which<lb/>
                    <pb n="56" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_34"/> which induced us to come forward,<lb/> we
                    gladly accepted the offer</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-17">17th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="celli1">Captain Elliott</persName> intending this day<lb/> for
                    the Indian Council, the following ad-<lb/>dress was agreed to, and enclosed in
                    a<lb/> Letter to <persName key="cmcke1">Colonel McKee</persName>, who is
                    desired<lb/> to communicate the same to the Indians</p>
                <floatingText type="letter">
                    <body>
                        <opener>
                            <salute>To the Indians, assembled at the <geogName key="miamr1"
                                    >Rapids<lb/> of the Miami</geogName></salute></opener>
                        <p> Brothers,<lb/>We who send you this Letter<lb/> are of the People called
                            Quakers, and have<lb/> left our homes and families in Pensylvania<lb/>
                            and New Jersey, and taken this long Journey<lb/> to see you purely from
                            motives of Love and<lb/> good will, and to endeavour to promote<lb/>
                            peace.- We have been now five weeks at<lb/> Detroit waiting for the
                            opening of the Treaty<lb/> at <placeName key="sandu"
                                >Sandusky</placeName>, where we expected to have seen<lb/> you all,
                            but as we have heard a number<lb/> of your People are gone to <placeName
                                key="niaga">Niagara</placeName> to meet<lb/> the Commissioners, we
                            do not know but the<lb/> business may be so concluded there, as that<lb/>
                            <pb n="57" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_34"/> they may come no farther.</p>
                        <p> Brothers, We have brought with us an<lb/> address to you from our
                            Brethren at home<lb/> which we are very desirous of presenting to<lb/>
                            you with our own hands, if an opportunity<lb/> can be had. - it is also
                            in our hearts to<lb/> acquaint you that we consider all Men<lb/> as the
                            Children of one common Father, and<lb/> think it our duty to Love all as
                            Brothers.<lb/> -We believe it displeases the Great and Good<lb/> Spirit
                            when Men injure and kill one<lb/> another, therefore we endeavour to do
                            Justice,<lb/> but when any dispute arises, we leave it<lb/> to be
                            settled by disinterested and impartial<lb/> persons, and never go to war
                            on any-<lb/> occasion.- We have been made very<lb/> sorrowful on account
                            of the War and bloodshed<lb/> between the United States and our
                            Indian<lb/> Brethren, and want much to see you<lb/> that we may open our
                            Hearts more<lb/> fully than we can do by writing, for we<lb/>
                            <pb n="58" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_35"/> are fully convinced that by
                            looking up<lb/> to the Great Spirit for Counsel, all differences<lb/>
                            may be settled without fighting and killing<lb/> one another, which we
                            think is very<lb/> Cruel and attended with many distressing<lb/>
                            circumstances both to you and the White People.</p>
                        <p> Our society have experienced for more<lb/> than one hundred years great
                            advantage<lb/> and satisfaction in living Peaceably with<lb/> all Men,
                            and are very desirous that you<lb/> may enjoy the same benefits, and to
                            that<lb/> end were made willing to expose ourselves,<lb/> encounter
                            hardships, and spend our sub-<lb/>stance to promote Peace and Love
                            between<lb/> you and the Government of the United<lb/> States.- We pray
                            the Good Spirit<lb/> that He may put an end to the ravages<lb/> of War
                            and unite all Men as Brethren,<lb/> that by being bound together in one
                            great<lb/> Chain of Love and friendship which <del>can</del><lb/> cannot
                            be broken, we may all seek the<lb/> happiness of each other in this
                            Life, and<lb/> be <del><unclear>prepared</unclear></del> prepared for
                            the enjoyment of<lb/>
                            <pb n="59" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_35"/> of everlasting happiness in the
                            Life<lb/> which is to come.</p>
                        <closer><dateline><placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>
                                <date when="1793-07-17">7 mo 17th,
                                1793</date></dateline><signed>J.P.<lb/> J.M.<lb/> J.L.<lb/>W.S.<lb/>
                                J.E.<lb/> W.H.</signed></closer>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-18">18th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Some of our Friends had an interview<lb/> with a Person of the Name of Wilbank,
                    who-<lb/> within a few days past arrived, with a Party<lb/> of 26 Southern
                    Indians, from the back parts of<lb/> the Carolina's and Georgia, at the Great
                    Council<lb/> at the Miami, - he came from thence to this<lb/> place, and a
                    Vessel is to be dispatched immediately<lb/> to carry him down to <persName
                        key="gsimc1">Governor Simcoe</persName>. He says,<lb/> that the Indians have
                    in several instances<lb/> been grossly imposed upon, particularly by<lb/>
                    <persName key="gblou1">Governor Blount</persName>, who by bribing an
                    Interpreter<lb/> had cheated them out of a great extent of<lb/> Country, and
                    defrauded them of one half<lb/> the Sum, agreed upon to be paid yearly, as<lb/>
                    as a compensation for the Land granted,-<lb/> in one instance where they had
                    agreed to<lb/> sell 50 miles square they had fraudulently<lb/> put in the Deed
                    80 miles - and where they had<lb/>
                    <pb n="60" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_36"/> had bargained for an extent of 10
                    miles<lb/> round the Town of Nashville, <persName key="gblou1">Governor
                        Blount</persName><lb/> had caused 40 miles to be inserted.- and instead<lb/>
                    of a Consideration of 2000 Dollars yearly, he had<lb/> put down but 1000
                    dollars.- This being but<lb/> one side of the question, we do not pretend
                    to<lb/> Judge, but it is the received opinion here, that<lb/> their errand to
                    the Council is, to form a Union<lb/> with the Northern Indians, and make
                    One<lb/> common cause, either in forming a Treaty,<lb/> or carrying on a War. -
                    The Vessell (the Felicity) to Carry<lb/> Wilbank to <placeName key="ferie">Fort
                        Erie</placeName>, sail'd about 2 oClock:-<lb/> - Yesterday a young Man going
                    out to look<lb/> for Horses, got lost in the Woods, which are very<lb/> thick
                    within less than a Mile of the Fort.-<lb/> several 18 pounders were fired in the
                    afternoon<lb/> in order to direct him in finding the way back,<lb/> which, I
                    suppose had the desired effect, as I am<lb/> informed he got safe home in the
                    Evening -<lb/>- several instances of the kind have before<lb/> occurred, and
                    sometimes the persons lost have<lb/> never returned. - It is said some little
                    time<lb/> past, two Indians were kill'd by the Wolves<lb/> in the Neighbourhood
                    of this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="61" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_36"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-19">19th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Having received many civilities from<lb/> the officers of the 24th British
                    Regiment, now at<lb/> this place, gratitude induces me to wish to<lb/> remember
                    their names, which from a printed<lb/> account published in the year <date
                        when="1792">1792</date>, I find to be<lb/> as follows.-</p>

                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Lt.Col-</cell>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline">Lieutenants</emph></cell>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline">Ensigns</emph></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="cengl1">Richd. England</persName> 2D</cell>
                        <cell><persName key="wshor1">W.C.Short.D</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="wkell1">Wm. Kelly</persName> D</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="wcamp1">Willm. Campbell</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="wrobi1">Wlm. Robison</persName> D.</cell>
                        <cell><persName key="cvand1">C.Vandeleur</persName> D</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline">Major~~</emph></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="gmeyr1">Geo. Meyrick</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="fobri1">F.J., O'Brien</persName> D</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline">Captains</emph></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="rchris1">R. Christmas</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="jstro1">J.C. Strong</persName></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="jblak1">John Blake</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="ttalb1">Thos. Talbot</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="jbroa1">J.R. Broadhead</persName> D</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="rneil1">Robn. Neill</persName>, D</cell>
                        <cell><persName key="lhenn1">Edmd. Henn D</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="tspen1">Thos. Spencer</persName></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="cfree1">Quin John Freeman D</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="candr1">Chs.S. Andrews</persName> D</cell>
                        <cell><persName key="abill1">Allan Billingham</persName> D</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="wdoyl1">William Doyle</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="edonn1">Ed<unclear/> Donnell</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="afost1">Andrew Foster.</persName></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="eleyb1">E. W. Leybourne</persName> D</cell>
                        <cell><persName key="jmaga1">Jam. Magarth</persName></cell>
                        <cell><persName key="jcraw1">-- Crawford-D</persName></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="pmoun1">Paul Mounsey</persName> D</cell>
                        <cell><persName key="rfost1">Richd. Foster</persName></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="fspee1">Ferg. Speers</persName>,</cell>
                        <cell><persName key="jblun1">Joseph Blunt</persName></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><persName key="cearl1">Chs. Earle</persName> Ct. Lt.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-20">20th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> The Wind which for many days past<lb/> has been from the S.W.and
                    consequently<lb/> unfavourable for coming up the Lake, yesterday<lb/> and today
                    has blown from the N.E., so that<lb/> we are now hourly in hopes of having<lb/>
                    intelligence from below, which we expect<lb/> will cause our immediate removal
                    from<lb/> this place</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-21">21st</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <pb n="62" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_37"/>
                <p> Being First Day, a Meeting was<lb/> held at 10 oClock in the Sail Loft and<lb/>
                    another at the same place at 5 in the<lb/> afternoon, both satisfactory.</p>
                <p> About Noon arrived <persName key="lgive1">Lieut. Givens</persName>
                    <del>Gibbons</del> of<lb/> the Queens Rangers, who brought the agree<lb/>able
                    intelligence that the Dunmore, with<lb/> the Commissioners on Board had arrived
                    at<lb/> the mouth of the River. - About 5 oClock,<lb/> (having Landed the
                    Commissioners) the<lb/> Dunmore came up to the wharf, - in<lb/> the evening had
                    a Visit from <persName key="lgive1">Lt. Givens</persName>
                    <del>Gibbons</del>,<lb/> by him we are informed that the Com-<lb/>missioners are
                    come forward with a<lb/> full expectation of a Treaty, very speedily,<lb/> being
                    held. - He says the Deputation from<lb/> the Indians, who had a conference
                    with<lb/> the Commissioners in the presence of <persName key="gsimc1"
                        >Govnr.<lb/> Simcoe</persName>, to all appearance, return'd well<lb/>
                    satisfied, and that in his opinion there<lb/> is a great probability of <del>an
                        accomodation</del> matters being<lb/> accomodated. - That the main
                    business<lb/> of the Indian Deputies was to enquire, in<lb/>
                    <pb n="63" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_37"/> in the first place, whither the
                    Com-<lb/>-missioners were properly authorized to<lb/> treat, and secondly,
                    whither they had<lb/> power to recede from the boundary-<lb/><del>Line</del> now
                    claimed by the United States,<lb/> and being satisfied in both these
                    points,<lb/> they took the Commissioners by the hand, and<lb/> presenting them
                    with a Belt of white Wamp<lb/>-um, invited them to come forward to the<lb/>
                    Treaty. - We are informed by <persName key="cford1">Captain<lb/> Ford</persName>
                    that he has orders to attend upon the<lb/> Commissioners with his Vessell, and
                    expects<lb/> to be ready to proceed to the Mouth of<lb/> the River in a Day or
                    two.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-22">22d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> We were busy in settling our little<lb/> concerns, and preparing to leave
                        <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <del>ware</del> where we have experienced many marks<lb/> of polite attention,
                    and hospitallity, especially<lb/> from the officers of the Garrison, beyond
                    what<lb/> some of us expected or even flatter'd ourselves<lb/> was our due. -
                    Our way hitherto, in every<lb/>
                    <pb n="64" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_38"/> every sense, has been made pleasant<lb/>
                    beyond what could have been foreseen,<lb/> or reasonably expected, - for this
                    great<lb/> favour, thanksgiving and praises are<lb/> due to the Great Author of
                    every good</p>
                <p> --The kind attention which, <emph rend="underline">unrecom-</emph><lb/><emph
                        rend="underline">mended</emph>, we have received from Strangers, I<lb/>
                    hope, will ever be kept in grateful re-<lb/>membrance, and I cannot but
                    conclude,<lb/> the obligation is greatly enhanced by the<lb/> persuasion, that
                    it proceeded not from<lb/> sinester motives, but was simply<lb/> the effusion of
                    noble and generous Minds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-07-23">23d</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning <persName key="cengl1">Col. England</persName> called<lb/> at our
                    Quarters, and kindly offered to<lb/> lend us his Barge to go down <del>to go
                        down</del><lb/> the River, or accommodate us in any<lb/> other way that
                    might be more agreeable,<lb/> but, as the Dunmore would be ready to Sail<lb/> on
                    the morning of the <date when="1793-07-25">25th</date>, he would re-<lb/>commend
                    it to us to wait untill that<lb/> time and go down in her - we<lb/>
                    <pb n="65" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_38"/> acknowledged his kindness, and
                    concluded<lb/> to go in the Dunmore -- We were this<lb/> Day visited by a young
                        <orgName key="shawnee">Shawnese</orgName> Warriour,<lb/> a relation of
                        <persName key="cmcke1">Col.McKee</persName>, the Brish Agent,<lb/> - His
                    Shirt was red stript Persian, orna-<lb/>mented with One thousand Six hundred
                    small<lb/> round silver Broaches.- He was accompanied<lb/> by another Beau, the
                    rim of whose Ears were<lb/> cut all round, <del>except about an inch of
                        the</del><lb/><del>upper</del>
                    <del>end</del>
                    <del>part</del> - the part thus cut was so<lb/> streatch'd, and wound about with
                    coarse<lb/> brass wire, that it form'd an Oval of about<lb/> three inches in
                    length and two in breadth,<lb/> at the lower end of <del>which</del> each hung
                        <del>an</del><lb/> a Silver Cross, of above four
                            <del><unclear>three</unclear></del> inches long.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-24">24th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> Got most of our Baggage, Stores etc. on<lb/> board the Dunmore, <persName
                        key="cford1">Captain Ford</persName> informing<lb/> us he intended to sail
                    early in the<lb/> Morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-07-25">25th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p> About 9 oClock embark'd on board<lb/> the Dunmore for the mouth of <geogName
                        key="detror">Detroit River</geogName><lb/>
                    <pb n="66" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_39"/> River. - <persName key="cengl1">Col
                        England</persName> having a desire<lb/> to see the Commissioners took a
                    passage<lb/> with us, together with <persName key="lhenn1">Lieut.
                        Henn</persName>, and<lb/> Ensign <persName key="fobri1">O 'Brien</persName>.
                    - We had a pleasant<lb/> Sail down the River, and in our way<lb/> spoke the
                    Schooner Nancy from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>.<lb/> -at 2
                    oClock P.M. anchor'd opposite the<lb/> House of <persName key="melli1">M.
                        Elliott</persName>, where the Commissioners<lb/> have taken up their
                    quarters-<lb/> We met<lb/> with a kind reception, and were truly<lb/> glad to
                    find our very respectable fellow<lb/> Travellers in good health and spirits.
                    --</p>
                <p> - <persName key="cbunb1">Captain Bunbury</persName> of the 5th. Regimt.<lb/> and
                        <persName key="lgive1">Lieutn. Givens</persName> of the Queens Rangers<lb/>
                    are appointed by <persName key="gsimc1">Govn. Simcoe</persName> to bear<lb/> the
                    Commissioners company to the<lb/> Treaty. - in the evening we<lb/> pitch'd our
                    Tents on a very pleasant<lb/> Green on the River side, near the<lb/> House where
                    the Commissnrs. reside. - Our<lb/> little encampment now consists of<lb/> Twelve
                    Tents.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-26">26th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <pb n="67" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_39"/>
                <p> a very sultry day, - walk'd<lb/> about a Mile &amp; a half down the
                        <del>River</del><lb/> Lake to <persName key="sgirt1">Simon
                    Girty</persName>'s, who is an<lb/> Indian interpretter in the Brittish<lb/>
                    Service, and now attending the<lb/> Council at the <geogName key="miamr">Miami
                        River</geogName> - in<lb/> the evening it became Cloudy with<lb/> distant
                    Thunder, and before morning<lb/> we had a very heavy Rain with much<lb/> Thunder
                    and Lightning - some of the<lb/> company were obliged to quit their Tents<lb/>
                    and take shelter in the House.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-27">27th</date>. <placeName key="detro"/></dateline>
                <p> This morning an opportunity<lb/> presenting, <persName key="wsave1">William
                        Savery</persName> and <persName key="jmoor1">Jos.<lb/> Moore</persName> went
                    up to <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName> in Company<lb/> with <persName
                        key="gsans1">Gotlob Sansemen</persName>, a Preacher among<lb/> the <orgName
                        key="moraind">Moravian Indians</orgName> who reside on the<lb/> River La
                    Trench.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-28">28th</date>. <placeName key="grosi"/></dateline>
                <p>
                    <persName key="jparr1">John Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jlind1">Jacob
                        Lindley</persName>, <del>and</del><lb/>
                    <persName key="jelli1">John Elliott</persName> and myself, went over to<lb/>
                    <pb n="68" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_40"/> to <geogName key="grosi">Gros
                        Isle</geogName> where we had a Meeting<lb/> at the House of <persName
                        key="wmcco2">Wm. McComb Esqr.</persName>, who<lb/> for the most part resides
                    at Detroit, where<lb/> his family is at present. - a considerable<lb/> number of
                    the Inhabitants were present<lb/> - <geogName key="grosi">Gros Isle</geogName>
                    is situated at the Mouth of<lb/>
                    <geogName key="detror">Detroit River</geogName>, is seven miles long and<lb/>
                    two wide - The soil and Timber remarkably<lb/> good, the whole being the
                    property of <persName key="wmcco2">Wm.<lb/> McComb</persName>. - several of our
                    acquaintance<lb/> came from <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName> to pay us
                    a Visit, among<lb/> whom <persName key="jasqu1">John Asquith</persName> and
                        <persName key="fcorn1">Francs. Cornwall</persName><lb/> - in the evening a
                    number of the<lb/>
                    <orgName key="oneida">Oneida Indians</orgName>, the same who arrived<lb/> the
                    first of this Month, were encouraged<lb/> by some of the young Men of our
                    Company<lb/> to have a Dance, - they began about<lb/> 8 oClock and continued
                    untill 2 in the<lb/> Morning, during which time, their<lb/> Music and Shouts,
                    effectually prevented<lb/> us from Sleeping.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="69" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_40"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-29">29th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>

                <p>
                    <persName key="wsave1">Willm. Savery</persName> return'd from Detroit<lb/> in
                    Company with <persName key="cfree1">Capt. Freeman</persName> and Ensign<lb/>
                    <persName key="jbroa1">Broadhead</persName>, <persName key="jmoor3">Joseph
                        Moore</persName> intending to<lb/> come down with the Schooner Nancy<lb/>
                    who it is expected will leave <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>
                    tomorrow<lb/> on her way to <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>.- In
                    the evening<lb/> arrived two large Batteaux, with <persName key="celli1"
                        >Captain<lb/> Elliott</persName>, <persName key="tmcke1">Tho.
                        McKee</persName> (son of the <persName key="cmcke1">Col.</persName>)
                    and<lb/> a number of Indians who are said to be a<lb/> deputation from the great
                    Council - <persName key="emcke1">Elliott<lb/> McKee</persName> and some others
                    came over to<lb/> us, but the Indians landed on an Island<lb/> opposite to our
                    Encampment. - We are<lb/> informed the Indians at the Council are<lb/> much
                    dissatisfied with the conduct of their<lb/> Chiefs who met the Commissioners at
                    Navy Hall<lb/> - that they either mistook their instructions,<lb/> or neglected
                    to follow them, in consequence<lb/> of which, this second Deputation is
                    sent.</p>
                <p> - Their first and Principal business we<lb/> are told is to know of the
                    Commissioners whither<lb/>
                    <pb n="70" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_41"/> whither they have power to make the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="ohior">Ohio</geogName> the boundary line, if not, the whole<lb/>
                    business is at an end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-30">30th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About 9 A.M. the Indian Deputies,<lb/> twenty five in number, came over and<lb/>
                    had a public conference with the Commissionrs</p>
                <p> -Their speaker (whose name in English is <persName key="carry1"
                            >Carry-<del>folks</del> People-<lb/> about</persName>) express'd their
                    gladness that it had pleas'd<lb/> the Great Spirit to bring the Commissioners
                    thus<lb/> far in safety and good health, and then<lb/> proceeding to business,
                    said, there had some<lb/> mistake happened <del><gap/></del> at the Conference
                    at <placeName key="nav">Navy<lb/> Hall</placeName>, <del>and</del> in order to
                    rectify which they<lb/> had now come forward wih a message<lb/> from the
                    Council, and, that they might not<lb/> be liable to blunder a second time, they
                    had<lb/> brought a Paper, which spoke what was in their <del>their
                    whole</del><lb/> Heart. - They then delivered the Letter, being<lb/> in
                    substance the same as we were told last<lb/> night, - After a few minutes
                    private consul-<lb/>tation, <persName key="glinc1">Genl. Lincoln</persName>, in
                    behalf of the Commiss.<lb/> told <del>them</del> the Indians, that the Contents
                    of the<lb/>
                    <pb n="71" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_41"/> Paper should be considered, and an
                    Answer<lb/> given Tomorrow. - We were inform'd,<lb/> that, as <persName
                        key="celli1">Capt.Elliott</persName>, when he parted with<lb/> the
                    Commissioners, on going to the <geogName key="miamr">Miami</geogName>,<lb/>
                    fully expected their would be a Treaty, had<lb/> concluded to leave the Letter
                    to <persName key="cmcke1">Col. McKee</persName><lb/> (inclosing our Address to
                    the Indians) of the<lb/>
                    <date when="1793-07-17">17th</date>, with the Comissnrs. to be return'd to
                    us,<lb/> which has been done accordingly.- about<lb/> 4 P.M. <persName
                        key="jmoor3">Joseph Moore</persName> landed from the<lb/> Schooner Nancy,
                    having left Detroit about<lb/> 10 in the morning,- the Nancy proceeded on<lb/>
                    her way to <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-07-31">31st</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> The Indians came over about 10 oClock, but<lb/> were informed that an answer
                    would not be ready<lb/> for them before 5 in the afternoon,- about<lb/> that
                    time the Deputies assembled, and <persName key="cpick1">Col.<lb/>
                        Pickering</persName>, in behalf of the Commissioners, ap<lb/> -pologized for
                    making them wait so long for<lb/> an answer.- He then according to the<lb/>
                    Indian custom, repeated over the Contents of<lb/> the written message brought
                    from the Council<lb/> at the Miami, and proceed to read a very<lb/>
                    <pb n="72" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_42"/> lengthy answer, which in the first
                    place<lb/> pointed out the improbability of any part of<lb/> the business being
                    misunderstood at the conference<lb/> at <placeName key="fniag"
                        >Niagara</placeName>, and stated such facts as made<lb/> it appear that such
                    a pretence could be<lb/> nothing less than want of sincerity.-
                    <del>men</del><lb/> -mention was then made of the several<lb/> Treaties
                    concluded since the establishment<lb/> of the Independance of the United States,
                    and<lb/> of the new settlements made in consequence<lb/> of those treaties, and
                    of the impossibility of<lb/> removing such a great number of Families<lb/> from
                    their habitations and Farms; and<lb/> therefore, in the most explicit terms
                        <del>de-</del><lb/><del>clared</del> declared that the United States
                    could<lb/> not agree that the<geogName key="ohior"> River Ohio</geogName> should
                    be<lb/> the boundary line.- In the next place<lb/> the Commissioners
                    acknowledged that very<lb/> improper Language had been held out at<lb/> former
                    Treaties, when it had been said that<lb/> the United States claimed all the
                    Indian Coun<lb/>-try, (within certain limits mark'd out by<lb/> the Treaty of
                    Peace with the British) as a con-<lb/>quer'd Country.- The Commissioners<lb/>
                    <pb n="73" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_42"/> therefore, in the clearest terms, now
                    relin-<lb/>-quishd all such claim, reserving only the<lb/> preemption, or
                    exclusive right of purchasing<lb/> of the Indians.- The Commissioners then<lb/>
                    express'd their desires to meet the Indians in<lb/> full Council, and a belief
                    that if such <del><gap/></del><lb/><del><unclear>work</unclear></del> a thing
                    could be done, and a friendly<lb/> conference take place, a satisfactory and
                    lasting<lb/> Peace would be the consequence - They<lb/> concluded with
                    intimating that for the<lb/> sake of an accommodation they would be<lb/> willing
                    to give up all the Land to the N.W. of the<lb/>
                    <geogName key="ohior">Ohio</geogName>, excepting such only as were
                    absolutely~<lb/> appropriated, and, for such as were appropri-<lb/>-ated, a
                    generous compensation should be<lb/> paid down, and a yearly Rent allowed<lb/>
                    forever.- The answer was interpretted<lb/> paragraphically as it was read, and
                    then<lb/> the whole writing given to the Indians.</p>
                <p> -The old Wiandot Chief who delivered the<lb/> message yesterday, got up and
                    said, as the<lb/>sun was going down they would consider of what was said by<lb/>
                    the Commissioners <del>answer</del> and speak a few<lb/> words to them in the
                    Morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-01">8 mo. 1</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <pb n="74" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_43"/>
                <p> - The Indians came over about<lb/> 7 oClock in the morning, and having met
                    the<lb/> Commissioners in Council - the old Chief<lb/> who spoke last night
                    arose, and said, they<lb/> perfectly understood all that was said to them<lb/>
                    yesterday, and had only to say, that in<lb/> regard to the several Treaties
                    mentioned<lb/> yesterday, they did not acknowledge any of<lb/> them to be valid,
                    and as the Commissioners<lb/> had said they could not remove the white<lb/>
                    People over the River, so they, the Indians,<lb/> could not consent to give up
                    any of their<lb/> Country, and concluded with saying,<lb/> they came as Men
                    wishing for Peace,<lb/> but as that could not be obtained, they<lb/> should
                    return to their Council, and speak<lb/> to their warriors:- And as for the
                    Commissioners.<lb/> they <del>the Indians</del> had nothing more to say to<lb/>
                    them, they might go home, and tell <del>the</del><lb/><del>President</del>
                    Washington what the Indians had said.-</p>
                <p> -After the Indians had retired a few minutes,<lb/>
                    <persName key="sgirt1">Simon Girty</persName> their interpretter, and several
                    of<lb/> their Chiefs, came back, and said, there had<lb/> been a mistake in the
                    last part of the -<lb/>
                    <pb n="75" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_43"/> speech - that the business of the
                    Deputies<lb/> was to carry the Commissioners answer to the<lb/> Great Council,
                    and they desired the Comissnrs.<lb/> would wait a few days for a final
                    answer.</p>
                <p> -The Indians then immediately took their<lb/> leave, and <persName key="tmcke1"
                        >Thos. McKee</persName>, about 11 oClock also<lb/> set off for the <geogName
                        key="miamr">Miami</geogName>, and as the prospect of meeting<lb/> the
                    Indians at a general Treaty now<lb/> appears very faint, Friends concluded to
                    forward<lb/> the address to the Indians, agreed upon the <date when="1793-07-17"
                        >17th</date> ulto. <del><unclear>ultimus</unclear></del><lb/> by him, under
                    cover to his Father <persName key="cmcke1">Col. McKee</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-02">2nd</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Being a pleasant day walk'd about four<lb/> miles down the Lake - the place
                    where we are<lb/> encamp'd is the property of <persName key="melli1">Capt.
                        Matthew Elliott</persName>,<lb/> on which is a handsome convenient
                    House,<lb/> and a very large new Barn - the Land appears<lb/> to be of an
                    excellent quallity both for Grass and<lb/> every kind of Grain.- He has a large
                    stock of<lb/> fine Cattle, among which are 12 yoke of Oxen,<lb/> and I counted
                    31 Calves and 43 milch Cows<lb/> - they are just now geting in the last of<lb/>
                    their Harvest, the wheat and oats have suffer'd<lb/> much from prodigious flocks
                    of Black Birds,<lb/>
                    <pb n="76" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_44"/> notwithstanding the vigilence of
                    several<lb/> who were continually upon the watch to keep<lb/> them off - The
                    Indian Corn is begining to<lb/> be fit for Roasting, and it is the business
                    of<lb/> one hand to watch the Birds, who have<lb/> already done great damage in
                    the field.</p>
                <p> --The Black Birds, we are told, are equally<lb/> mischievious in all parts of
                    the Country.</p>
                <p> --Came down, and <del>sail'd the Sloop</del> anchor'd<lb/> opposite our
                    Encampment, the Sloop Detroit<lb/> from <placeName key="michi"
                        >Michilimackanac</placeName> bound to <placeName key="ferie">Fort
                        Erie</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-03">3d</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> This morning intended going in a Canoe<lb/> about 4 miles up the River to a
                    Wiandot<lb/> Village, but the wind blowing hard from<lb/> the S.W. prevented
                    us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-04">4th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Heavy rain last night, and all this<lb/> morning untill Hoon - in the
                    afternoon<lb/> had a Meeting at the House of <persName key="sgirt1">Simon
                        Girty</persName><lb/> about 5 oClock.- about 11 A.M. the Chipeway<lb/>
                    pass'd by on her way from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName> and
                        <geogName key="miamr">Miami<lb/> River</geogName>, bound to Detroit - She
                    sent on Shore<lb/> a Packet for the Commissioners from Philadelp<emph
                        rend="superscript">a</emph><lb/> among its contents were News Papers as<lb/>
                    late at the <date when="1793-06-25">25th of the 6th month</date>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="77" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_44"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-05">5th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>

                <p> The Wind moderated, and Weather<lb/> clear'd away, - sail'd the Sloop Detroit for<lb/>
                    <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-06">6th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About 2 oClock P.M. departed this Life a<lb/> poor Indian Slave who belonged to
                        <persName key="melli1">M. Elliott</persName>.</p>
                <p> --There is a Nation far to the westward,-<lb/> called Panies, or <orgName
                        key="pawnee">Pawnees</orgName>, with whom, it is said,<lb/> the <orgName
                        key="ojibwe">Chippeway's</orgName> are at perpetual war, - it<lb/> was a
                    Custom formerly among these barbarous<lb/> Nations to put all their prisoners to
                    Death,<lb/> but since their acquaintance with the<lb/> White People these
                    prisoners are become an<lb/> article of Traffic, and sold to the Traders,
                    --<lb/> who again dispose of them to the Settlers,<lb/> by this means Indian
                    Slaves are become<lb/> numerous, and all, however acquired, go<lb/> under the
                    denomination of <orgName key="pawnee">Pawnees</orgName>. --</p>
                <p> -The poor fellow above mentioned was a <orgName key="pawnee"
                    >Pawnee</orgName><lb/> and had for a long time been in a declining way,<lb/> but
                    was so well this morning as to be able to walk<lb/> about the Door - he died at
                    2 in the afternoon and<lb/> was put in the Grave about 7 the same evening -<lb/>
                    -The burial was attended by most of the Commissioners<lb/> retinue, and
                        <persName key="jmoor3">J.M.</persName> spoke a few words at the Grave<lb/>
                    well adapted to the occasion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="78" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_45"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-07">7th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>

                <p> This day the Commissioners were furnished<lb/> with a few ripe Water Melons,
                    being the first I<lb/> have seen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-08">8th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> The wind blew hard from the Eastward<lb/> the greatest part of the last night,
                    attended<lb/> with Rain- this Wind we hope will hasten<lb/> the arrival of a
                    Vessell from <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, by whom<lb/> a Person
                    is expected from Philadelphia that<lb/> was sent there an Express by the
                    Commissioners<lb/> from <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>.- Some of our
                    company kill'd<lb/> one of the small black Rattle Snakes - there<lb/> skin is
                    much darker than the large sort, -<lb/> they seldom exceed the length of 18
                    inches, and<lb/> have but two or three Rattles - there bite, <del>is</del><lb/>
                    is said to be very venomous, much more<lb/> so than that of the larger kind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-09">9th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Last night arrived two of the <orgName key="stockbridge">Stockbridge<lb/>
                        Indians</orgName> with letters from <persName key="haupa1"
                        >Hendrick</persName> their Chief, <del>with</del><lb/> by which we were
                    informed that there seem'd to be<lb/> a disposition in the Indian Council to
                    admit<lb/> the Commissioners to a Treaty, and giving it<lb/> as his opinion that
                    a Peace would be soon<lb/> established.- We are further told that the<lb/> place
                    of Treaty is like to be altered from<lb/>
                    <pb n="79" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_45"/>
                    <placeName key="sandu">Sandusky</placeName> to the mouth of the <geogName
                        key="miamr">Miami</geogName>, and<lb/> that a Deputation from the Council
                    may be<lb/> expected <del>to</del> this day or tomorrow, who <del>were</del> are
                    to give<lb/> a favourable answer to the Commissioner's Speech<lb/> and attend
                    them to the place of Treaty - about<lb/> 10 oClock a Canoe with 7 <orgName
                        key="ojibwe">Chipewa Indians</orgName> from<lb/> the Council, arrived here
                    on their way home.<lb/> --these people confirm the intelligence we received<lb/>
                    last night, and we are again fill 'd with the pleasing<lb/> hope that this
                    tedious and expensive Embassy will<lb/> not be altogethe fruitless.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-10">10th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Warm and sultry - anxiously waiting the<lb/> return of the Indians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-11">11th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> This morning arrived the Ottaway from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, in her came <persName key="jparr2"
                        >Jasper Parrish</persName> who was<lb/> sent an Express by the Commissioners
                    from <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName><lb/> to <placeName key="phila"
                        >Philadelphia</placeName>. - he brought Letters for most of<lb/> our
                    friends, and News Papers as late as the<lb/>
                    <date when="1793-07-20">20th</date> of last month.- The <orgName key="ojibwe"
                        >Chippeway</orgName> also came<lb/> down from Detroit, bound to <placeName
                        key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>, and anchor'd<lb/> near our Encampment.­
                    Friends had a Meeting<lb/> this afternoon at <geogName key="grosi">Gros
                        Isle</geogName>, at which I was not<lb/> present.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Since we have been upon this spot we have<lb/> experienced from a certain class
                    of Men, a treatment<lb/>
                    <pb n="80" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_46"/> very different from the generous
                    politeness received<lb/> from their brethren at Detroit, but have a hope<lb/>
                    that their ungenerous aspersions has not injured<lb/> us individua1ly or brought
                    any reproach upon the<lb/> Society at large -- may their rude and
                    ungenerous<lb/> attempts serve to keen us more upon our guard<lb/> and watchful
                    over those weaknesses, which doubtless<lb/> are more or less, the portion of
                    human nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-13">13th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> In the Ottaway arrived <persName key="cwilb1">Captain Wilbank</persName><lb/>
                    who came from the Southward with a party of<lb/> Indians, as beforementioned he
                    this day<lb/> Dined with the Commissioners, and confirm'd<lb/> what was noted as
                    coming from him on the<lb/>
                    <date when="1793-07-18">18th of last month</date>, and gave a more full
                    in-<lb/>-formation of the complaints of the Southern<lb/> Indians, and of <emph
                        rend="underline">the attempts of the Spaniards</emph> to<lb/> foment the
                    difference subsisting between them<lb/> and the United tates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> In the forepart of last night had a<lb/> sudden and heavy fall of rain which
                    made<lb/> our Tents very uncomfortable for the remainder<lb/> of the night.- The
                    Commissioners growing<lb/> impatient at the delay of the Indians, sent<lb/> off
                    an Express to the Council in order<lb/> to hasten their answer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="81" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_46"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>

                <p> Two Wiandots from the other side inform<lb/> us that an Indian from the Council
                    arrived<lb/> last night at their Village with intelligence that<lb/> there had
                    been great debates among them <del>res</del><lb/> respecting the answer to be
                    return'd to the<lb/> Commissioners The <orgName key="shawnee"
                    >Shawnese</orgName>, <orgName key="delaware">Delawares</orgName>, <lb/>
                    <orgName key="wyandot">Wiandots</orgName> and <orgName key="miami"
                        >Miami</orgName>'s being for war, and<lb/> the Six Nations, on the Contrary,
                    peacably inclined,<lb/> that finally the Six Nations had prevail'd and<lb/>
                    messangers were to be dispatched three Nights<lb/> ago with a favourable answer,
                    and an invitation<lb/> for the Commissioners to come forward.- One of<lb/> the
                        <orgName key="wyandot">Wiandots</orgName> abovementioned was a White
                    Man<lb/> taken by the Indians in his infancy, he cannot<lb/> speak a word of
                    English, <del>he can give no</del> or give any account<lb/> of his Family; and
                    only remembers that his<lb/> Name was Honnes - His Ears were cut, and<lb/>
                    himself, in all respects, dress'd &amp; ornamented<lb/> in the Indian stile -
                    dullness and stupidity<lb/> seemed to be spread over his Countenance, and<lb/>
                    his whole appearance could not but raise<lb/> emotions of sorrow and
                    commiseration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-16">16th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> About 4 P.M. the long look-for answer<lb/> arrived which at once put an end to all<lb/>
                    <pb n="82" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_47"/> to all hopes of a Peace at present -
                    the<lb/> substance of this lengthy reply, which fill'd<lb/> near two sheets of
                    Paper was, that no consi-<lb/>-deration would induce the Indians to<lb/> give up
                    their Country, and nothing short<lb/> of making the <geogName key="ohior"
                        >Ohio</geogName> the boundary could give<lb/> them satisfaction, and if the
                    Commissioners<lb/> could not agree to this there would be no use<lb/> in meeting
                    at a Treaty - The answer was<lb/> signed, it is said, by sixteen Nations,
                    being<lb/> all that were present except the Six<lb/> Nations, who all refused
                    their concurrence<lb/> and are favourably disposed towards the<lb/> United
                    States.- About 8 P.M. the two<lb/> young <orgName key="onondaga"
                        >Onondaga</orgName>'s return'd who were<lb/> sent express by the
                    Commissioners, as<lb/> mentioned the <date when="1793-08-14">14th</date>, they
                    brought no<lb/> written reply, and could give very little in-<lb/>formation,
                    except that they delivered their<lb/> message to <persName key="cbran1">Capt.
                        Brandt</persName> the <orgName key="mohawk">Mohawk</orgName> Chief,<lb/> who
                    informed that an answer to the Commissnr.<lb/> Speech was already gone down, the purport<lb/>
                    <pb n="83" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_47"/> of which he was intirely unacquainted
                    with,<lb/> as he, with the rest of the Six Nations, were<lb/> not admitted into
                    the Council - Thus ends<lb/> a business in which, it is too probable, the
                    fate<lb/> of thousands are involved, - should there be<lb/> any, who from
                    interested motives, or mis-<lb/>-taken policy, have endeavoured to retard<lb/>
                    the work of Peace, and promote the horrid<lb/> consequences attendant upon War,
                    what<lb/> will they not have to answer for!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-17">17th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> Struck our Tents and embarked our<lb/> Baggage and Stoves on board the
                    Dunmore-<lb/> -the Wind being strong from the S.W., it<lb/> was 4 in the
                    afternoon before we got under<lb/> way, when we work'd down with the-<lb/>
                    current into the Lake - in the evening<lb/> we were about 10 miles from the
                    place<lb/> of our departure.- the wind about South.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-18">18th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p> The wind shifting last night to the N.E. brought<lb/> us up to the <geogName
                        key="bassi">Bass Islands</geogName> this morning, where we<lb/> came to an
                    anchor in Pudding Bay about 7 oClock,<lb/> being 40 miles from the mouth of
                        <geogName key="detror">Detroit River</geogName>­ about<lb/>
                    <pb n="84" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_48"/> about 10 A.M. the wind shifted round
                    to<lb/> N.N.W., we made sail, and run through the<lb/> Islands - in the
                    afternoon it fell calm, at<lb/>6 in the evening we were about 10 miles
                    below<lb/>the Islands.­ This being <del>the</del> first day
                        <del>p<unclear/></del><lb/> (and just 10 weeks since we passed the same
                    Islands)<lb/>Friends had a Meeting in the Cabbin, which was<lb/>in the main a
                    satisfactory time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-19">19th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Little wind all the last night, mostly<lb/> from the N.E. - this morning
                    almost<lb/>calm, the <geogName key="bassi">Bass Islands</geogName> still in
                    sight -<lb/>light airs of wind all Day from the Northward<lb/>- we made but
                    little progress.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-20">20th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Last night about 10 a fresh breeze<lb/>sprung up from the N. N. W. which
                    conti-<lb/>nued untill this morning - the fore part<lb/>of the Day calm - at 1
                    P.M. a breeze sprung<lb/>up about N.B.E. about which time a Vessell<lb/>hove in
                    sight a stern of us which we<lb/>suppose to be the Ottaway bound to <placeName
                        key="ferie">Fort<lb/>Erie</placeName> - at 4 P.M. close in with the
                    Land<lb/>near the mouth of Elk River on the South<lb/>side of the Lake, - tack'd
                    and stood to<lb/>the Northward</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-21">21st</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <pb n="85" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_48"/>
                <p>A small breeze from the Eastward<lb/> all night, - in the morning the
                    South<lb/>Shore in sight - the Ottaway about 2<lb/>Leagues to Leeward - at 2 P.M
                    the Land<lb/>on both sides the Lake in sight <del>and
                        the</del><lb/><del><gap/></del> - at 4 P.M. the Ottaway<lb/>abreast of us,
                    about half a mile to an<lb/>Windward. - the Wind N.N.E.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-22">22nd</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>The wind last night hauld round to <del>them</del>
                    <del>Sou</del><lb/>South, and continued a fresh breeze untill<lb/>morning - Our
                    Course E.N.E. - The Ottaway<lb/>on our Lee bow about 4 Leagues distant<lb/>- the
                    Land in sight on both sides the Lake<lb/>- at 10 A.M opposite Long Point, from
                    whence<lb/> over to the opposite Shore, near <placeName key="presq">Presq
                        Isle</placeName>, the<lb/>distance is about 12 Leagues - at 2 P.M.<lb/>
                    calm, no land to be seen to the Northward<lb/> - at 4 P.M.a breeze sprung up
                    about<lb/>South, which increased and blew<lb/> fresh in the Evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-23">23d</date>. <placeName key="ferie"/></dateline>
                <p>About 1 A.M. anchor'd at <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName> - the<lb/>
                    wind blowing hard all day made it very difficult<lb/>to Land which prevented our
                    making much progress<lb/>in preparing to get on our way to <placeName
                        key="niaga">Niagara</placeName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="86" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_49"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-24">24th</date>. <placeName key="ferie"/></dateline>

                <p>Disposed of most of our spare Stores - <persName key="grand1">Govr.<lb/>
                        Randolph</persName> and <persName key="cpick1">Col. Pickering</persName>
                    crossd over to<lb/><geogName key="buffc1">Buffaloe Creek</geogName>, intending
                    to go through the Genesee<lb/>Country down to New York. <persName key="jparr1"
                        >J.Parrish</persName>, <persName key="jlind1">Ja.<lb/> Lindley</persName>,
                        <persName key="jmoor3">J. Moore</persName>, &amp; <persName key="jelli1">J.
                        Elliott</persName>, also took their<lb/>leave of us, intending to proceed
                    through the<lb/>woods to <placeName key="phila">Philad</placeName>. - <persName
                        key="glinc1">General Lincoln</persName>, <persName key="cstor1">Ch.<lb/>
                        Storer</persName>, <persName key="jheck1">J.Heckenvelder</persName>,
                        <persName key="wmcco1">Dr. McCoskry</persName>, <persName key="wsave1"
                        >Wm.<lb/> Savery</persName> &amp; myself, intending to go by the
                    way<lb/>Montreal to New York.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-25">25th</date>. <placeName key=""/></dateline>
                <p>Procured Batteaux in which we put our<lb/>Baggage and embark'd about 9 oClock
                    down<lb/>to <geogName key="chipp">Chippeway Creek</geogName>, within two miles
                    of the<lb/>Great Fall, where we arrived about one - <lb/>after Dinner <persName
                        key="jheck1">J.Heckenvelder</persName> &amp; myself went<lb/>to take a
                    second view of the Falls, we went<lb/>down by Birch's Mill, and along under
                    the<lb/>Hill to Table Rock, opposite the <geogName key="niagf">Falls</geogName>,
                    J.H. being<lb/>fatigued would go no further, I procured a guide<lb/>and went
                    about a mile below to a place where<lb/><del>we f<unclear/></del> by the help of
                    Indian Ladders we<lb/>decended down to the waters edge, and went<lb/> along upon
                    the broken Rocks up to the<lb/>Falls - The River to the Eastward of the
                    Island<lb/>I suppose to be 250 yards wide, the lower end<lb/>
                    <pb n="87" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_49"/> of the Island, and the River to the
                    Westward of <del>the</del><lb/>it, I suppose to be each of the same width, -</p>
                <p>After spending some time in viewing this<lb/>wonderful sight, we ascended the
                    hill and walk'd<lb/>about three miles, where we got Lodgings and<lb/>tarried all
                    Night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-26">26th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Walk'd down to the Landing where we found<lb/><persName key="glinc1">General
                        Lincoln</persName>, <persName key="wsave1">Wm. Savery</persName> &amp; some
                    others who came<lb/> in a Waggon last night - about noon our<lb/>
                    <pb n="88" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_50"/> our Baggage arrived and was deposited
                    in<lb/> the Kings Store.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-27">27th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>A Light Breeze of wind from the Westward,<lb/> we could hear the roaring of the
                    Falls uncommonly<lb/>loud, the distance being seven miles. - We<lb/>hear there
                    is a Vessell at Navy Ha11 bound to<lb/><placeName key="kings"
                        >Kingston</placeName>, but it is thought she will be detain'd<lb/> untill
                    they hear from <persName key="gsimc1">Governor Simcoe</persName> who<lb/> is on
                    the opposite side of the Lake at Torento--<lb/><del><gap/></del></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-28">28th</date>. <placeName key="nav"/></dateline>
                <p>Procured a Batteau and went down<lb/>to Navy Hall, and were accommodated<lb/>with
                    the Governor's empty House - the<lb/>evening being calm could distinctly
                        <del>clearly</del> hear<lb/> the roaring of the Falls as I lay in
                    Bed,<lb/>the distance 18 miles</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-29">29th</date>. <placeName key="nav"/></dateline>
                <p>Arrived the Missesaga, a Kings <del>Scho</del><lb/> Schooner, from Toronto, by
                    her we learn<lb/> that the Gun Boat, in which <persName key="cbunb1"
                        >Captain<lb/>Bunbury</persName> was a Passenger, who left this<lb/>place the
                        <date when="1793-08-23">23rd</date> was not arrived at 7 oClock<lb/>last
                    evening - as the wind blew hard<lb/>the night after she sail'd, we are
                    fearful<lb/>some accident has befallen her. - The<lb/>
                    <pb n="89" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_50"/> Sloop Caldwell being ready to Sail for
                        <placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName><lb/>and there being a prospect
                    of a Wind, we<lb/> got all our Baggage on board this evening</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-30">30th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>At 4 A.M. embark'd on board the<lb/>Vessell abovementioned, Commanded
                        by<lb/><persName key="cpaxt1">Captain Paxton</persName>, and left <placeName
                        key="niaga">Niagara</placeName> with<lb/>a fair Wind, bound for Kingston at
                    the<lb/> entrance of the <geogName key="stlar">River St. Lawrence</geogName>, -
                    having<lb/>a fresh breeze all Day, about 8 P.M were<lb/>a breast of <placeName
                        key="longp">long Point</placeName> on the North sides<lb/> of the Lake 100
                    miles from <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-08-31">31st</date>. <placeName key="kings"/></dateline>
                <p>This morning about 5 oClock pass'd<lb/>by the Islands call'd the Ducks, - Course from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName> to the Islands about E.N.E.,
                    from<lb/> thence to <placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName> about N.b.E. -
                    from the<lb/> Islands to <placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName> 28 m. whole
                    distance<lb/>150 miles - At 10 oClock, anchor'd at<lb/><placeName key="kings"
                        >Kingston</placeName>, formerly Fort Frontenac. - here<lb/>is a Fort and
                    small Garrison, the Town consists<lb/>of a few scattering Houses, and the Land
                    in<lb/>the neighbour'd appears to be very Stoney and<lb/> poor. - A Batteau
                    being procured we left<lb/><placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName> about 1
                    P.M., and having a fair<lb/>wind, run all Night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="90" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_51"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-01">9 mo. 1st.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>

                <p>Went on Shore this morning<lb/>about 6 and breakfasted at a Tavern<lb/>three
                    miles above <placeName key="osweg1">Oswegatche</placeName>, being 72<lb/>miles
                    from <placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName>. - The River <geogName
                        key="stlar">St.<lb/>Lawrence</geogName> for about 10 Leagues
                        below<lb/><placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName> has no current, and
                    but<lb/>a very gentle one the remainder<lb/>of the way to <placeName
                        key="osweg1">Oswegatche</placeName>; from thence<lb/>it begins to be very
                    rapid. - in the<lb/>afternoon we pass'd the Rapids call'd<lb/>the Long Sue, and
                    about 6 oClock enter'd<lb/>
                    <geogName key="laksf">Lake St. Francis</geogName>, which is 7 Leagues<lb/>in
                    length and <del>2 wide</del> two in breadth.<lb/> - at 10 we were overtaken with
                    a<lb/> violent squall of Wind and Rain; and<lb/> with difficulty got to land on
                    the N.W.<lb/> side, about 14 miles from the N.E. end<lb/> of the Lake, where we
                    left our Boat and<lb/>made up a fire on this Shore, and<lb/>spent a very
                    uncomfortable Night</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-02">2nd.</date>
                    <placeName key="lachi"/></dateline>
                <p>A fresh Breese from the Westward<lb/> - embark'd about 6 A.M. and at 8 landed<lb/>
                    <pb n="91" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_51"/> at Mclntire's at the N.E. end of the
                    Lake<lb/> where we got a little refreshment and then<lb/>proceeded on our way
                    down the River, - about<lb/>one pass'd the Rapids of the Cedars, and<lb/>at 4
                    arrived at <placeName key="lachi">La Chine</placeName>, where we took<lb/>up our
                    Quarters at Grants Tavern, &amp; tarried<lb/>all Night</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-03">3rd.</date>
                    <placeName key="montr"/></dateline>
                <p>Sent on two Carts with our Baggage<lb/>and about 9 A.M., in three Calathes,
                    set<lb/>off for <placeName key="montr">Montreal</placeName>, where we arrived
                    in<lb/>about an hour &amp; a half. - Distance from<lb/>
                    <placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName> to <placeName key="montr"
                        >Montreal</placeName> 200 miles - In the<lb/>afternoon that we left
                        <placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName> we run<lb/>about 30 miles before
                    dark, and in all that<lb/>distance saw but very few settlements, the<lb/>Land
                    appearing very rough and poor - the<lb/>next morning at day light, when we
                    were<lb/>about <del>60</del> 60 miles from <placeName key="kings"
                        >Kingston</placeName>, we found<lb/>the N.W. side of the River thickly
                    inhabited,<lb/> which continued to be the case all the way<lb/>down to <geogName
                        key="laksf">Lake St. Francis</geogName>, the improvements<lb/>are new, and
                    the inhabitants mostly Loyalists<lb/>
                    <pb n="92" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_52"/> and emigrants from different
                    quarters,<lb/> - after we got below the boundary Line<lb/> which strikes the
                    water somewhere on <geogName key="laksf">Lake<lb/> St.Francis,</geogName> we
                    found improvements on<lb/>both sides, but the N.W. side of the Lake<lb/>being
                    low and Marshy <del>swampy</del> had but few settle­<lb/>ments, <del>on</del>
                    the S.E. side appeared more<lb/>pleasant, and better cultivated. -
                    The<lb/>Country on both sides the River, below<lb/>the Lake, is thickly
                    inhabited, especially<lb/> on the West side, where the Land appears<lb/>to be
                    fertile and well improved. - The<lb/> Rapids in this River are not easily
                    de-<lb/>scribed, - those of Long Sue, and the Cedars<lb/>are the most
                    remarkable, in one of<lb/>which we went 3 Leagues in 35 minutes<lb/> and
                        <del>the</del> in the other the same distance<lb/>in 40 minutes.- Opposite
                        <placeName key="lachi">La Chine</placeName>,<lb/>which is 9 miles from
                        <placeName key="montr">Montreal</placeName>, is a<lb/>large Indian Town, the
                    Houses appear'd<lb/>to be commodious &amp; well built, a large<lb/>Church, or
                    Chappel, standing in the Town,<lb/>and another building of the like kind, 3 or<lb/>
                    <pb n="93" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_52"/> four miles from it. - <placeName
                        key="lachi">La Chine</placeName> is a<lb/> Village situated on the same
                    Island on<lb/>which <placeName key="montr">Montreal</placeName> is built, to
                    this place all<lb/>Goods intended for the Western Trade is<lb/>brought by Land
                    from <placeName key="montr">Montreal</placeName>, &amp; from<lb/>thence sent by
                    Batteaux, Canoe's &amp;c in<lb/>many directions into the Indian Country.<lb/>-
                    in the <geogName key="stlar">River St.Lawrence</geogName>, between <placeName
                        key="kings">Kingston</placeName><lb/>and <del>the</del>
                    <geogName key="laksf">Lake St. Francis</geogName> are a vast mul-<lb/>titude of
                    Islands, most of which are small,<lb/>barren, and Rocky. - The Country
                    in<lb/>the Neighborhood of Montreal appears<lb/>to be very thickly inhabited,
                    fertile &amp;<lb/> pleasant. - The Town is about half<lb/> the size of
                        <placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName>, the buildings
                    <del>mo</del><lb/> mostly of stone, some of the Houses<lb/>are roof'd with Tin
                    plates, and in<lb/>general are pretty well built, - some<lb/>of the Streets are
                    commodious and well<lb/>paved, - it appears to have a plentiful<lb/>Market, and
                    provision, in general,<lb/> about the same price as in <placeName key="nycit"
                        >New York</placeName><lb/>
                    <pb n="94" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_53"/> - after dining at <placeName key="montr"
                        >Montreal</placeName> we cross'd<lb/>the River at Longuiel Ferry,
                    intending<lb/>to proceed on our way to <geogName key="lakec">Lake
                        Champlain</geogName><lb/> immediately, but it being in the heigth
                    of<lb/>their Oat Harvest, we were disappointed<lb/>in getting Carriages, and
                    were obliged<lb/>to take up our Quarters at the Ferry-<lb/>House for the
                    Night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-04">4th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>We were provided with Carriages &amp;<lb/> about 6 in the morning set off for<lb/>
                    <placeName key="stjoh">St. Johns</placeName>, in our way pass'd by <placeName
                        key="fcham">Fort<lb/> Chamblee</placeName>, in which is a Garrison,
                    and<lb/>about 12 oClock arrived at <placeName key="stjoh">St.John's</placeName>,
                    the<lb/>distance being 27 miles. - <placeName key="fcham">Chamblee</placeName>
                    is<lb/>situated at the foot of the Rapids of the<lb/>River Sorrell, which runs
                    out of <geogName key="lakec">Lake<lb/>Chamblain</geogName>, at <placeName
                        key="stjoh">St. Johns</placeName>, into the <geogName key="stlar"
                        >River<lb/>St. Lawrence</geogName>, from <placeName key="fcham"
                        >Chamblee</placeName> to <placeName key="stjoh">St. Johns</placeName><lb/>
                    is a carrying place of about 12 miles, the<lb/>road very good. - about 5 P.M.
                    embark'd<lb/>on board a Boat of about 9 Tons burthen,<lb/>Sloop rigg'd, and
                    Deck'd, it being almost<lb/>
                    <pb n="95" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_53"/> Calm, got only 5 miles on our way,
                    and<lb/> went on Shore, at a very ordinary Public House<lb/>where we tarried all
                    night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1793-09-05">5th</date>. <placeName key="ileau"/></dateline>
                <p> Embark'd about about 7 A.M. - the wind<lb/>being ahead, we work'd up about 9
                    miles<lb/>to a Tavern One mile below the <geogName key="ileau">Isle
                        aux<lb/>Noix</geogName>, where we put up for the Night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-06">6th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Set off about 7 A.M., had to stop and<lb/>give an account of ourselves at the
                    Fort on<lb/> the <geogName key="ileau">Isle aux Noix</geogName> - the Wind
                    coming fair<lb/>about 11 oClock we got up the Lake to where<lb/>the boundary
                    Line intersects it in 45° of<lb/> N. Lattitude, - the Country on the East
                    side<lb/>of the Lake appears pleasant &amp; fertile, &amp; thickly<lb/>settled
                    on both sides of the Line, - on the<lb/>West side also are many settlements,
                    but<lb/>not so flourishing as on the East. - about<lb/>One oClock pass'd the
                    Brittish Garrison on Point<lb/>au Fair, and also the Kings Schooner
                    laying<lb/>in the Lake opposite to it, to both of which<lb/>the master of the
                    Boat was obliged to give<lb/>some account of himself and his Cargo.</p>
                <pb n="96" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_54"/>
                <p>-- at 4 P.M. we arrived at Cumberland<lb/>head in the State of New York, where
                    a<lb/> Custom House is established, here also,<lb/>our little Vessell underwent
                    another <del>exa</del><lb/> examination.- Our Skipper being<lb/>very ill with
                    the Ague &amp; Fever, desired<lb/>to be left here, and gave up the
                    manage-<lb/>ment of his Boat to the Passengers, &amp; a<lb/> little Boy about 14
                    or 15 Years of Age, as a Pilot.<lb/> - the wind being fair and blowing
                    very<lb/>fresh we were loth to loose it, &amp; ventured<lb/>to push on, being
                    told we could make<lb/>a harbour at Gillilands Creek about 20<lb/>miles further
                    up the Lake, at which<lb/>place we arrived about 8 in the evening,<lb/>but in
                    attempting to go in we found a<lb/> Bar quite a Cross the Creeks mouth,
                    on<lb/>which we got a Ground,<lb/> and the wind<lb/>blowing fresh, with a pretty
                    high Sea<lb/>we struck hard, - it was with a good<lb/>deal of difficulty that we
                    got our Boat off<lb/>which when we had accomplished, not <lb/>
                    <pb n="97" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_54"/> liking to trust any longer to our pilot,
                    we<lb/>came to an Anchor, pretty much exposed<lb/>to the Wind and Sea, and
                    pass'd a very<lb/> uncomfortable Night, having 12 Men and<lb/>one Woman on
                    board.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-07">7th.</date>
                    <placeName key="checkPlace"/></dateline>
                <p>As soon as day light appear'd we made<lb/>sail, and run 12 miles to <placeName
                        key="basin">Bason harbour</placeName>,<lb/> on the Vermont side where we
                    breakfasted<lb/>- at 9 oClock pass'd the old <placeName key="fcrow">Fort of
                        Crown<lb/>Point</placeName>, 12 miles from <placeName key="basin">Bason
                        harbour</placeName> - at 3 P.M<lb/>pass 'd through the Piers opposite the
                    remains<lb/>of <placeName key="ticon">Ticonderoga</placeName>, and at 7 in the
                    evening got<lb/>up to cold spring, a public Hquse within 8<lb/>miles of
                        <placeName key="skene">Skeensborough</placeName>. - The Shores of
                    this<lb/>Lake are mostly high and bold, and the<lb/>Country on both sides has by
                    far a pleasanter<lb/>appearance than any we saw on the<lb/>upper Lakes - there
                    are settlements all<lb/>round <geogName key="lakec">Lake Champlaine</geogName>,
                    those towards<lb/>the North end, and in general, on the East,<lb/>or Vermont
                    Side, appear to have the <del>pre</del><lb/> preference - At the South end of
                    the Lake, on<lb/>
                    <pb n="98" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_55"/> on both sides, the Country is very
                    Rocky<lb/> and Mountainous - From <placeName key="ticon"
                    >Ticonderoga</placeName><lb/>to <placeName key="skene"
                    >Skeensborough</placeName>, the distance of 25 miles,<lb/> the Lake is like a
                    narrow River, with<lb/>very high Cliffs on both sides, in some<lb/> places much
                    resembling the High Lands<lb/> on <geogName key="hudsr">Hudsons
                    River</geogName>. - About 12 miles below<lb/>
                    <placeName key="skene">Skeensboroug</placeName> the River is contracted
                    between<lb/>large Bodies of Marsh, which continue<lb/>nearly all the way up, -
                    among these<lb/><del>Swam</del> Marshes were great numbers of<lb/> Ducks of
                    different kinds, but mostly<lb/>what are call'd Wood Ducks</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-08">8th.</date>
                    <placeName key="skene"/></dateline>
                <p>We arrived at <placeName key="skene">Skeensborough</placeName> about<lb/>11
                    oClock, the distance being 150 miles<lb/> from <placeName key="stjoh">St.
                        Johns</placeName> - at <placeName key="skene">Skeensborough</placeName>
                    are<lb/>fine Mills upon the Falls of <geogName key="wcree">Wood
                    Creek</geogName><lb/>where it empties into the east end of<lb/><geogName
                        key="lakec">Lake Champlain</geogName>, - the Land, in general<lb/>very rough
                    &amp; Mountainous, in which<lb/>are some fertile Vallies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-09">9th</date>. <placeName key="sarat"/></dateline>
                <p>Having procured two waggons to bring<lb/>our Baggage, six of us set off about 7<lb/>
                    <pb n="99" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_55"/> in the Stage Waggon for <placeName
                        key="alban">Albany</placeName>. - We<lb/>pass'd the remains of <placeName
                        key="fann">Fort Ann</placeName> &amp; <placeName key="fedwa">Fort<lb/>
                        Edward</placeName>, the first 11, the latter 24 miles from<lb/><placeName
                        key="skene">Skeensborough</placeName>, - about 8 in the evening<lb/>arrived
                    at <placeName key="sarat">Saratoga</placeName> on the <geogName key="nrive"
                        >North River</geogName>, 35 miles from <placeName key="skene"
                        >Skeensbugh.</placeName><lb/> and 36 miles from <placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-10">10th</date>. <placeName key="alban"/></dateline>
                <p>We left <placeName key="sarat">Saratoga</placeName> about 6 A.M.and
                        reach'd<lb/><placeName key="lansi">Lansingburg</placeName> about 2 P.M.
                    where we dined,<lb/> - our ride this morning has been all the<lb/>way in a very
                    pleasant Road on the banks<lb/>of <geogName key="hudsr">Hudsons River</geogName>
                    - we pass'd through <del>so</del><lb/>some beautiful Villages, particularly
                    the<lb/>half Moon, or Waterford, on the west side<lb/>of the River, about a Mile
                    above <placeName key="lansi">Lansing-<lb/>bourg</placeName>, which is situated
                    on the East side,<lb/>they both appear to be places of considerable<lb/>Trade,
                    and from the number of new buildings<lb/>erecting, very rapidly increasing in
                    size<lb/>and beauty, - the same may be said<lb/>of <placeName key="troy"
                        >Troy</placeName> which stands a few miles below<lb/>
                    <placeName key="lansi">Lansingbourg</placeName> on the same side of the
                    River<lb/> where we again Ferried over and arrived at<lb/><placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName> about 5 oClock - <placeName key="lansi"
                        >Lansingbourgh</placeName> 9 m. from <placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="100" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_56"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-11">11th.</date>
                    <placeName key="alban"/></dateline>

                <p>Our Baggage arrived this afternoon<lb/>and was put on board the Sloop Vley,
                        <persName key="cmars1">Capt.<lb/>Marseilles</persName>, who expects to sail
                    tomorrow for<lb/><placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-12">12th</date>. <placeName key="alban"/></dateline>
                <p>Left <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> about 10 oClock, with a<lb/>fine
                    wind, and very shortly after, ran<lb/>aground upon the Oversloughs about<lb/>two
                    Miles below, where all our <del>exert</del><lb/>exertions to get off this Tide
                    proved in<lb/>vain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-13">13th</date>. <placeName key="checkPlace"
                    /></dateline>
                <p>Not being able to get the Vessell off at<lb/>high water last night, this
                    morning<lb/>made a Raft of the boards upon Deck<lb/>by which means and a great
                    deal of<lb/> labour got <del>off</del> a float and run down<lb/>over the shoals,
                    and came to an Anchor<lb/> in order to take in our Raft of Boards.<lb/> - about
                    4 P.M. again made sail,<lb/>the Wind, which for several days past<lb/>has been
                    strong from the Northward, is<lb/>now almost done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-14">14th</date>. <placeName key="redho"/></dateline>
                <p>Light airs of wind from the southwd.<lb/> - pass'd <placeName key="huds"
                        >Hudson</placeName> in the Night, which is<lb/>
                    <pb n="101" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_56"/> 30 miles from <placeName key="alban"
                        >Albany</placeName> - at 8 A.M. opposite<lb/><placeName key="catsk1"
                        >Katskill</placeName> on the west side of the River 40 miles<lb/> from
                        <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName>, - in the evening lay at <geogName
                        key="redho">Red<lb/> Hook wharf</geogName>, on the East side of the River
                    45<lb/>miles from <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-15">15th</date>. <placeName key="pough"/></dateline>
                <p>Small breeses of Wind still from the S.ward<lb/> - in the Morning found ourselves
                    at Anchor<lb/>opposite <placeName key="esopu">Usopus</placeName>, on the West
                    side, 100 miles<lb/> from New York, - work'd down with the Ebb.<lb/> and
                    anchor'd in the evening about 4 miles<lb/>above <placeName key="pough"
                        >Poughkeepsie</placeName>, on the East side, which<lb/> is call'd half way
                    from <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> to <placeName key="nycit">New
                        York</placeName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-16">16</date>. <placeName key="westp"/></dateline>
                <p>Wind the same as Yesterday - in the<lb/>morning we lay along side a Lime
                    Kiln<lb/> wharf opposite the mouth of <geogName key="wappi">Wappings
                            <del>Cr</del><lb/>Creek</geogName>, <del>6 miles below Newburgh</del> -
                    about 1 oClock<lb/> pass'd <placeName key="newbu">Newburg</placeName> on the
                    West side of the River,<lb/> opposite to which on the east side of the River
                    is<lb/> the Fish Kills - <placeName key="nwind">New Windsor</placeName> lays
                    about one<lb/> mile below <placeName key="newbu">Newburgh</placeName>, on the
                    same side<lb/>of the River - two or three miles below <del>New W</del><lb/>
                    <placeName key="nwind">New Windsor</placeName>, we enter the High Lands,
                    &amp;<lb/> anchor'd during the Flood, about 2 miles above<lb/><placeName
                        key="westp">West Point</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
                <pb n="102" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_57"/>
                <dateline><date when="1793-09-17">17th</date>. <placeName key="nycit"/></dateline>

                <p>Having a strong Current in<lb/>the Night we pass'd, <placeName key="westp">West
                        Point</placeName>, and<lb/><placeName key="stony">Stoney Point</placeName>,
                    Forts, and got clear of the<lb/>High Lands about 4 o'clock in the Morning<lb/>at
                    which time we were overtaken with<lb/>a heavy squall of wind &amp; Rain from
                    the<lb/> Northward - about 8 we were opposite<lb/><placeName key="tappa"
                        >Tappan</placeName> - the wind still continuing we<lb/> arrived at
                        <placeName key="nycit">New York</placeName> about 1 in the<lb/>afternoon</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="appendix">
                <note>Following the Journal are 33 blank pages. and then 3 pages and the back cover.
                    upon which is written the following</note>
                <pb facs="SW_WH1793_Page_58"/>
                <pb n="122" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_59"/>
                <p><date when="1793-06-22">1793<lb/> June 22</date></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>paid <persName key="mdols">Matthew Dolson</persName> Accd<lb/> for
                            board diet &amp;c. 6 weeks</cell>
                        <cell>£13.9.--</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb n="123" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_59"/>
                <p>The perpetual Almanack<lb/>Is governed by the day on which the 3d mo<lb/>comes
                    in</p>
                <table cols="8">
                    <row>
                        <cell>AD</cell>
                        <cell>3 mo<lb/>begins</cell>
                        <cell>AD</cell>
                        <cell>3 mo<lb/>begins</cell>
                        <cell>AD</cell>
                        <cell>3 mo<lb/>begins</cell>
                        <cell>AD</cell>
                        <cell>3 mo<lb/>begins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1750<lb/>60<lb/>64<lb/>68<lb/>72<lb/>76<lb/>80<lb/><lb/></cell>
                        <cell>2<lb/>7<lb/>5<lb/>3<lb/>1<lb/>6<lb/>4<lb/><lb/></cell>
                        <cell>1784<lb/>88<lb/>92<lb/>93<lb/>94<lb/>95<lb/>96<lb/>97<lb/></cell>
                        <cell>2<lb/>7<lb/>5<lb/>6<lb/>7<lb/>1<lb/>3<lb/>4<lb/></cell>
                        <cell>1798<lb/>99<lb/>1800<lb/>1<lb/>2<lb/>3<lb/>4<lb/>5<lb/>6</cell>
                        <cell>5<lb/>6<lb/>1<lb/>2<lb/>3<lb/>4<lb/>6<lb/>7<lb/>1</cell>
                        <cell>1807<lb/>8<lb/>9<lb/>10<lb/>11<lb/>12<lb/>13<lb/><lb/></cell>
                        <cell>2<lb/>4<lb/>5<lb/>6<lb/>7<lb/>2<lb/>3<lb/><lb/></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table cols="7">
                    <row>
                        <cell>3 mo</cell>
                        <cell>8 mo</cell>
                        <cell>5 mo</cell>
                        <cell>10 mo</cell>
                        <cell>7 mo</cell>
                        <cell>9 mo</cell>
                        <cell>2 mo</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>11 mo</cell>
                        <cell>---</cell>
                        <cell>1 mo</cell>
                        <cell>---</cell>
                        <cell>4 mo</cell>
                        <cell>12 mo</cell>
                        <cell>6 mo</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb n="125" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_59"/>
                <p>It is a matter of perfect indifference whither<lb/>the Potatoes employed as Sets,
                    be whole or cut<lb/>in pieces; but that a variation in the<lb/>size of the Sets
                    planted, always affects<lb/>the amount of the Crop in a very remark-<lb/>able
                    degree, the largest sets in all Cases<lb/>producing the greatest Crops<lb/>
                    English Review <date when="1788-08">Octo. 1788.</date></p>
                <pb n="126" facs="SW_WH1793_Page_59"/>
                <p>Distance from New York<lb/>to Albany...165</p>
                <table cols="3">

                    <row>
                        <cell>From <placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName> to <placeName
                                key="schen">Schenectady</placeName>...</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>to <placeName key="fstan">Fort Stanwix</placeName> by Water...</cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><geogName key="oneil">Oneida Lake</geogName>...do...</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="fbrewl">Fort Brewerton</placeName>-----<lb/>entrance
                            Onondago River...do</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="osweo">Oswego</placeName>, by Water...</cell>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline">36</emph></cell>
                        <cell>238</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="niaga">Niagara</placeName>, along shore...</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>....</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName>, up <geogName key="lakee"
                                >Lake Erie</geogName>....</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline">285</emph></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>884</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                
                <p>From <placeName key="detro">Detroit</placeName></p>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell>to <placeName key="ferie">Fort Erie</placeName>....</cell>
                        <cell>285</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="niaga">Niagara....</placeName></cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="kings">Kingston</placeName>, or Frontenac...</cell>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="montr">Montreal</placeName>...</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="stjoh">St. Johns</placeName>...</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="skene">Skeensborough</placeName>...</cell>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="alban">Albany</placeName>...</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><placeName key="newyo">New York</placeName>...</cell>
                        <cell><emph rend="underline">165</emph></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1084</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
